<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ladies' Aid Society cook book</title>
            <editor>Madeleine + Moses</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This edition was created as part of the TXTDS 404/504 course at the University of
               Washington</p>
            <p>Special care was put into transcribing the text presented here as diplomatically as
               possible. This edition was created with the intention of providing historical
               recipies for readers for a variery of purposes, be it a study of ingredients
               available, culinary culture of the early 20th century, and kitchen technology.</p>
            <p>Origionally, the source text contained full page advertisments on every other page,
               akin to what is seen in Victorian serials. These have been omitted from our edition,
               as we felt that they were extranious information and rather that the effort should be
               put into including as many recipies as possible.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The Ladies' Aid Society cook book is an instructional text divided into the following
               sections: Soups, Fish, Meats, Vegetables, Bread, Relishes, Salads, Pies, Cakes,
               Puddings, tables of weights and measure, Candies, and an unnamed section containing
               recipes for household fluids. Each section contains different recipes. First, we
               transcribed ten different pages of recipes from various sections. After some of these
               recipes, there is a name of a person who contributed the recipe to the cookbook. The
               page numbers are at the bottom of each page. Also, since everything is organized
               similarly, we planned to reflect this in our transcription. Finally, we have written
               a diplomatic transcription since our text is so sparse and modern. <bibl>
                  <title>Ladies' Aid Society cookbook</title>
                  <author>Unknown. This was likely a collaborative effort among a group of
                     people.</author>
                  <publisher>Vincent Methodist Episcopal Church, in Spokane, WA</publisher>
                  <date>1915</date>
                  <idno type="OCLC">950973749</idno>
               </bibl>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>A great way to engage in and learn much about a historical period can come from cuisine
            and the foods people used to prepare and eat. The Ladies’ Aid Society cook book was
            published by the Vincent Methodist Episcopal Church in Spokane, WA, in 1915. It is an
            interesting text because this is not only a cookbook but also a kind of guidebook for
            homemakers of the time. It is an instructional text divided into sections one might find
            in a typical cookbook, such as Soups, Fish, Meats, Vegetables, Bread, Relishes, Salads,
            Pies, Cakes, Puddings, tables of weights and measure, and Candies. An unnamed section
            also contains recipes for household fluids like library paste. At the end of some of
            these recipes, there is a name of a person who contributed the recipe to the cookbook.
            The original copy also contains full-page advertisements on every other page, akin to
            what is seen in Victorian serials, with advertisements promoting products and businesses
            of the local community.</p>
         <p>We created a digital version of this text because we believe anyone interested in
            cuisine, food, and the history of the early 20th century would be curious about this
            text and to bring about a new appreciation for this unique text from the Special
            Collections of the University of Washington Library. If anyone wants to know how food
            played a role in the history and culture of the time, they would be interested in this
            book. Because the original text is so modern and sparse, special care was put into
            transcribing the text presented here as diplomatically as possible. This edition was
            created to provide historical recipes for readers for various purposes, be it a study of
            ingredients available, the culinary culture of the early 20th century, or kitchen
            technology. Even though the text has full-page advertisements on every other page, these
            have been omitted from our edition, as we felt that they were extraneous information and
            rather that the effort should be put into including as many recipes as possible.</p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="section" n="Handwritten notes">
            <p>Beets. sugar. milk. nuts. oranges. lemons. butter. eggs. meat. candy.</p>
            <p>Sift baking powder in flour 5 tablespoons melted butter 1 coffee cup sugar creamed
               together 2 eggs nutmeg to taste 3 teaspoons baking powder heaping 2 coffee cups milk
               added Eggs + sugar + butter About 2 quarts flour added almost at once</p>
            <note>this section is hand written addition, and is not an official part of the printed
               text</note>
            <note>the list is likley a shopping list</note>
            <note>im adding something here to test the push. please edit out later</note>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="Soups">
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="bold">NORMANDY SOUP.</head>
               <p>One knuckle veal, 3 quarts cold water, 1 onion, ½ loaf baker’s bread, 1 quart
                  cream, 2 tablespoonfuls butter, 2 tablespoonfuls flour. Put veal and onion on in
                  cold water, let simmer 2 hours. Then add bread cut in slices, let simmer 2 hours
                  longer. Remove meat and press the other ingredients through sieve. Rub butter and
                  flour together, stir into boiling soup. Add cream, salt, and pepper.</p>
               <p><name type="person" ref="#M._F._Mendenhall">—Mrs. M. F. Mendenhall.</name></p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="bold">SPLIT PEA SOUP.</head>
               <p>Two cups split peas, add 3 pints water and clean piece of bacon rind or small
                  piece of bacon or ham; teaspoon salt, pepper to taste, small onion, small carrot.
                  Boil all at least 3 hours. If preferred run through colander.</p>
               <p><name type="person" ref="#John_R._Corkery">—Mrs. John R. Corkery</name></p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="bold">GERMAN POTATO SOUP.</head>
               <p>A 10-cent shin bone, add 4 quarts water , boil 3 hours , cool and skim off fat,
                  then put back on stove and add small handful salt, 1 dried chili pepper or black
                  pepper to taste, 1 large onion, 2 medium sized carrots, small amount of cabbage or
                  turnip, some dried celery or fresh, 8 good sized potatoes. Boil all at least 1
                  hour and then run through colander and serve with bread croutons.</p>
               <p><name type="person" ref="#John_R._Corkery">—Mrs. John R. Corkery.</name></p>
               <note>The "10-cent shin bone" is likley just a refrence to the expected price of the
                     ingredient.<ref target="#Food_Timeline"/></note>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="bold">SHRIMP SOUP.</head>
               <p>Scald 1 quart milk in double boiler. Add 1 tablespoonful flour, 1 yolk egg mixed
                  with a little milk. When cooked and ready to serve add 1 cup minced shrimps, 1
                  tablespoon grated cheese, white 1 egg whipped, salt and pepper to taste.</p>
               <p><name type="person" ref="#McCreary">—Mrs. McCreary.</name></p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="fish">
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="bold">MINCED CLAM PATTIES.</head>
               <p>One can of minced sea clams, 2 cupfuls off cream or milk, 3 tablespoonfuls flour,
                  2 eggs, 1 tablespoonful butter, salt and pepper (to taste). Put in a stew pan or
                  chafing dish the cream and clam juice and let come to a boil. Then add the eggs
                  well beaten , salt, pepper, butter and clam meat. When this is hot thicken with
                  the flour dissolved in a little milk or water. Pour into pastry patties and serve
                  hot.</p>
               <p><name type="person" ref="#E.C._McRae">—Mrs. E.C. McRae.</name></p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="bold">SHRIMP PIRLEAU.</head>
               <p>One teacup rice, ½ lb. bacon diced, 1 cup chopped onion, ½ can tomatoes, 1 lb.
                  shrimp meat, 1 teaspoon beef extract, 1 teaspoon flour, ¼ lb. red pepper, 1
                  teaspoon celery seed. Cook rice until dry. Cook bacon and onion together. Then mix
                  all together and cook one hour.</p>
               <p><name type="person" ref="#Bruce_Blake">—Mrs. Bruce Blake</name></p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="bold">SALMON LOAF.</head>
               <p>One-half cup milk, 1 can salmon, ½ cup bread crumbs, 2 eggs well beaten, little
                  chopped parsley, little mace, salt and pepper to taste. Turn into greased mold and
                  steam 1 hour.</p>
               <p><name type="person" ref="#Joseph_Briggs">—Mrs. Joseph Briggs.</name></p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="bold">SCALLOPED FISH.</head>
               <p>Boil 2 lbs. halibut in a cloth with 1 slice onion, 1 stalk celery, 1 sprig
                  parlsey, 1 bay leaf, 4 cloves and juice ½ lemon. Separate fish from bone. Cut in
                  buttered baking dish with laternate layers of white sauce made of 1 cup milk, 1
                  tablespoon flour, 1 tablespoon butter. Heat in oven.</p>
               <p><name type="person" ref="#A._B._Lee">—Mrs. A. B. Lee</name></p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="bold">PIGS IN BLANKETS.</head>
               <p>Sifter of flour; 4 teaspoons baking powder, 1 teaspoon salt; 2 tablespoons
                  shortening; water or milk to make biscuit dough. Take 25 cents’ worth of link
                  sausage and cut each link apart; roll our dough ¼ inch thick and cut in pieces;
                  put one link of sausage in dough and cover all of sausage. Bake in oven, as
                  biscuits. Do not place many in a pan, as they rise. Enough for 6 persons.</p>
               <note>Again, this section is transcribed diplomatically. This recipe is misplaced in
                  the Fish sction of the origional document, an editorial mistake as it was likley
                  meant to be placed in the proceeding Meats section.</note>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="section" n="Meats">
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="bold">HAM EN CASSEROLE.</head>
               <p>Select a slice of ham about 2 inches thick; dredge with flour and saute brown in
                  its own fat. Brown 2 sliced onions in this fat, also a carrot scraped and sliced.
                  Place the ham in the casserole, cover with the vegetables, add 1 turnip, pared and
                  cut into small cubes. Add ½ teaspoon of pepper; then pour on a cupful of boiling
                  water, cover and cook for 3 hours in a moderate oven; half an hour before the
                  cooking is finished, add a cupful of strained tomatoes.</p>
               <p><name type="person" ref="#B._L._Jenkins">—Mrs. B. L. Jenkins</name></p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="bold">STEAMED HAM.</head>
               <p>Steam good sugar cured ham 30 minutes to the pound. Cover on all sides with sugar.
                  Put into baking pan and add extra sugar on top and around it. Add 1 pint of water
                  and bake until the water and sugar have formed a thick syrup. Put ham on platter
                  and pour the syrup over it. Surround with rings of pineapple sauted in butter.
                  Varnish with parsley.</p>
               <p><name type="person" ref="#J._K._Cecil">-Mrs. J. K. Cecil.</name></p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="bold">"DOBE" MEAT.</head>
               <p>One large onion browned in tablespoonful of lard, 1 teaspoonful of cinnamon, 1
                  dozen cloves, pepper and salt to taste, ½ cup sugar, ½ cup tomatoes. Rub your pan
                  with garlic. When onions are browned, flour your meat, put in a pan, add other
                  ingredients and cook slowly in an over for 2 hours.</p>
               <p><name type="person" ref="#Newman">—Mrs. Newman.</name></p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head rend="bold">CASSEROLE OF RICE AND MEAT.</head>
               <p>Cook rice until tender in salted water. Butter a mold and line it ½ inch or more
                  with the rice. Fill the center with the following: 2cups finely chopped cold
                  cooked meat, 1 beaten egg, ¼ cup cracker or bread crumbs, salt, pepper, celery
                  salt, onion juice, sage, nutmeg, or lemon juice depending on the variety of meat,
                  hot stock or water to moisten. Pack the meat in the rice lined mold. Cover the top
                  with riceand cover the rice with buttered paper to keep out the moisture. Steam ¾
                  of an hour. Serve with tomato sauce. Potato may be used in place of rice.</p>
               <p><name type="person" ref="#A._D._Butler">—Mrs. A. D. Butler.</name></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="Vegetables">
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">STUFFED PEPPERS.</head>
                  <p>Six green peppers, remove seeds amd led stand in hot water ½ hour; 1 cup
                     chopped meat or oysters, 1¼ cups bread crumbs, ½ cup tomatoes, ½ onion
                     (chopped), 1 tablespoon parsley (chopped), salt, 1 egg. Fill peppers. Pour over
                     stock and bake ⅓ hour.</p>
                  <p><name type="person" ref="#Rutter">—Mrs. Rutter.</name></p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">MEXICAN CORN.</head>
                  <p>Two green peppers (chopped), ½ onion (chopped), fry in butter, then add 1
                     tablespoon flour, 1 egg (beaten), 1 cup milk, 1 cup corn, ½ cup Mexican beans,
                     cooked, salt and pepper, paprika. Pour in buttered dish, covered with
                     bread-crumbs and bake in oven ½ hour.</p>
                  <p><name type="person" ref="#J._E._Daniel">—Mrs. J. E. Daniel.</name></p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">CABBAGE AU GRATIN.</head>
                  <p>Cut medium sized cabbage and cook in boiling salted water to cover until
                     tender. Chop moderately and season with pepper, salt if necessary, and 1 green
                     pepper pr pimento finely chopped. Cover with 1¼ cups thin white sauce, add 1-3
                     cup grated cheese, mix well and sprinkle thickly with ¾ cup buttered crumbs.
                     Place in oven and baker until mixture is heated through and crumbs are
                     browned.</p>
                  <p><name type="person" ref="#Glen_Powell">—Mrs. Glen Powell</name></p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">STUFFED PEPPERS(MEXICAN STYLE).</head>
                  <p>Parboil peppers from which seeds have been removed, stuff with cold minced meat
                     and bread crumbs, to which add a few raisins; dot the top with butter and bake
                     half an hour.</p>
                  <p><name type="person" ref="#Mathers">—Miss Mathers.</name></p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">CORN PUDDING</head>
                  <p>Eight ears corn scored down center, thne scraped; 1 tablespoon butter, 1 cup
                     milk, 1 teaspoon flour, 3 ggs beaten light. Bake ¾ hour.</p>
                  <p><name type="person" ref="#W._S._McCrea">—Mrs. W. S. McCrea.</name></p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">SPANISH RICE.</head>
                  <p>Two slices of bacon, cut into small pieces and fried nicely brown; add 2 cups
                     water, 1 cup rice, 1 onion, ½ can tomatoes, 1 chile pepper; cook 30
                     minutes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="Bread">
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">CREAM DATE ROLES.</head>
                  <p>Two cups pastry flour, ½ teaspoon salt, 4 teaspoons Royal baking powder, 1
                     tablespoon butter, 1 cup cream (all measurements level), dates.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="bold">Process:</hi> Sift dry ingredients together; rub in butter with
                     fingers. Add cream, mix with spatula to soft dough. Handle lightly. Roll on
                     floured board to 1-3 inch thickness. Cut with biscuit cutter; place ½ a stoned
                     date on ½ biscuit, brush edges with milk, and fold as Parker House rolls. Press
                     edges together, brush top of rolls with milk, place ½ date on top. Bake about
                     15 minutes.</p>
                  <p>Cheese Biscuit may be made by substituting grated cheese for dates in above
                     recipe, and are delicious.</p>
                  <p><name type="person" ref="#E._F._Waggoner.">-Mrs. E. F. Waggoner.</name></p>
                  <note>A "Parker House roll" is a variety of bread roll made by rolling the dough
                     into an oval shape and then folding them in half. They were invented at the
                     Parker House Hotel in Boston in the 1870s.</note>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">>BROWN BREAD</head>
                  <p>Mix together 1 teaspoonful salt, 2 teaspoonfuls soda (level), pinch ginger. Add
                     1 cup molasses 2 cups sweet milk, 3¼ cups graham flour, ½ cup raisins. Steam 3
                     hours, then bake 10 minutes.</p>
                  <p><name type="person" ref="#Wm._Merryweather">-Mrs. Wm. Merryweather.</name></p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">POTATO MUFFINS.</head>
                  <p>Two cups mashed potato, 1 cup warm milk, 1 cake compressed yeast, 2 eggs well
                     beaten, 1 tablespoon lard, 1 tablespoon sugar, 1 teaspoon butter, salt to
                     taste, 3 cups flour. Set then at 11 o’clock. Roll at 4 and bake at 6.</p>
                  <p><name type="person" ref="#E._Taylor">—Mrs. E. Taylor.</name></p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">NUT BREAD.</head>
                  <p>One cup sour milk, 1 cup sweet milk, 2 cups whole wheat or graham flour, 1 cup
                     white flour, 1 cup sugar (scant), 1 teaspoon baking powder, 1 teaspoon soda, 1
                     teaspoon salt, ½ cup raisins and ½ cup walnuts chopped.</p>
                  <p><name type="person" ref="#W._H._Matthews">—Mrs. W. H. Matthews.</name></p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="Relishes">
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">ORANGE MARMALADE.</head>
                  <p>Take 1 dozen oranges, peel very thin (cut peel fine); remove all the white and
                     slice oranges thin, add 2 qts. of cold water. Let stand for 24 hours, cook
                     until tender, then add 8 lbs. sugar, juice of 4 lemons and boil at least 1 hour
                     longer.</p>
                  <p><name type="person" ref="#M._K.">–M. K.</name></p>
                  <note>Interestingly, this is the only submission with a name that does not have a
                     gendered title. All other recipes submissions with attached names have
                     explicitly feminine titles such as miss or mrs. This segmentation is to be
                     expected, as the setting of the early 20th century and only recent urbanization
                     of Spokane at the time both would have reinforced more tradtional western
                     gender roles.</note>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">PEACH CONSERVE.</head>
                  <p>Six pounds peaches (diced), 1 can pineapple (diced), 3 oranges, peel of 1
                     orange, 6 cups sugar. Make a thick syrup of the sugar. Into this, drop the
                     peaches and cook for 10 minutes. Cook the orange peel until tender and shred.
                     Then add the pineapple, oranges and peel to the peaches, and cook for 5 minutes
                     more.</p>
                  <p><name type="person" ref="#J._D._Ellis">-Mrs. J. D. Ellis.</name></p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">RHUBARB CONSERVE.</head>
                  <p>Five pounds rhubarb, 5 lbs. sugar, 3 oranges, 1 small tablespoon ground ginger,
                     1 lb. walnut meats. Prepare rhubarb as for stewing peel and slice oranges fine,
                     add sugar and ginger and cook until quite thick. Take off and add the nuts
                     (chopped). Prunes can be used instead of rhubarb. Put them through grinder
                     before cooking.</p>
                  <p><name type="person" ref="#Mae_Jones">—Mrs. Mae Jones.</name></p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">INDIAN PEACH PICKLES.</head>
                  <p>Seven pounds fruit, 3 pounds sugar, 1 pint vinegar. Heat vinegar, sugar, and
                     teaspoon whole allspice and cloves and several pieces of mace (these three
                     spices tied in cloth), 1 tablespoon stick cinnamon. Pour over uncorked peaches,
                     heating and pouring over peaches for 9 days. The last day cork peaches few
                     minutes. Boil down syrup and pour over peaches.</p>
                  <p><name type="person" ref="#A._E._Blake">—Mrs. A. E. Blake.</name></p>
                  <note>It is unclear whether the term "indian" here is a refrence to the country in
                     southern Asia or to the Indigenous peoples of the US.</note>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">GRAPE CONSERVE.</head>
                  <p>Three pints Concord grapes, 3 pints granulated sugar, 1 pint water, ½ pound
                     seeded raisins, 2 oranges chopped fine, 1 cup chopped walnuts added last. Pulp
                     grapes and cook pulps. Put through colander. Add skins and other inregdients
                     and cook 1 hour.</p>
                  <p><name type="person" ref="#May_Jason">—Mrs. May Jason.</name></p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="Salads">
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">PINEAPPLE AND TOMATO SALAD.</head>
                  <p>On a lettuce leaf place a ring of pineapple, then a slice of ripe tomato; put
                     on a spoonful or two of mayonnaise dressing and garnish with a salted cherry or
                     stuffed olive.</p>
                  <p><name type="person" ref="Mrs._B._L._Jenkins">-Mrs. B. L. Jenkins.</name></p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">POTATO SALAD.</head>
                  <p>Six large boiled potatoes cut in cubes, 1 onion cut fine, 3 hard boiled eggs
                     chopped. Mix with this dressing ½ cup sugar, ½ cup vinegar, ½ cup water, 1
                     tablespoon flour, 1 tablespoon butter, 3 ggs. Mix well and cook in double
                     boiler. When cool add cream.</p>
                  <p><name type="person" ref="Dana Child">-Mrs. Dana Child.</name></p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">SALAD DRESSING FOR TEN PEOPLE.</head>
                  <p>One-half cup vinegar, ½ cup butter, ½ cup sugar, 4 eggs. Boil all together
                     until thick. Add 1 cup thick, sour cream. Let stand a minute. Pour over 12
                     large potatoes, 8 hard-boiled eggs and 1 small onion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">FRUIT SALAD DRESSING.</head>
                  <p>One-fourth cup fruit juice (pineapple)m juice of ½ lemon, ¼ cup sugarm yolks of
                     2 eggs. Cook slowly and cool before serving.</p>
                  <p><name type="person" ref="F._H._Quilliam">-Mrs. F. H. Quilliam</name></p>
                  <note>The seemingly put of place "m"s are present in the origional text and have
                     been transcribed here diplomatically</note>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">HOT POTATO SALAD.</head>
                  <p>Boil 6 or 8 potatoes without paring and dice while hot; peel and chop 1 large
                     onion and mix with potato; cut up some breakfast bacon into small bits
                     sufficient to fill a teacup and fry it a light brown; remove the meat, and into
                     the grease stir 3 tablespoonsful of vinegar, making a sour gravy, which, with
                     the bacon pour over the potato and onion; mix lightly. To be eaten hot.</p>
                  <p><name type="person" ref="J._E._Horton">-Mrs. J. E. Horton.</name></p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">SALAD DRESSING.</head>
                  <p>Mix together 1 teaspoon of salt, 1 teaspoon of dry mustard, 2 tablepsoons of
                     sugar, 1 tablespoon of flour. To this add the yolks of 2 eggs, well beaten, 2
                     tablespoons of melted butter, 1 cup sweet milk and ½ cup vinegar, the latter
                     added slowly. Cook in double boiler, stirring constantly until thick. This will
                     keep for weeks.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="Pies">
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">PINEAPPLE PIE.</head>
                  <p>Fill a rich, flaky crust with the following: In a double boiler put the liquid
                     of a can of shredded pineapple with two (2) cups of water, bring to a boil. Add
                     five (5) tablespoons corn starch, dissolved in a liter of water, yolks of four
                     (4) eggs, one and one-half (1½) cups of sugar, butter size of a walnut. When
                     cool add the shredded pineapple. Fill crust with this mixture. Uhe the whites
                     of the eggs for meringue, beaten with two (2) tablespoons sugar. Brown lightly
                     in oven. This recipe makes two (2) large pies.</p>
                  <p><name type="person" ref="A._M._Johnson">-Mrs. A. M. Johnson.</name></p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">WALNUT PIES.</head>
                  <p>Boil together until thick, yolks of 3 eggs, 1 cup sugar, 1 cup milk, 1 heaping
                     teaspoon flour. Let cool and add a cup of chopped walnuts, then turn into baked
                     pie crust, use whites for top.</p>
                  <p><name type="person" ref="H._A._Flood">-Mrs. H. A. Flood.</name></p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">DIVINITY PIES.</head>
                  <p>Whites of 3 eggs, beaten to a stiff froth; 1 tablespoon sugar, stirred into the
                     whites of eggs; put eggs and sugar into the crust (baked the day before) and
                     bake a short time; let cool, take ½ pint of whipping cream, beat to a stiffness
                     and tdd 2 tablespoons sugar and spread over pie. Flavor to taste.</p>
                  <p><name type="person" ref="Glenn_Russell">-Mrs. Glenn Russell.</name></p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">APPLE CUSTARD PIE.</head>
                  <p>One cup stewed apple, mashed very fine; 2 eggs, 1 cup sugar, ⅓ cup butter. Bake
                     with one crust and use the whites of the eggs for frosting after the pie is
                     done. Brown nicely by returning to oven.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">PUMPKIN PIE.</head>
                  <p>One and one-half cups stewed pumpkin, dry; 2 cups milk, 2 beaten eggs, ½ cup
                     brown sugar, 1 teaspoon cinnamon, ½ teaspoon each of sale and ginger. Line pie
                     tins and bake in slow oven.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">RHUBARD PIE.</head>
                  <p>One cup rhubarb, chopped fine 1 cup sugar, 1 egg. Bake in two crusts. Flavor
                     with lemon if desired.</p>
                  <note>correction: this recipie is recorded diplomatically, including the
                     mispelling of "rhubarb" as "rhubard"</note>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="Cakes">
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">NUT CAKES.</head>
                  <p>One-half cup butter, 1 cup sugar, 3 eggs, ½ cup milk, 1¾ cups flour, 3
                     teaspoons baking powder, 1 teaspoon flavoring, ¾ cup of nuts (walnuts or
                     pecans) broken in small pieces Mixin usual manner and bake in small pans.</p>
                  <p><name type="person" ref="Chas_L._Featherstone">-Mrs. Chas L.
                        Featherstone.</name></p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">DATE CAKE.</head>
                  <p>One pound dates (after stoning), 1 pound English walnut meats, 1 cup flour, 2
                     rounded teaspoons baking powder, ½ teaspoon salt, 1 small cup sugar, 4 eggs
                     beaten separately, teaspoon vanilla. Bake in loaf.</p>
                  <p><name type="person" ref="G._W._Paine">-Mrs. G. W. Paine.</name></p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">DELICIOUS PORK CAKE.</head>
                  <p>Two cups solid fat pork (ground fine), 2 cups boiling water (pour over pork), 2
                     cups sugar, 2 cups New Orleans molasses, ½ pound currants, ½ pound raisins, ¼
                     pound pound citron and lemon peel, 1 cup chopped nuts, 3 teaspoons soda,
                     dissolved in boiling water, cloves, cinnamon, nutmeg, to taste. Mix quite stiff
                     with flour and bake for 1¼ hours with a steady fire. Will keep
                     indefinitely.</p>
                  <p><name type="person" ref="A. _E._Keats">-Mrs. A. E. Keats.</name></p>
                  <note>At the time of publication, most homes had either a wood stove or a range,
                     which used natural or coal gas. The "steady fire" mentioned here could be in
                     refrence to fire in a wood stove, or possibly that the submiter was invisioning
                     that people would could this over the hearth,, which had only recently gone out
                     of style.<ref target="#Cookstove_Community"/></note>
                  <note>The citron mentioned here was not a common ingredient, and instead other
                     citruses like lemons or oranges were commonly used. When citrons are mentioned
                     though, it is often candied or in sweeter baked goods such as this.</note>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">SPICE CAKE.</head>
                  <p>One egg, 1 cup sugar, ½ cup butter, 1 cup sour milk, 1 teaspoon soda, 2⅔ cups
                     flour, all spices as desired.</p>
                  <p><name type="person" ref="Z._Stewart">-Mrs. Z. Stewart.</name></p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head rend="bold">AUNT EMMA'S FRUIT CAKE.</head>
                  <p>One and one-half cups light brown sugar, ⅔ cup butter, 2 eggs, ½ cup sour milk,
                     scant 2½ cups flour, ⅔ cup raisins, ⅔ teaspoon soda, 2 tablespoons cut citron
                     or ¼ cup chopped nuts.</p>
                  <p><name type="person" ref="Emma_Till">-Mrs. Emma Till.</name></p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div/>
         <div/>
         <div/>
         <div/>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="biliography">
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Seattle_Times" n="1" type="webpage">
                  <author>Daniel Newman</author>, <title>A delicious decade: The food of
                     1910-1920</title>
                  <publisher>Seattle Times</publisher>
                  <date>2016</date>
                  <ref
                     target="https://www.seattletimes.com/life/food-drink/a-delicious-decade-the-food-of-1910-1920/"
                  />
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Cookstove_Community" n="2" type="webpage">
                  <author>Michael Umphrey</author>
                  <title>Foodways in 1910</title>
                  <publisher>The Montana Heritage Project</publisher>
                  <date>2004</date>
                  <ref target="https://cookstoves.net/articles/cookstove-history/foodways-1910/"/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Food_Timeline" n="3" type="digital_book"><author>Frances Stern and
                     Gertrude Spitz</author>
                  <title>Food for the Worker</title>
                  <publisher>Witcomb and Barrows</publisher>
                  <date>1917</date>
                  <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                  <ref target="https://www.foodtimeline.org/1917prices.pdf"/></bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="American_Cookery" n="4" type="digital_book"><author>Amelia
                     Simmons</author>
                  <title>American Cookery</title>
                  <publisher>Hudson and Goodwin</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Hartford</pubPlace>
                  <date>1796</date>
                  <ref target="http://www.fullbooks.com/American-Cookery.html"/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Wikipedia" n="5" type="webpage">
                  <title>Spokane, Washington</title>
                  <publisher>Wikipedia</publisher>
                  <date>edited 2024</date></bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
