<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="teibp.xsl"?>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Harlequin and Friar Bacon</title>
            <author>Francesco Frost</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Bonnie Ha, Cassidy Fallon Vierling, Echo Yu</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Seattle, WA</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>University of Washington, Seattle</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2024-02​-XX</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>We were able to read the pamphlet in the collection classroom located on the base level
            of Allen Library North. 
               <bibl>
                  <title>Harlequin and Friar Bacon</title>
                  <author>Francesco Frost</author>
                  <publisher>The Music-Publishing Company</publisher>
                  <date>1863 </date>
                  <pubPlace>London: 19 Peter's Hill, St. Paul's</pubPlace>
               </bibl>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>
            <p>Editorial notes in the 1863's edition have not been reproduced</p>
         </samplingDecl>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization method="silent">
               <p>Original punctuation conventions in the 1863's edition will be retained as much as possible</p>
            </normalization>
            <interpretation>
               <p>Italics will be recorded without interpretation</p>
            </interpretation>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition>caps, italics, bold</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>“Harlequin and Friar Bacon” is a British pantomime play from the collection of Glenn Hughes who used the collection in the 1930s and 1940s as a tool for research and teaching his students in the drama program at the University of Washington. It comes from a collection of over 3,000 plays, the majority British. It is likely that “Harlequin and Friar Bacon” belongs to the subset within the collection of works added from a single contributing collection, all of which were made as sales or gifts to the audience of a performance, mainly consisting of Christmas extravaganzas, pantomimes, and burlesques. Pantomimes are usually performed around Christmas and are comedies that often include slapstick humor, jokes, innuendos, magic, fairies, and gender reversal.</p>
	 <p>The focus of our edition of “Harlequin and Friar Bacon” is digitizing the original play to become accessible to actors and students who are interested in its content, whether that be for purposes of studying drama or gleaning an understanding of the content of historical plays. Pantomimes are still performed in the United States but with less frequency and popularity than in England, so the edition will also function to introduce actors to studies of plays on a global scale.</p>
	 <p>Our edition features a transcription which is intended to maintain as much of the original content as possible, including preserving the British spellings for words as opposed to Americanizing them. Racial slurs have been redacted and given note in the end notes if relevant to understanding the passage. Any italics and bold are preserved as they are displayed in the original play. In the original print, advertisements line the jacket and are interspersed throughout the text, which have not been preserved in this digital edition because it is not intended for viewing by audiences but by actors.</p>
         <div type='editorial'>
            <listPerson>
               <!-- GT: good! Is this a cast list? You could also use the TEI element <castList>: https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-castList.html
                  The other thing I'd suggest is giving more evocative xml:id's. Eg. for the first one: @xml:id="goodfellows" , etc. 
                  The notes are terrific. Nice job. -->
               <person xml:id="char1" role="fictional">
                  <persName>
                     <surname>Goodfellows</surname>
                     <forename>Robin</forename>
                     <!-- GT: here you don't need <choice>. You only use <choice> when you present 2 options. Here there's just one -->
                     <choice>
                        <orig>The Puck</orig>
                     </choice>
                  </persName>
                  <note>
                     <p>In English folklore, The Puck, also known as Goodfellows, are/is a domestic and nature sprite, demon, or fairy.</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="char2" role="fictional" sex="m">
                  <persName>Oberon</persName>
                  <note>
                     <p>Oberon is a king of the fairies in medieval and Renaissance literature. He is best known as a character in William 
                        Shakespeare's play A Midsummer Night's Dream, in which he is King of the Fairies and spouse of Titania, Queen of 
                        the Fairies.</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="char3" role="fictional" sex="m">
                  <persName>Harry Bailly or Harry Bailey</persName>
                  <note>
                     <p>The Host is a character who plays a key role in and throughout Geoffrey Chaucer's The Canterbury Tales. He is the 
                        owner of the Tabard Inn in London, where the pilgrimage begins and he agrees to travel on the pilgrimage, and promises to judge both the tales the pilgrims tell, and disputes among the pilgrims.</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="char4" role="real" sex="m">
                  <persName>Geoffrey Chaucer</persName>
                  <birth>1340s</birth>
                  <death>25 October 1400</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Geoffrey Chaucer was an English poet, author, and civil servant best known for The Canterbury Tales. He has been 
                        called the "father of English literature", or, alternatively, the "father of English poetry".</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="char5" role="real" sex="m">
                  <persName>
                     John of Gaunt
                  </persName>
                  <birth>6 March 1340</birth>
                  <death>3 February 1399</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>John of Gaunt, Duke of Lancaster was an English royal prince, military leader, and statesman. He was the fourth son of 
                        King Edward III of England, and the father of King Henry IV. </p>
                  </note>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
            
            <bibl n="1">
               <title>Puck (folklore)</title>
               <!-- GT: use the @when attribute with <date> -->
               <date>This page was last edited on 26 January 2024, at 15:00 (UTC).</date>
               <!-- GT: And use <ptr/> if there's no content:
                  <ptr target="URL"/> -->
               <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Puck_(folklore)"/>
            </bibl>
            
            <bibl n="2">
               <title>Oberon</title>
               <date>This page was last edited on 21 January 2024, at 15:31 (UTC).</date>
               <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oberon"/>
            </bibl>
            
            <bibl n="3">
               <title>The Host (Canterbury Tales)</title>
               <date>This page was last edited on 25 January 2022, at 13:16 (UTC).</date>
               <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Host"/>
            </bibl>
            
            <bibl n="4">
               <title>Geoffrey Chaucer</title>
               <date>This page was last edited on 7 February 2024, at 09:54 (UTC).</date>
               <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geoffrey_Chaucer"/>
            </bibl>
            
            <bibl n="5">
               <title>John of Gaunt</title>
               <date>This page was last edited on 8 February 2024, at 16:06 (UTC).</date>
               <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_of_Gaunt"/>
            </bibl>
		 
	    <bibl n="6">
    		<title>19th century acting editions collection, 1762-1946</title>
    		<date>Historical note and collection information added 2017</date>
    		<ref target="https://archiveswest.orbiscascade.org/ark:80444/xv656279"/>
	    </bibl>

	    <bibl n="7">
   		<title>A Complete Guide to Pantomime</title>
   		<date>03 June 2022</date>
   		<ref target="https://www.blackpoolgrand.co.uk/complete-guide-to-pantomime"/>
	    </bibl>
         </div><!-- GT: I think you're missing a closing </bibl> here... -->
         
         <!-- SCENE V -->
         <div type="scene" n='5'>
            <head rend="italic bold">SCENE V. – FRIAR BACON’S OBSERVATORY AT SUNNINGWELL NEAR OXFORD, AND DISTANT VIEW OF JOHN OF GAUNT‘
               S CASTLE, BY SUNSET</head>
            <stage>Over door of observatory, an inscription— ‘<hi rend="italic">Friar Bacon, Licensed Dealer in Black Art.</hi>’ 
               –Other boards about, such as ‘<hi rend="italic">Conjuring Tricks provided, Evening Parties attended</hi>’ — 
               ‘<hi rend="italic">Dissolving Views lent out for the Evening</hi>’ — ‘<hi rend="italic">Love-Philters made up</hi>’— ‘
               <hi rend="italic">Private Lessons in Parlour Magic.</hi>’ Expressive Music.</stage>
            <p>JOHN OF GAUNT enters, mysteriously. Enveloped in a large cloak, and attended by his ‘Squire, whom he dismisses as soon as he 
               finds himself at the house of which he is in search—points to board, ‘<hi rend="italic">Love Philters made up,’</hi> and 
               signifies that is the sort of thing he requires —knocks at door—House Pocus, the Friar’s servant, appears—john desires to 
               see the learned <hi rend="bold italic">Friar Bacon</hi>—man refuses—brings out board—‘<hi rend="italic">The Friar is engaged 
                  in profound study</hi>’—John of Gaunt tries a bribe, and succeeds—the Friar is summoned, and appears with a large frying-pan,
               as if disturbed in frying a rasher of being discovered at this culinary operation, slaps man in, throws frying-pan after him, 
               and attends to John of Gaunt, who takes him mysteriously down stage.</p>
            <sp who="#JOHN">
               <speaker>John.</speaker>
               <l>Before me, I behold, or I’m mistaken,</l>
               <l>The famous necromancer, <hi rend="bold italic">Friar Bacon</hi>!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#FRIAR">
               <speaker>Friar.</speaker>
               <l>Can I believe my eyes? It is—it arn’t—</l>
               <l>Do I behold behind me John of Gaunt?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JOHN">
               <speaker>John.</speaker>
               <l>Hush! Mum! I come incog—would not be known—</l>
               <l>You understand?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#FRIAR">
               <speaker>Friar.</speaker>
               <l>I do !</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JOHN">
               <speaker>John.</speaker>
               <l>Are we alone?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#FRIAR">
               <speaker>Friar.</speaker>
               <l>We are!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JOHN">
               <speaker>John.</speaker>
               <l>‘Tis well! Now listen ;--in your trade,</l>
               <l>I have heard, that curious potions can be made,</l>
               <l>Which if a damsel drinks, she then is sure</l>
               <l>To love the man she couldn’t bear before.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#FRIAR">
               <speaker>Friar.</speaker>
               <l>You have heard aright. Here, Hocus Pocus, quick,</l>
               <l>Bring me my magic drugs—I’ll show you a trick.</l>
            </sp>
            <p>[<hi rend="italic">Hocus Pocus appears from door, and receives instructions—goes off, and returns with large Brazier and
               large Bottle, which the Friar arranges on the stage—The assistant then brings in Packets, severally inscribed ’10,000 a year’
               —‘Unlimited Pin Money’—‘Marriage Settlement’—‘A new Bonnet every Week’—these are successively put into the Bottle.</hi> 
            </p>
            <p>These various things united—mark the list—</p>
            <p>I never knew a woman to resist.</p>
            <p>[<hi rend="italic">Red Fire is kindled below, and the Friar then draws a Phial forth from the Bottle. 
               One trial proves the fact: its worth the heeding,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though some might call this quite a phial proceeding.</p>
            <sp who="#JOHN">
               <speaker>John.</speaker>
               <l>I’ll give the draft at once.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#FRIAR">
               <speaker>Friar.</speaker>
               <l>That’s all right—thank yer—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JOHN">
               <speaker>John.</speaker>
               <l>We’ll talk of that anon.	Now, Friar, learn,</l> 
               <l>To-day, in honor of my safe return,</l> 
               <l>We give a sumptuous spread—it there you walk,</l>
               <l>You are sure to find a friendly knife and fork—</l>
               <l> This ticket will admit you to the fete.</l>
               <l>And there’s a Tournament, if you like to wait.</l>
               <p>[<hi rend="italic">Gives Card, Labelle’</hi></p>
               <p>'ADMIT FRIAR BACON AND FRIEND</p>
               <p>TO THE TOURNAMENT,</p>
               <p>RESERVED SEATS,</p>
               <p>JOHN OF GAUNT.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#FRIAR">
               <speaker>Friar.</speaker>
               <l>You very good, but there’s a small amount—</l>
               <l>Consoling himself.</l>
               <l>Well, I’ll do some business on my own account.</l>
            </sp>
            <p>[<hi rend="italic">Friar calls on Hocus Pocus, who has cleared off the other articles whilst the Friar puts on clean collar, and goes through 
               toilet business, and a Box is brought on, labelled ‘Conjuring Tricks.’ which the Friar takes and goes off with, followed 
               by Hocus Pocus, bearing a Box, labelled ‘Magic Lantern.’—Excunt(Latin)—scene closes.</hi></p>
         </div>
         
         <!-- SCENE VI -->
         <div type="scene">
            <head rend="italic bold">SCENE VI.—GOTHIC CORRIDOR, LEADING TO BANQUETING ROOM.</head>
            <p>
               Lively Music. –The Retainers and Servants of John of Gaunt cross the stage, bearing the customary Pantomimic, Viands for 
               the Banquet—after they have crossed, JOHN OF GAUNT enters, with ROSE, whom he drags on—he renews his protestations- she 
               repulses him—CHAUCER, with his lance in his hand, appears at the back, through sliding panel—he observes them—Servant 
               crosses with Goblet of Wine on a tray, which Gaunt takes—unseen by Rose, he turns into it the contents of the phial—offers 
               it to Rose—Chaucer stepping forward at the moment touches it with his Lance, and the contents of the goblet blaze up and 
               are gone.—Through being over the flame, John of Gaunt is seized with a sudden fit of sneezing.—In the confusion, Chaucer 
               escapes with Rose—Servants return—John wreaks his vengeance upon them—Herald enters, with Trumpet and Scroll, labelled 
            </p>
            <p rend="center">‘THE TOURNAMENT HAS COMMENCED’</p>
            <p>All rush off—and scene draws, discovering</p>
         </div>
         
         <!-- SCENE VII -->
         <div type="scene">
            <head rend="italic bold">SCENE VII.—THE COURT-YARD OF JOHN OF GAUNT’S CASTLE.</head>
            <p>Pavilion at back—The Lists are formed—The Galleries are filled with spectators—Stage full at the sides, and
               only the centre kept clear for the Combatants—Herald blows a trumpet—Chaucer enters with Rose, and signifies 
               he is confident of success—Large Scroll unfolded, ‘The Victor may claims any Prize in the Lists.’—JOHN OF GAUNT 
               enters and flings down large gauntlet into the arena—Chaucer picks it up, and challenges John of Gaunt, who first of 
               all produces sword and shield—These are no sooner touched by the Magic Lance than the shield expands into a large bouquet 
               of Roses, and the sword opens into a large Fan—John of Gaunt gives them to a Lady of the Court, and then commences a 
               Comic Combat with lances, which ends in the discomfiture of John of Gaunt.—Chaucer goes to the Pavilion and leads Rose down.
            </p>
            <sp who="#CHAUCER">
               <speaker>Chaucer.</speaker>
               <l>Be witness all—this is the prize I choose.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JOHN">
               <speaker>John.</speaker>
               <l>A slight mistake—that maiden I refuse.</l>
               <l>What ho, there!  Seize the caitiff!—now I’m calmer.</l>
               <p>[<hi rend = "italic">Retainers seize Chaucer, whilst John of Gaunt snatches the lamp.</hi></p>
               <l>I have his charms, and now I’ll have his charmer.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#CHAUCER">
               <speaker>Chaucer.</speaker>
               <l>Then thus on Robin Goodfellow I call.</l>
            </sp>
            <p rend = "right italic">Chord—and instantaneous change to</p>
         </div>
         
         <!-- SCENE VIII -->
         <div type="scene">
            <head rend="italic bold">SCENE VIII.—THE TRANSPARENT REALMS OF ILLUTIONS, IN THE REGIONS OF POETRY.</head>
            <p rend = "center italic"> All the Fairies discovered.</p>
            <sp who="#ROBIN">
               <speaker>Robin.</speaker>
               <l>Behold our Fairy Court assembled all.</l>
               <l>This lady fair, through no one did imagine it,</l>
               <l>Is in reality Miss Rose Plantagenet.</l>
               <l>Woo’d by the poet in her humble guise,</l>
               <l>He now has fairly won her for his prize.</l>
               <l>To aid the promised revels of to-night,</l>
               <l>As Columbine, henceforth the world delight.</l>
               <p rend = "right italic">[Change Rose to COLUMBINE.</p>
               <l>You, whose poetic feet we nimble see,</l>
               <l>As Harlequin, her lover still shall be</l>
               <p rend = "right italic">[Change Chaucer to HARLEQUIN.</p>
            </sp>
            <p rend = "center">Enter IMAGINATION.</p>
            <sp who = "#IMAGINATION">
               <speaker>Imagination.</speaker> 
               <l>To do without me you were much mistaken,</l>
               <l> From all this change, you shall not save your Bacon.</l>
               <l> So, Friar, stand forth, these robes abandon soon,</l>
               <l>And only have a band on Pantaloon.</l>
               <p rend = "right italics">[Change Friar Bacon to PANTALOON.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who = "#ROBIN">
               <speaker>Robin.</speaker>	
               <l> John of Gaunt escape? In well-know lingo</l>
               <l>I’ll swear he still shall have more thumps, by jingo.</l>
               <l>So, change to Clown—your fame has spread afar—</l>
               <l>And charm each ear with jocund ‘Here we are.;’</l>
               <p rend  = "right italic">[Change John of Gaunt to CLOWN.</p>
               <l><hi rend = "italic">[To Harlequin,]</hi> Your magic lance, sir, this will supersede;</l>
               <l>But still ‘twill answer in the hour of need.	 <hi rend = "right italic">[Gives bat.</hi></l>
            </sp>
            <sp who = "IMAGINATION">
               <speaker>Imagination.</speaker> 
               <l> Yet one word more—behold this Christmas Tree,</l>
               <l>Shall this appear and we no blossom see?</l>
               <l>Not so! Receive this little augmentation</l>
               <l>Of all these ‘pleasures of Imagination!’</l>
               <p rend = "right italic">[SPRITE appears.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who = "#ROBIN">
               <speaker>Robin.</speaker>	
               <l>Now, then, away, once more, to quote the poet,</l>
               <l>In all your merriment be wise—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who = "#IMAGINATION">
               <speaker>Imagination.</speaker>						
               <l rend = "right">And go it.</l>
            </sp>
         </div>
         
         <div>
            <p rend = "bold italic center"> (Comic Business Commences)</p>
            <p rend = "bold center">Scene I.—TOY SHOP AND CONFECTIONER’S.</p>
            <p rend = "bold cneter">By Messrs. T. Totum and Toffey</p>
            <p rend = "bold cneter">Scene II.—A SURBURBAN BOARDING-SCHOOL and YOUNG LADIES’ SEMINARY.</p>
            <p rend = "bold cneter">By Mr. Birch and Miss O’Thwackham.</p>
            <p rend = "bold cneter">Scene III.—COTTON BROKERS AND GENERAL DEALERS.</p>
            <p rend = "bold cneter">By A. Sell and E. Sell.</p>
            <p rend = "bold cneter">Scene IV.—GRANDMAMMMA”S DRAWING-ROOM.</p>
            <p rend = "bold cneter">By Jolly Boy and Assistants.</p>
            <p rend = "bold cneter">Scene IV.__LOAN OFFICE, RESTAURANT’S, and FARRIER’S</p>
            <p rend = "bold cneter">By Touch and Go.</p>
            <p rend = "bold cneter">Scene VI.—and Last –The Grand Finale.</p>
            <p rend = "bold cneter">The SALAMANDRINE TEMPLE.</p>
            <p rend = "bold">With the Wonder of the World in a cage with a thousand fires, the Children’s Christmas Squibs, and the Triumph of 
               Francisco Frost, with a Darby effect.</p>
         </div>
         
         <!-- FOOTNOTE PAGE -->
         <div type="footnote">
            <head>Footnote Page</head>
            <p>THE TABARD.—As the Borough High Street was formerly the great passage into a great part of the kingdom to and from the capital, 
               it was well furnished with inns, the above having been immortalized by Chaucer. The sign is now perverted into ‘The Talbot.’ 
               It originally was ‘The Tabard,’ so called from the sign, a sleeveless coat open on both sides, with a square collar and winged 
               at the shoulders: worn by persons of rank in the wars, with their arms painted on them, that they might be known. The use of 
               this coat is now transferred to the heralds. This was the rendezvous of the jolly pilgrims who formed the group which our 
               ‘father of poetry’ describes sallying out to pay their devotions to the great saint, Thomas a Beckett, whose shrine, for a 
               long time, surperseded almost every other, being resorted to down to the Reformation by pilgrims from every part of Christendom. 
               The sign was changed from the ‘Tabard’ to the ‘Talbot,’ about the year 1676. The following inscription used to appear on the 
               frieze of the beams which hung across the road, and from the centre of which the sign was suspended.—‘This is the inn where 
               Sir Jeffery Chaucer and the nine-and -twenty pilgrims lay, in their journey to Canterbury, anno 1383.</p>
         </div>
         
         <!-- ACKNOWLEDGEMENT PAGE -->
         <div type="acknowledgement">
            <head>Acknowledgement Page</head>
            <p>The Scenery (from historical authorities), with the Grand Transformation Effects, the greatest and most extraordinary ever yet 
               attempted, by Mr. GATES, assisted by Messrs. Albert Callcott, W. Broadfoot, Gourie, Lambert, Devigne, Buckley, and Atkins.</p>
            <p>For an Illustrative Pictorial Tableau of the residence of the Ancient Magician, Friar Bacon, at Sunningwell, the valuable 
               services of Mr. CHARLES JAMES have been specially secured, whose artistic pencil will add and additional charm to the highly 
               elaborate scenic illustrations.</p>
            <p>The Pantomime invented and written by the celebrated FRANCESCO FROST, Esq.</p>
            <p>The Music by J. H. TULLY. Esq.</p>
            <p>The Ballet and Dances by Signor MILANO.</p>
            <p>The Comical Facial Expressions and Quaint by QUICK DIGIT.</p>
            <p>The Gas Appointments by Mr. PEPPER and Assistants.</p>
            <p>The Costumes by Mr. LAURI</p>
            <p>The Properties by Mr. MOON.</p>
            <p>The Extensive Machinery by Mr. SLOMAN.</p>
            <p>The Box Department by Mr. CHARLES NUGENT, of Her Majesty’s Theatre, to to whom a telegraph or letter will secure places 
               without charge for booking.</p>
            <p>And the whole Arranged and Produced under the entire direction of Mr. T. H. HIGGIE, Stage-manager.</p>
         </div>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
