<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="teibp.xsl"?>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Harlequin and Friar Bacon</title>
            <author>Francesco Frost</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Bonnie Ha, Cassidy Fallon Vierling, Echo Yu</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Seattle, WA</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>University of Washington, Seattle</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2024-02​-XX</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>We were able to read the pamphlet in the collection classroom located on the base level
            of Allen Library North. 
               <bibl>
                  <title>Harlequin and Friar Bacon</title>
                  <author>Francesco Frost</author>
                  <publisher>The Music-Publishing Company</publisher>
                  <date>1863 </date>
                  <pubPlace>London: 19 Peter's Hill, St. Paul's</pubPlace>
               </bibl>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>
            <p>Editorial notes in the 1863's edition have not been reproduced</p>
         </samplingDecl>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization method="silent">
               <p>Original punctuation conventions in the 1863's edition will be retained as much as possible</p>
            </normalization>
            <interpretation>
               <p>Italics will be recorded without interpretation</p>
            </interpretation>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition>caps, italics, bold</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>“Harlequin and Friar Bacon” is a British pantomime play from the collection of Glenn Hughes who used the collection in the 1930s and 1940s as a tool for research and teaching his students in the drama program at the University of Washington. It comes from a collection of over 3,000 plays, the majority British. It is likely that “Harlequin and Friar Bacon” belongs to the subset within the collection of works added from a single contributing collection, all of which were made as sales or gifts to the audience of a performance, mainly consisting of Christmas extravaganzas, pantomimes, and burlesques. Pantomimes are usually performed around Christmas and are comedies that often include slapstick humor, jokes, innuendos, magic, fairies, and gender reversal.</p>
	 <p>The focus of our edition of “Harlequin and Friar Bacon” is digitizing the original play to become accessible to actors and students who are interested in its content, whether that be for purposes of studying drama or gleaning an understanding of the content of historical plays. Pantomimes are still performed in the United States but with less frequency and popularity than in England, so the edition will also function to introduce actors to studies of plays on a global scale.</p>
	 <p>Our edition features a transcription which is intended to maintain as much of the original content as possible, including preserving the British spellings for words as opposed to Americanizing them. Racial slurs have been redacted and given note in the end notes if relevant to understanding the passage. Any italics and bold are preserved as they are displayed in the original play. In the original print, advertisements line the jacket and are interspersed throughout the text, which have not been preserved in this digital edition because it is not intended for viewing by audiences but by actors.</p>
         <div type='editorial'>
            <listPerson>
               <!-- GT: good! Is this a cast list? You could also use the TEI element <castList>: https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-castList.html
                  The other thing I'd suggest is giving more evocative xml:id's. Eg. for the first one: @xml:id="goodfellows" , etc. 
                  The notes are terrific. Nice job. -->
               <person xml:id="char1" role="fictional">
                  <persName>
                     <surname>Goodfellows</surname>
                     <forename>Robin</forename>
                     <!-- GT: here you don't need <choice>. You only use <choice> when you present 2 options. Here there's just one -->
                     <choice>
                        <orig>The Puck</orig>
                     </choice>
                  </persName>
                  <note>
                     <p>In English folklore, The Puck, also known as Goodfellows, are/is a domestic and nature sprite, demon, or fairy.</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="char2" role="fictional" sex="m">
                  <persName>Oberon</persName>
                  <note>
                     <p>Oberon is a king of the fairies in medieval and Renaissance literature. He is best known as a character in William 
                        Shakespeare's play A Midsummer Night's Dream, in which he is King of the Fairies and spouse of Titania, Queen of 
                        the Fairies.</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="char3" role="fictional" sex="m">
                  <persName>Harry Bailly or Harry Bailey</persName>
                  <note>
                     <p>The Host is a character who plays a key role in and throughout Geoffrey Chaucer's The Canterbury Tales. He is the 
                        owner of the Tabard Inn in London, where the pilgrimage begins and he agrees to travel on the pilgrimage, and promises to judge both the tales the pilgrims tell, and disputes among the pilgrims.</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="char4" role="real" sex="m">
                  <persName>Geoffrey Chaucer</persName>
                  <birth>1340s</birth>
                  <death>25 October 1400</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Geoffrey Chaucer was an English poet, author, and civil servant best known for The Canterbury Tales. He has been 
                        called the "father of English literature", or, alternatively, the "father of English poetry".</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="char5" role="real" sex="m">
                  <persName>
                     John of Gaunt
                  </persName>
                  <birth>6 March 1340</birth>
                  <death>3 February 1399</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>John of Gaunt, Duke of Lancaster was an English royal prince, military leader, and statesman. He was the fourth son of 
                        King Edward III of England, and the father of King Henry IV. </p>
                  </note>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
            
            <bibl n="1">
               <title>Puck (folklore)</title>
               <!-- GT: use the @when attribute with <date> -->
               <date>This page was last edited on 26 January 2024, at 15:00 (UTC).</date>
               <!-- GT: And use <ptr/> if there's no content:
                  <ptr target="URL"/> -->
               <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Puck_(folklore)"/>
            </bibl>
            
            <bibl n="2">
               <title>Oberon</title>
               <date>This page was last edited on 21 January 2024, at 15:31 (UTC).</date>
               <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oberon"/>
            </bibl>
            
            <bibl n="3">
               <title>The Host (Canterbury Tales)</title>
               <date>This page was last edited on 25 January 2022, at 13:16 (UTC).</date>
               <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Host"/>
            </bibl>
            
            <bibl n="4">
               <title>Geoffrey Chaucer</title>
               <date>This page was last edited on 7 February 2024, at 09:54 (UTC).</date>
               <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geoffrey_Chaucer"/>
            </bibl>
            
            <bibl n="5">
               <title>John of Gaunt</title>
               <date>This page was last edited on 8 February 2024, at 16:06 (UTC).</date>
               <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_of_Gaunt"/>
            </bibl>
		 
	    <bibl n="6">
    		<title>19th century acting editions collection, 1762-1946</title>
    		<date>Historical note and collection information added 2017</date>
    		<ref target="https://archiveswest.orbiscascade.org/ark:80444/xv656279"/>
	    </bibl>

	    <bibl n="7">
   		<title>A Complete Guide to Pantomime</title>
   		<date>03 June 2022</date>
   		<ref target="https://www.blackpoolgrand.co.uk/complete-guide-to-pantomime"/>
	    </bibl>
         </div><!-- GT: I think you're missing a closing </bibl> here... -->

<!-- TITLE PAGE -->
         <div type="title_page">
            <head rend="caps">Harlequin and Friar Bacon</head>
            <head rend="caps">or</head>
            <head rend="caps">Great Grim John of Gaunt,</head>
            <p rend="caps">and the</p>
            <p rend="caps">Enchanted Lance of Robin Goodfellow:</p>
            <p> rend="caps">An entirely new and original grotesque, burlesque, poetic, pictorial,
               spectacular, historical, dramatic, and hippo-dramatic, grand comic Christmas
               Pantomime.</p>
            <p rend="caps">By Francesco Frost.</p>
            <p rend="caps">London:</p>
            <p rend="caps">The Music-Publishing Company, / 19 Peter’s Hill, St. Paul’s, E.C.</p>
         </div>

<!-- SYNOPSIS AND CHARACTERS -->
         <div type="synopsis">
            <head rend="caps">Synopsis of Scenery, Incidents, and Characters,</head>
            <p rend="caps">Fairy Encampment by Moonlight.</p>
            <p>‘All was this land full of færie, The Elf-Queen with her jolly company, Danced full
               oft’ in many a green mead.’ –<hi rend="italics">Chaucer</hi>.</p>
            <p>Robin Goodfellow (‘that merry wanderer of the night’), Miss Eliza Arden;</p>
            <p>Will O’ the Wisp, Miss Gasflitter;</p>
            <p> Oberon, (the Fairy King), Miss Nesbitt;</p>
            <p>Imagination (Queen of the Realms of Poetry), Miss Weber;</p>
            <p>Romance, Reverie, Fiction, Song, Wit, and Humour (attendants on Imagination);</p>
            <p>Misses Brown, Johnson, Fudge, Jones, Somes, and Lewis.</p>
            <p><hi rend="caps">The Fairy Army</hi>.–Captain, Miss Eliza Grosvenor; Lieutenant, Miss
               Polly Grosvenor; assisted by a numerous corps of coryphées.</p>
            <p rend="caps">Arrival of Oberon in his glow-worm chariot, and grand ballet, of the
               Amazonian Fairies.</p>
            <p>Principal danseuse, Madlle Stellinos, from Paris.</p>
            <p>Old Pantomime, Mr. Allen; Broadgrin (his Herald), Mr. Hawshaw; Trap, Flap, Slap,
               Bump, Jump, and Thump (his attendants), Masters Trip, Flip, Slip, Whack, Bang, and
               Smart.</p>
            <p>How Oberon calls upon Imagination to assist good Old Pantomime, and the result.</p>
            <p rend="caps">The Grotto of good-idea, in the world of fancy.</p>
            <p> ‘By Imagination’s aid, thus we are to-night conveyed, Far away into the past to a
               region that will last enshrined in fame for ever.’</p>
            <p>How Imagination reveals a treasure of the past, and bestows it on the present as a
               gift for the future.</p>
            <p rend="caps">The ancient hostelrie of ‘The Tabard,’</p>
            <p>in the Borough, with the Inn-yard and Projecting Galleries of the Period, as it
               appeared May-Day, 1383. (Gates.)</p>
            <p>Master Henry Bailly (host of ‘The Tabard’), Mr. Templeton.</p>
            <p>Ostler, Mr. Bonemeals; Boots, Mr. Samwella;</p>
            <p>Chambermaids, Miss Bumptious and Miss Scrumptious;</p>
            <p>Rose (the ‘pretty Barmaid’), Miss Morelli;</p>
            <p>Waiters, Messrs. Runquick, Yessir, and Cumming;</p>
            <p>Geoffrey Chaucer (the Poet), Miss Craven.</p>
            <p><hi rend="caps">Canterbury Pilgrims</hi>–The Knight, the Yeoman, the Prior, the Monk,
               the Miller, the Friar, the Scholar, the Sergeant of the Law, the Doctor, the
               Franklin, and the Wife of Bath, by eminent equestrians of Astleyan celebrity.</p>
            <p>‘It so befelle that season on a daye, In Southwark at the Tabard Inn I laye, Ready by
               morne my progress to pursue.’ <hi rend="italics">Chaucer’s Canterbury Tales</hi>.</p>
            <p rend="caps">The Old English Morris-dance.</p>
            <p>Great Grim John of Gaunt (Duke of Lancaster), Mr. Lingham.</p>
            <p>His retainers, Messrs. Grumpy, Stumpy, Smash, Crash, Whack, Crackdrill, Swill, Swop,
               Chop, Glum, Grum, Snip, Snap, and Cutaway.</p>
            <p>How John of Gaunt, returning from the wars, is struck by the beauty of the Barmaid
               and the stout arm of Chaucer, and what ensues in consequence.</p>
            <p rend="caps">Old Bridle-Way and Wishing-Gate on the road to Canterbury.</p>
            <p>‘Now as every Pilgrim tells a tale that shall make short the day, Jingling go our
               palfrey-bells, as we onward wend our way.’</p>
            <p>The wish uttered. Blooming of hawthorn tree, and presentation of the enchanted
               lance.</p>
            <p>Gnome of the Fiery Phiz, Master Wrednose.</p>
            <p rend="caps">Friar Bacon’s observatory at Sunningwell,</p>
            <p> near Oxford, with Distant View of John of Gaunt’s Castle by Sunset. (C. S.
               James.)</p>
            <p>Old Friar Bacon (the Necromancer), Mr. Russell.</p>
            <p>Hocus Pocus (his attendant), Mr. G. Craig.</p>
            <p>The mysterious visitor–The conjuror’s cabalistic charm and concoction of the magic
               love-potion–How John of Gaunt gives an invitation to a fête–How the Friar meets with
               another fate he never expected.</p>
            <p><hi rend="caps">Exterior of John of Gaunt’s castle</hi>. (A. Callcott.)</p>
            <p><hi rend="small-caps">Grand procession to the tournament</hi>, and Brilliant Display
               of the Knights of the Days of Yore on their Richly Caparisoned Horses.</p>
            <p><hi rend="caps">Corridor leading to banquetting-room</hi>. (W. Broadfoot.)</p>
            <p>Preparations for the feast and fray–Marvellous effects of the gift of Robin
               Goodfellow, and how John of Gaunt having gone down on his knees in one way, goes down
               on his sneeze in another.</p>
            <p><hi rend="caps">Court-yard of the castle, prepared for the tournament</hi>. (A.
               Callcott.)</p>
            <p>Formation of the lists–Desperate encounter–The ‘Gentle and joyous passage of arms’
               among the knightly competitors for the prizes, and tremendous tilt between Chaucer
               and Grim John of Gaunt, which leads to a startling effect on one of combatants, and
               results in the magnificent effect of</p>
            <p rend="caps">The transparent realms of illusion,</p>
            <p><hi rend="small-caps">and grand flight of Imagination from the fragrant clusters of
                  Canterbury bells</hi>. (Gates).</p>
            <p rend="caps bold">The Transformation.</p>
            <p>Harlequin ………………………………………………… Mr. W. <hi rend="caps">Driver</hi>.</p>
            <p>Columbine ………………………………………………… Miss <hi rend="caps">Newham</hi>.</p>
            <p>Harlequina ……………………………………………… Miss <hi rend="caps"> Nelly Davis</hi>.</p>
            <p>Pantaloon ………………………………………………… Mr. <hi rend="caps">Stilt</hi>.</p>
            <p>Clown ……………………………………………………… Mr. <hi rend="caps">Edwin Edwards</hi>.</p>
            <stage>(From the Continental Theatres.</stage>
         </div>

<!-- SCENE I -->
         <div type="scene" n="1">
            <head rend="caps">Friar Bacon.</head>
            <head rend="italic bold">Scene 1.–Fairy encampment, by moonlight, on the
                  plains of phantasy</hi>.</head>
            <stage><hi rend="italics">A picturesque view of a Fairy Camp, with Mushrooms for Tents,
                  appearing to occupy on extensive plain, with hills beyond, dotted with lines of
                  Mushrooms, diminishing in perspective–Two large Mushrooms, as tents, in the
                  foreground–one at each front wing–The whole scene imitative of the Camp at
                  Aldershot</hi>.–<hi rend="small-caps">Robin Goodfellow</hi><hi rend="italics">
                  discovered, as a Fairy Sentinel</hi>.</stage>
            <p><hi rend="caps">Song</hi>, <hi rend="small-caps">Robin Goodfellow</hi>.</p>
            <p>Elfins who, in fairy tent,</p>
            <p>After day’s exhaustion, slumber,</p>
            <p>Shoulder arms, and here present</p>
            <p>All your force in mighty number;</p>
            <p>Gathered on the plains of Surrey,</p>
            <p>Here appear now, in a hurry.</p>
            <stage rend="italics">[Music.–Mushroom Tents all expand, and the stage becomes filled
               with Fairies, each bearing a fantastic bulrush as a weapon.–Tableau.</stage>
            <sp who="#ROBIN">
               <speaker rend="italics">Robin.</speaker>
               <l>A fair assembly, formed in gallant style.</l>
               <l>How does my old acquaintance of this isle?</l>
               <l>From bud and blossom, forest, lake, and stream,</l>
               <l>Ye have been summoned–for, as mortals deem,</l>
               <l>Your power is gone–that Fairy Land must cease–</l>
               <l>Unfit for war–used up in every <hi rend="italics">piece</hi>.</l>
               <l>There has been fixed, by Oberon’s direction,</l>
               <l>A Volunteer Review for his inspection.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage rend="italics">[A Fairy comes forward unsteadily.</stage>
            <sp who="#FAIRY">
               <speaker rend="italics">Fairy.</speaker>
               <l>Our general grows particular, methinks.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ROBIN">
               <speaker rend="italics">Robin.</speaker>
               <l>This comes of those intoxicating drinks.</l>
               <l>Duty off wines should satisfy your throttle:</l>
               <l>Try good French claret, eighteen-pence per bottle.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#FAIRY">
               <speaker rend="italics">Fairy.</speaker>
               <l>My thirsty lips did but dewdrop drain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ROBIN">
               <speaker rend="italics">Robin.</speaker>
               <l>These slips I hope won’t lead to goes again.</l>
               <l>But Oberon comes.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage><hi rend="italics">Music.–A Will-O’-the-Wisp passes across the state, followed by
                  </hi><hi rend="small-caps">Oberon</hi>,<hi rend="italics">in his glow-worm
                  Chariot, drawn by gigantic Moths</hi>.</stage>
            <sp who="#ROBIN">
               <speaker rend="italics">Robin.</speaker>
               <l>Our great commander, hail!</l>
               <l>I thought your royal visit would not fail.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#OBERON">
               <speaker rend="italics">Oberon.</speaker>
               <l>I scarce could see, the road’s so dark to-night.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ROBIN">
               <speaker rend="italics">Robin.</speaker>
               <l>Allow me, then, to help you to a-light.</l>
               <stage rend="italics">[Robin assists Oberon from his chariot, which goes off.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#OBERON">
               <speaker rend="italics">Oberon.</speaker>
               <l>Now, would you like to learn on what pretences</l>
               <l>You are here encamped?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ROBIN">
               <speaker rend="italics">Robin.</speaker>
               <l>Our national defences?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#OBERON">
               <speaker rend="italics">Oberon.</speaker>
               <l>Just so; for mortals, shunning our assistance,</l>
               <l> Don’t even now believe in our existence.</l>
               <l>Science and art, they say–a fact too true–</l>
               <l>Accomplish all the work <hi rend="italics">we</hi> used to do.</l>
               <l>So, show the world no longer they must doubt us;</l>
               <l>At <hi rend="italics">Christmas</hi> time they <hi rend="italics">cannot</hi> do
                  without us.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage rend="italics">[Comic Pantomime Music heard, without.</stage>
            <sp who="#OBERON">
               <speaker rend="italics">Oberon.</speaker>
               <l>Who’s there? Do you hear that strain? it comes in time.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ROBIN">
               <speaker rend="italics">Robin.</speaker>
               <l> I know him well–it’s good old Pantomime!</l>
            </sp>
            <stage><hi rend="italics">Enter, preceded by Broadgrin (a large Head with broad grinning
                  mouth), and six Imps, Trap, Flap, Slap, Bump, Jump, and Thump,</hi>
               <hi rend="small-caps">Old Pantomime</hi>, <hi rend="italics"/>dressed in a grotesque
               mixture of the usual costume of all the characters in Pantomime–crown of carrots and
               turnips, red hot poker for staff.–He presents a petition to Oberon, who reads
               it.</stage>
            <sp who="OBERON">
               <speaker rend="italics">Oberon.</speaker>
               <l>What’s this? of subjects I am so bereft,</l>
               <l>That I’ve scarce got a single subject left!</l>
               <l>For help again am I so soon accosted?</l>
               <l>Are all the funds I gave you quite exhausted?</l>
            </sp>
            <stage rend="italics">[Pantomime regrets they are:</stage>
            <sp who="#ROBIN">
               <speaker rend="italics">Robin.</speaker>
               <l>His fairy treasury is very low.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#OBERON">
               <speaker rend="italics">Oberon.</speaker>
               <l>That Pantomime’s extravagant we know.</l>
               <l>But where are all the tales I gave the hints?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#ROBIN">
               <speaker rend="italics">Robin.</speaker>
               <l>For Christmas entertainments used long since.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#OBERON">
               <speaker rend="italics">Oberon.</speaker>
               <l>Well, for the sake of all those little folks,</l>
               <l>Who still look forward to his annual jokes,</l>
               <l>I on Imagination now will call,</l>
               <l>And ask her aid to benefit us all.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage rend="italics">[Waving wand, and speaking through Music:</stage>
            <sp who="#OBERON">
               <l>Queen of our fairy world, Imagination,</l>
               <l>Respond unto your children’s invocation.</l>
               <l>To Oberon, born in your poetic sphere,</l>
               <l>In all your glowing colours now appear.</l>
               <l>Imagination can’t imagine why–</l>
               <l> But just suppose a [-] air I try.</l>
            </sp>
            <p><hi rend="caps">Song</hi>, <hi rend="small-caps">Oberon.</hi></p>
            <sp who="#OBERON">
               <l>Imagination now appear–</l>
               <l>Come now readily;</l>
               <l>And let me know that you are near;</l>
               <l>Do now!</l>
               <l>For Oberon desires</l>
               <l>Your spark to light his fires.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage rend="italics">[Gradual descent, and change to</stage>
         </div>
   <!-- SCENE II -->
<div type="scene" n='2'>
<head rend="italic bold">Scene II.–The Grotto of Good Idea, in the World of Fancy. </head>
<p rend="italics">In the Rainbow Car is Imagination, attended by Romance, Reverie, Fiction, Poetry, Wit, and Humour–at the back is inscribed, in glistening letters, 
‘Chaucer’s Canterbury Tales.’</p> 
<sp who="#IMAGINATION"><speaker rend="italics">Imagination.</speaker> 
<l> I’m here to serve you, and can serve you greatly; I’ve been in much request in Christmas, lately. </l>
<l>Behold what never can be old! Take these </l>
<l>Immortal Tales, and use them as you please. </l>
<l>At once, then, stepping just five centuries back,</l> 
<l>Here shall you start upon your annual track.</l> 
<l>Old Geoffrey Chaucer, he my eldest child, </l>
<l>Who quaffed the well of English undefiled, </l>
<l>Shall wake to life again–and with him those </l>
<l>Who lived about that period, we’ll suppose; </l>
<l>The ancient Tabard shall once more be found,</l> 
With pilgrims famed to Canterbury bound.</sp> 
<stage rend="italics">[Music.–Old Pantomime expresses his thanks for aid. </stage>
<sp who="#IMAGINATION #OBERON #ROBIN GOODFELLOW"><speaker rend="italics">Trio.–Imagination, Oberon, and Robin Goodfellow. </speaker>
<l>By Imagination’s aid, </l>
<l>Thus are we to-night conveyed </l>
<l>Far away into the past, </l>
<l>To a region that will last </l>
<l>Enshrined in fame for ever.</l> 
<l>But, whilst we glean from poet’s page </l>
<l>Memories of a bygone age, </l>
<l>Let us borrow, by the way,</l> 
<l>Something from the present day, </l>
<l>To show what we endeavor. </l> </sp>
<sp who="#CHORUS"><speaker rend="italics">Chorus.</speaker> <l>Then lightly, sprightly, trip along– </l>
<l>Which always ends a fairy song.</l></sp> 
<stage rend="italics">[At conclusion Imagination returns to her Car, and ascends with her Attendants, whilst Oberson and the Fairies go off on one side, and Robin Goodfellow leads off Pantomime and his retinue on the other.</stage> </div>
   <!-- SCENE III -->
<div type="scene" n='3'>
 <head rend="italic bold"> Scene III.–The Ancient Hostelrie of The Tabard, in the Borough.* </head>
 <stage rend="italics">The scene occupies the full extent of the stage, with the Inn-Yard and projecting galleries of the period distinctly marked.–Lively Music. 
 Ostler appears as if just risen, goes to stable at side, and gets large sieve Labelled ‘Oats’–signifies he must feed the horses–goes to stable, and the heads of your horses are visible projecting over a rack–is about to feed them, but thinks a little roguery better–empties oats into his pocket and beats horses heads back again with sieve, which he throws in amongst them. 
 Bell rings–Boots rushes from door into Inn-yard with an arm full of 
 * For descriptive Note, see page fifteen.
 boots and shoes, and upsets Ostler in his hurry, who tumbles into horse-trough at side.–Whilst Ostler is being extricated, bells ring again violently, from all sides. 
<hi rend="italics"> Two Chambermaids</hi> rush in, with mop and broom, as if in great bustle–mop off Ostler–and Boots, picking up the bundle of boots, and shoes, goes up to gallery above, and is seen to deposit a pair at each door–whilst this is going on above, 
<hi rend="small caps"> Master Henry Bailly</hi>, the host, enters, with Waiters, who spread table for breakfast at side, their movements being accelerated by the occasional insertion of the points of large carving knife and fork–Huge tankards of ale, large loaves, round of beef, and chine of ham, are brought on and placed on table. 
<hi rend="small caps"> Rose,</hi> the Barmaid, enters, with dish of eggs, and at the same time Geoffrey Chaucer comes on, from opposite doorway–they exchange tokens of recognition–the Host observes them, and is indignant–Geoffrey takes the eggs from Rose, to put on table, when just as he has placed them there, the Host comes between them and jumping on table, to prevent their love-making, sits down upon the eggs–hearty merriment of Waiters, who are immediatel re-proved by the forks as before–Host sends Rose off to get more eggs, and quietly signifies he shall attend to her lover by and bye. 
<hi rend="itlaics"> The Pilgrims</hi> now all make their appearance–the Knight, the Squire, the Yeomen his attendants, the Prior, the Monk, the Miller, the Friar, the Scholar, the Serjeant of the Law, the Doctor, the Franklin, and the Wife of Bath. 
<hi rend="small caps"> Rose</hi> returns with another dish of eggs, and they all commence breakfast but Chaucer, who is making</stage> love to Rose–wanting to get the Host out of the way, he asks for his bill–the Host goes off, and returns with it immediately, chuckling over the prices he has charged–Chaucer waits to examine it–the Host and two Waiters then unroll the scroll which is raised by prop to nearly roof of inn–and there is then seen, to Chaucer’s amazement, this:– 
<p> The Tabard, Family Hotel and Posting-House, </p>
<p> High Street, Borough. </p>
<p> May-day, 1383.</p> 
<p> Number – £ s. d. </p>
<p> Mutton Chop .......... 0 5 0 </p>
<p> Pickles ……………. 0 3 0 </p>
<p> Penny Roll ………… 0 1 0 </p>
<p> Salt ……………… 0 0 6</p> 
<p> Pepper …………… 0 0 6 </p>
 <p>Glass Pale Ale ………. 0 1 0</p> 
<p> Bed ……………… 0 3 0 </p>
<p> Apartments …………. 0 8 0 </p>
 <p>A Farthing Rushlight …. 0 2 6 </p>
<p> Attendance ………… 0 6 0 </p>
 <p>(summation bar) 1 10 6 </p>
<stage rend="italics"> Chaucer pulls out purse, and reluctantly pays money–the Host calls down Waiters with pen and ink and, after much flourishing, puts a cross to the bill as his signature. </stage>
 <sp who="#CHAUCER"><speaker rend="italics">Chaucer.</speaker> 
  <l>What! charge one man so much! I hate to boast, But see how one man now can charge a Host.</l></sp>
 <stage rend="italics">[Chaucer wrests his pen from the landlord, and is about to drive him in with it, when a trumpet sounds, without–Pilgrims all rise. </stage>
 <sp who="#HOST"><speaker>Host.</speaker> <l>What means that martial flourish? Ha! by Mars, </l>
<l> Tis John of Gaunt, returning from the wars.</l> </sp>
 <sp who="#CHAUCER"><speaker rend="italics">Chaucer.</speaker> 
<l>  If War is near, then Industry may stump it, </l>
<l> For then nought flourishes, except the trumpet.</l> </sp>
 <stage><hi rend="small caps">March.</hi>–Enter the Soldiers and Retainers of <hi rend="small caps">John of Gaunt</hi>, one carry-ing a banner, ‘Down with the Dust,’ another with double spear banner, a head being impaled on the top of each, and a motto, ‘Two Heads are better than One.”–’Squire, with shield, inscribed ‘No Thoroughfare,’ which he keeps placed over his body.–Lastly, <hi rend="small caps">John of Gaunt </hi>him-self, a grim, gaunt personage, with tremendous mask–he carries a large sword and shield, the latter with his inscription, ‘Jack’s Alive!” –Pantomime business. </stage>
<sp who="#JOHN"> <speaker rend="italics">John.</speaker> <l>So long a march has made us dry again. </l>
<l> So here we’ll rest, and do a quiet drain.</l> 
<l> What ho! some wine, and for our heroes here</l> 
 <l>Bring forth a gallon</l> <stage rend="italics">[All shout.]</stage> <l>of small table-beer. </l></sp>
<stage rend="italics"> [Grumbling–Host obeys the order with alacrity, supplies John of Gaunt with wine, and sends Waiter round with kegs of beer to his followers–he then waits for payment expectantly.</stage> 
<sp who="#JOHN"> <speaker rend="italics">John.</speaker> <l>Just score it up with John of Gaunt, who’ll pay</l> 
<l> The very next time that he comes this way.</l> </sp>
<stage rend="italics"> [Host disappointed, but, producing a large piece of chalk, signifies that he shall score double, and goes off to the door to make entries against it accordingly.–Morris Dance, during which John Gaunt is struck with the beauty of Rose. </stage>
<sp who="#JOHN"> <speaker rend="italics">John.</speaker> <l>Who have we here? a buxom barmaid, too.</l> 
<l> This nectar being on draught, we’ll take some.</l></sp> 
<stage rend="italics"> [Is about to kiss her, when Rose smacks his face. </stage>
<sp who="#JOHN"> <speaker rend="italics">John.</speaker> <l>Pooh!</l> 
<l> I’m one of the excise, and so, my beauty,</l> 
<l> Can’t let this spirit pass without the duty.</l> </sp>
<stage rend="italics"> [Is going to seize her, when Chaucer interposes.</stage> 
<sp who="#CHAUCER"> <speaker rend="italics">Chaucer.</speaker> <l>My lord of Lancaster, one small objection– </l>
 <l>This lovely Rose is under my protection.</l></sp> 
<sp who="#JOHN"> <speaker rend="italics">John.</speaker> <l>What! shall a peer be baffled by a poet! </l>
<l> Not when I choose, sir Chaucer, if I know it. </l>
<l> A duke’s estate this lovely Rose shall deck, </l>
<l> And our king’s castle keep this knight in check.</l></sp> 
<stage rend="italics"> [Music.–John of Gaunt beckons forward two of his retainers–they seize Chaucer, whilst two others bear Rose away.–A general melee ensues–Chaucer breaks away, and attacks John of Gaunt, but the Monk interferes as he is struck down, and John of Gaunt goes off with his retinue triumphantly–Chaucer is in despair.–The Pil-grims busy themselves with preparations for departure–Chaucer is reflecting on his condition, when these two lines appear on a scroll, behind him, on a trough, in golden letters:– </stage>
 <p>‘Fear not, your pilgrimage pursue </p>
<p> For Fairies aid all lovers true.’</p>
<stage rend="italics"> [Chaucer reads the magic scroll, and becomes reassured.–The Pilgrims now return down stage, when the Chambermaid, Head Waiter, Boots, Ostler, &c. (each showing their vocation on a scroll) appeal to them severally for the usual fees–difficulty of supplying them. Business–Pilgrims depart, and a Tableau is formed, whilst the scene changes to–</stage> </div>
   <!-- SCENE IV -->
	  <div type="scene" n='4'>
  <head rend="italic bold"> Scene IV.–Old Bridle-Way and Wishing-Gate, on the Road to Canterbury. </head>
 <stage rend="italics">Finger-Post, ‘To Canterbury.–The Wishing-Guide in the centre–Haw-thorn Tree in blossom, and bank. </stage>
<sp who="#CHORUS"> <speaker rend="bold">Chorus of Pilgrims,</speaker> <stage>[Without.] </stage>
<l> Now as every pilgrim tells</l> 
<l> A tale that shall make short the day,</l> 
<l> Jingling g our palfrey bells, </l>
 <l>As we onward wind our way.</l> </sp>
 <stage rend="italics">[Pilgrims enter, on horseback, across the stage, and, after them, Chaucer, who comes on despondingly, whilst the Pilgrims are seen moving in perspective across the scene–he leans against the Gate, and the Chorus is heard faintly repeated in the distance. </stage>
 <sp who="#CHAUCER"><speaker rend="italics">Chaucer.</speaker> <l>Their merry tales have well beguiled the way, </l>
<l> Yet still upon the road I lingering stay. </l>
<l> The wishing-gate! as legends have instilled,</l> 
<l> Who breathes a wish here has that wish fulfilled. </l>
<l> If truth will come of that old fable, let it, </l>
<l> I’ll wish for aid, and wish that I may get it.</l></sp> 
 <stage rend="italics">[Music.–The Hawthorn Tree, which by this time has become completely covered with Red May, opens, Robin Goodfellow appears, and at the same time Fairies enter at different sides, and a group is formed in the centre.</stage> 
<sp who="#ROBIN"> <speaker rend="italics">Robin.</speaker> <l>You have your wish, we come as soon as wanted, </l>
<l> And, in this sort of style, behold it granted. </l>
<l> You have only got whate’er you wish to say, </l>
<l> And, like this Hawthorn, we respond with May!</l> 
<l> So much we owe the poet for existence, </l>
<l> We can but render you our best assistance.</l> </sp>
<sp who="#CHAUCER"> <speaker rend="italics">Chaucer.</speaker> <l>How to commence my tale of woe–I’m fluttered!</l></sp> 
<sp who="#ROBIN"> <speaker rend="italics">Robin.</speaker> <l>Fear not, I know your story, ere ‘tis uttered.</l> </sp>
 <sp who="#CHAUCER"><speaker rend="italics">Chaucer.</speaker> <l>Wonderful being!–Marvellous penetration!</l> 
 <l>This saves a deal of tedious explanation.</l> </sp>
 <sp who="#ROBIN"><speaker rend="italics">Robin.</speaker> <l>Of course it does.–That party you suppose </l>
<l> To be a party who–no matter–Rose!</l> <stage>[Very mysteriously. </stage>
<l> Has met a party, who did sneer and scoff</l>, 
<l> And then this party, took that party off.</l></sp> 
<sp who="#CHAUCER"> <speaker rend="italics">Chaucer.</speaker> <l>Most true!</l> </sp>
<sp who="#ROBIN"> <speaker rend="italics">Robin.</speaker> <l>He’s one that every body rifles,</l> 
 <l>‘A snapper-up of unconsidered trifles.’</l> </sp>
 <sp who="CHAUCER"><speaker rend="italics">Chaucer.</speaker> <l>Trifles!</l> </sp>
<sp who="#ROBIN"> <speaker rend="italics">Robin.</speaker> <l>‘Twas but a small quotation–no offence–</l> 
<l> From one that’s going to live two centuries hence.</l>
<l> But now to business: at his castle haunt </l>
<l> You must yourself attack grim John of Gaunt!</l> 
<l> With fairy weapons you shall make advance. </l>
<l> What ho! my Gnomes, bring forth the enchanted lance!</l> </sp>
 <stage rend="italics">[Music.–Trap opens and small Cavern rises, in which two Imps, like the famous Kobold, or Gnomes, ar seen finishing a highly-polished lance–Robin Goodfellow takes it, approves the workmanship, and the Cavern descends with Gnomes–Robin then presents it to Chaucer, who appears delighted at the gift. </stage>
<sp who="#ROBIN"> <speaker rend="italics">Robin.</speaker> <l>With this go forth. The magic power such is 
 That nothing can resist it which it touches.</l> </sp>
<sp who="#CHAUCER"> <speaker rend="italics">Chaucer.</speaker> <l>Nay, this is coming to the point indeed.</l> </sp>
<sp who="#ROBIN"> <speaker rend="italics">Robin.</speaker> <l>We will be near you.</l></sp> 
<sp who="#CHAUCER"> <speaker rend="italics">Chaucer.</speaker> <l>Then let Gaunt take heed.</l></sp> 
 <stage rend="italics">[Music.–Chaucer thanks Robin for the gift, and goes off rejoicingly on one side, whilst the Fairies and Robin trip off on the other. </stage>
<sp who="#CHORUS"> <speaker rend="italics">Chorus.</speaker> <l>Use but well your magic lance,</l> 
<l> You may teach your foes to dance.</l> </sp>
<p> Duet, Robin and Chaucer.–Air, ‘Soldiers’ Chorus,’ Il Trovatore.</p> 
<sp who="#ROBIN"> <speaker rend="italics">Robin.</speaker> <l>For glory your story is like the Trovatore,</l>
<l> Which all the more we hear of it does popular become.</l></sp>
<sp who="#ROBIN"> <speaker rend="italics">Chaucer.</speaker> <l>For glory a story we work out con amore,</l> 
<l> Makes Chaucer feel that he is quite at home.</l> </sp>
<sp who="#ROBIN #CHAUCER"> <speaker rend="italics">Together.</speaker> <l>With (my/your) lance advancing, all the risk (I’m/you’re) chancing,</l> 
<l> So that, if they can’t sing, your foes you’ll set a dancing,</l> 
 <l>With oh my! ah! I thought you’d soon be prancing,</l> 
<l> When you felt the pointed weapon of the gnome.</l></sp> 
 <stage rend="italics">[As they are going off. </stage>
<sp who="#ROBIN"> <speaker rend="italics">Robin.</speaker> <l>Then on, thrust– </l></sp>
<sp who="#CHAUCER"> <speaker rend="italics">Chaucer.</speaker> <l>You must–couldn’t think of taking first </l>
 <l>The precedence of any one who’s super-nat-ur-al.</l></sp> 
<sp who="#ROBIN"> <speaker rend="italics">Robin.</speaker><l> I do think you won’t become the very worst </l>
 <l>Of youths I could have chosen for the gal</l></sp>.<stage> [Exeunt.</stage> </div>
         
<!-- SCENE V -->
         <div type="scene" n='5'>
            <head rend="italic bold">SCENE V. – FRIAR BACON’S OBSERVATORY AT SUNNINGWELL NEAR OXFORD, AND DISTANT VIEW OF JOHN OF GAUNT‘
               S CASTLE, BY SUNSET</head>
            <stage>Over door of observatory, an inscription— ‘<hi rend="italic">Friar Bacon, Licensed Dealer in Black Art.</hi>’ 
               –Other boards about, such as ‘<hi rend="italic">Conjuring Tricks provided, Evening Parties attended</hi>’ — 
               ‘<hi rend="italic">Dissolving Views lent out for the Evening</hi>’ — ‘<hi rend="italic">Love-Philters made up</hi>’— ‘
               <hi rend="italic">Private Lessons in Parlour Magic.</hi>’ Expressive Music.</stage>
            <p>JOHN OF GAUNT enters, mysteriously. Enveloped in a large cloak, and attended by his ‘Squire, whom he dismisses as soon as he 
               finds himself at the house of which he is in search—points to board, ‘<hi rend="italic">Love Philters made up,’</hi> and 
               signifies that is the sort of thing he requires —knocks at door—House Pocus, the Friar’s servant, appears—john desires to 
               see the learned <hi rend="bold italic">Friar Bacon</hi>—man refuses—brings out board—‘<hi rend="italic">The Friar is engaged 
                  in profound study</hi>’—John of Gaunt tries a bribe, and succeeds—the Friar is summoned, and appears with a large frying-pan,
               as if disturbed in frying a rasher of being discovered at this culinary operation, slaps man in, throws frying-pan after him, 
               and attends to John of Gaunt, who takes him mysteriously down stage.</p>
            <sp who="#JOHN">
               <speaker>John.</speaker>
               <l>Before me, I behold, or I’m mistaken,</l>
               <l>The famous necromancer, <hi rend="bold italic">Friar Bacon</hi>!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#FRIAR">
               <speaker>Friar.</speaker>
               <l>Can I believe my eyes? It is—it arn’t—</l>
               <l>Do I behold behind me John of Gaunt?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JOHN">
               <speaker>John.</speaker>
               <l>Hush! Mum! I come incog—would not be known—</l>
               <l>You understand?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#FRIAR">
               <speaker>Friar.</speaker>
               <l>I do !</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JOHN">
               <speaker>John.</speaker>
               <l>Are we alone?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#FRIAR">
               <speaker>Friar.</speaker>
               <l>We are!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JOHN">
               <speaker>John.</speaker>
               <l>‘Tis well! Now listen ;--in your trade,</l>
               <l>I have heard, that curious potions can be made,</l>
               <l>Which if a damsel drinks, she then is sure</l>
               <l>To love the man she couldn’t bear before.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#FRIAR">
               <speaker>Friar.</speaker>
               <l>You have heard aright. Here, Hocus Pocus, quick,</l>
               <l>Bring me my magic drugs—I’ll show you a trick.</l>
            </sp>
            <p>[<hi rend="italic">Hocus Pocus appears from door, and receives instructions—goes off, and returns with large Brazier and
               large Bottle, which the Friar arranges on the stage—The assistant then brings in Packets, severally inscribed ’10,000 a year’
               —‘Unlimited Pin Money’—‘Marriage Settlement’—‘A new Bonnet every Week’—these are successively put into the Bottle.</hi> 
            </p>
            <p>These various things united—mark the list—</p>
            <p>I never knew a woman to resist.</p>
            <p>[<hi rend="italic">Red Fire is kindled below, and the Friar then draws a Phial forth from the Bottle. 
               One trial proves the fact: its worth the heeding,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though some might call this quite a phial proceeding.</p>
            <sp who="#JOHN">
               <speaker>John.</speaker>
               <l>I’ll give the draft at once.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#FRIAR">
               <speaker>Friar.</speaker>
               <l>That’s all right—thank yer—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JOHN">
               <speaker>John.</speaker>
               <l>We’ll talk of that anon.	Now, Friar, learn,</l> 
               <l>To-day, in honor of my safe return,</l> 
               <l>We give a sumptuous spread—it there you walk,</l>
               <l>You are sure to find a friendly knife and fork—</l>
               <l> This ticket will admit you to the fete.</l>
               <l>And there’s a Tournament, if you like to wait.</l>
               <p>[<hi rend="italic">Gives Card, Labelle’</hi></p>
               <p>'ADMIT FRIAR BACON AND FRIEND</p>
               <p>TO THE TOURNAMENT,</p>
               <p>RESERVED SEATS,</p>
               <p>JOHN OF GAUNT.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#FRIAR">
               <speaker>Friar.</speaker>
               <l>You very good, but there’s a small amount—</l>
               <l>Consoling himself.</l>
               <l>Well, I’ll do some business on my own account.</l>
            </sp>
            <p>[<hi rend="italic">Friar calls on Hocus Pocus, who has cleared off the other articles whilst the Friar puts on clean collar, and goes through 
               toilet business, and a Box is brought on, labelled ‘Conjuring Tricks.’ which the Friar takes and goes off with, followed 
               by Hocus Pocus, bearing a Box, labelled ‘Magic Lantern.’—Excunt(Latin)—scene closes.</hi></p>
         </div>
         
<!-- SCENE VI -->
         <div type="scene">
            <head rend="italic bold">SCENE VI.—GOTHIC CORRIDOR, LEADING TO BANQUETING ROOM.</head>
            <p>
               Lively Music. –The Retainers and Servants of John of Gaunt cross the stage, bearing the customary Pantomimic, Viands for 
               the Banquet—after they have crossed, JOHN OF GAUNT enters, with ROSE, whom he drags on—he renews his protestations- she 
               repulses him—CHAUCER, with his lance in his hand, appears at the back, through sliding panel—he observes them—Servant 
               crosses with Goblet of Wine on a tray, which Gaunt takes—unseen by Rose, he turns into it the contents of the phial—offers 
               it to Rose—Chaucer stepping forward at the moment touches it with his Lance, and the contents of the goblet blaze up and 
               are gone.—Through being over the flame, John of Gaunt is seized with a sudden fit of sneezing.—In the confusion, Chaucer 
               escapes with Rose—Servants return—John wreaks his vengeance upon them—Herald enters, with Trumpet and Scroll, labelled 
            </p>
            <p rend="center">‘THE TOURNAMENT HAS COMMENCED’</p>
            <p>All rush off—and scene draws, discovering</p>
         </div>
         
<!-- SCENE VII -->
         <div type="scene">
            <head rend="italic bold">SCENE VII.—THE COURT-YARD OF JOHN OF GAUNT’S CASTLE.</head>
            <p>Pavilion at back—The Lists are formed—The Galleries are filled with spectators—Stage full at the sides, and
               only the centre kept clear for the Combatants—Herald blows a trumpet—Chaucer enters with Rose, and signifies 
               he is confident of success—Large Scroll unfolded, ‘The Victor may claims any Prize in the Lists.’—JOHN OF GAUNT 
               enters and flings down large gauntlet into the arena—Chaucer picks it up, and challenges John of Gaunt, who first of 
               all produces sword and shield—These are no sooner touched by the Magic Lance than the shield expands into a large bouquet 
               of Roses, and the sword opens into a large Fan—John of Gaunt gives them to a Lady of the Court, and then commences a 
               Comic Combat with lances, which ends in the discomfiture of John of Gaunt.—Chaucer goes to the Pavilion and leads Rose down.
            </p>
            <sp who="#CHAUCER">
               <speaker>Chaucer.</speaker>
               <l>Be witness all—this is the prize I choose.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JOHN">
               <speaker>John.</speaker>
               <l>A slight mistake—that maiden I refuse.</l>
               <l>What ho, there!  Seize the caitiff!—now I’m calmer.</l>
               <p>[<hi rend = "italic">Retainers seize Chaucer, whilst John of Gaunt snatches the lamp.</hi></p>
               <l>I have his charms, and now I’ll have his charmer.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#CHAUCER">
               <speaker>Chaucer.</speaker>
               <l>Then thus on Robin Goodfellow I call.</l>
            </sp>
            <p rend = "right italic">Chord—and instantaneous change to</p>
         </div>
         
<!-- SCENE VIII -->
         <div type="scene">
            <head rend="italic bold">SCENE VIII.—THE TRANSPARENT REALMS OF ILLUTIONS, IN THE REGIONS OF POETRY.</head>
            <p rend = "center italic"> All the Fairies discovered.</p>
            <sp who="#ROBIN">
               <speaker>Robin.</speaker>
               <l>Behold our Fairy Court assembled all.</l>
               <l>This lady fair, through no one did imagine it,</l>
               <l>Is in reality Miss Rose Plantagenet.</l>
               <l>Woo’d by the poet in her humble guise,</l>
               <l>He now has fairly won her for his prize.</l>
               <l>To aid the promised revels of to-night,</l>
               <l>As Columbine, henceforth the world delight.</l>
               <p rend = "right italic">[Change Rose to COLUMBINE.</p>
               <l>You, whose poetic feet we nimble see,</l>
               <l>As Harlequin, her lover still shall be</l>
               <p rend = "right italic">[Change Chaucer to HARLEQUIN.</p>
            </sp>
            <p rend = "center">Enter IMAGINATION.</p>
            <sp who = "#IMAGINATION">
               <speaker>Imagination.</speaker> 
               <l>To do without me you were much mistaken,</l>
               <l> From all this change, you shall not save your Bacon.</l>
               <l> So, Friar, stand forth, these robes abandon soon,</l>
               <l>And only have a band on Pantaloon.</l>
               <p rend = "right italics">[Change Friar Bacon to PANTALOON.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who = "#ROBIN">
               <speaker>Robin.</speaker>	
               <l> John of Gaunt escape? In well-know lingo</l>
               <l>I’ll swear he still shall have more thumps, by jingo.</l>
               <l>So, change to Clown—your fame has spread afar—</l>
               <l>And charm each ear with jocund ‘Here we are.;’</l>
               <p rend  = "right italic">[Change John of Gaunt to CLOWN.</p>
               <l><hi rend = "italic">[To Harlequin,]</hi> Your magic lance, sir, this will supersede;</l>
               <l>But still ‘twill answer in the hour of need.	 <hi rend = "right italic">[Gives bat.</hi></l>
            </sp>
            <sp who = "IMAGINATION">
               <speaker>Imagination.</speaker> 
               <l> Yet one word more—behold this Christmas Tree,</l>
               <l>Shall this appear and we no blossom see?</l>
               <l>Not so! Receive this little augmentation</l>
               <l>Of all these ‘pleasures of Imagination!’</l>
               <p rend = "right italic">[SPRITE appears.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who = "#ROBIN">
               <speaker>Robin.</speaker>	
               <l>Now, then, away, once more, to quote the poet,</l>
               <l>In all your merriment be wise—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp who = "#IMAGINATION">
               <speaker>Imagination.</speaker>						
               <l rend = "right">And go it.</l>
            </sp>
         </div>
         
         <div>
            <p rend="bold italic center"> (Comic Business Commences)</p>
            <p rend="bold center">Scene I.—TOY SHOP AND CONFECTIONER’S.</p>
            <p rend="bold center">By Messrs. T. Totum and Toffey</p>
            <p rend="bold center">Scene II.—A SURBURBAN BOARDING-SCHOOL and YOUNG LADIES’ SEMINARY.</p>
            <p rend="bold center">By Mr. Birch and Miss O’Thwackham.</p>
            <p rend="bold center">Scene III.—COTTON BROKERS AND GENERAL DEALERS.</p>
            <p rend="bold center">By A. Sell and E. Sell.</p>
            <p rend="bold center">Scene IV.—GRANDMAMMMA”S DRAWING-ROOM.</p>
            <p rend="bold center">By Jolly Boy and Assistants.</p>
            <p rend="bold center">Scene IV.__LOAN OFFICE, RESTAURANT’S, and FARRIER’S</p>
            <p rend="bold center">By Touch and Go.</p>
            <p rend="bold center">Scene VI.—and Last –The Grand Finale.</p>
            <p rend="bold center">The SALAMANDRINE TEMPLE.</p>
            <p rend="bold">With the Wonder of the World in a cage with a thousand fires, the Children’s Christmas Squibs, and the Triumph of 
               Francisco Frost, with a Darby effect.</p>
         </div>
         
<!-- FOOTNOTE PAGE -->
         <div type="footnote">
            <head>Footnote Page</head>
            <p>THE TABARD.—As the Borough High Street was formerly the great passage into a great part of the kingdom to and from the capital, 
               it was well furnished with inns, the above having been immortalized by Chaucer. The sign is now perverted into ‘The Talbot.’ 
               It originally was ‘The Tabard,’ so called from the sign, a sleeveless coat open on both sides, with a square collar and winged 
               at the shoulders: worn by persons of rank in the wars, with their arms painted on them, that they might be known. The use of 
               this coat is now transferred to the heralds. This was the rendezvous of the jolly pilgrims who formed the group which our 
               ‘father of poetry’ describes sallying out to pay their devotions to the great saint, Thomas a Beckett, whose shrine, for a 
               long time, surperseded almost every other, being resorted to down to the Reformation by pilgrims from every part of Christendom. 
               The sign was changed from the ‘Tabard’ to the ‘Talbot,’ about the year 1676. The following inscription used to appear on the 
               frieze of the beams which hung across the road, and from the centre of which the sign was suspended.—‘This is the inn where 
               Sir Jeffery Chaucer and the nine-and -twenty pilgrims lay, in their journey to Canterbury, anno 1383.</p>
         </div>
         
<!-- ACKNOWLEDGEMENT PAGE -->
         <div type="acknowledgement">
            <head>Acknowledgement Page</head>
            <p>The Scenery (from historical authorities), with the Grand Transformation Effects, the greatest and most extraordinary ever yet 
               attempted, by Mr. GATES, assisted by Messrs. Albert Callcott, W. Broadfoot, Gourie, Lambert, Devigne, Buckley, and Atkins.</p>
            <p>For an Illustrative Pictorial Tableau of the residence of the Ancient Magician, Friar Bacon, at Sunningwell, the valuable 
               services of Mr. CHARLES JAMES have been specially secured, whose artistic pencil will add and additional charm to the highly 
               elaborate scenic illustrations.</p>
            <p>The Pantomime invented and written by the celebrated FRANCESCO FROST, Esq.</p>
            <p>The Music by J. H. TULLY. Esq.</p>
            <p>The Ballet and Dances by Signor MILANO.</p>
            <p>The Comical Facial Expressions and Quaint by QUICK DIGIT.</p>
            <p>The Gas Appointments by Mr. PEPPER and Assistants.</p>
            <p>The Costumes by Mr. LAURI</p>
            <p>The Properties by Mr. MOON.</p>
            <p>The Extensive Machinery by Mr. SLOMAN.</p>
            <p>The Box Department by Mr. CHARLES NUGENT, of Her Majesty’s Theatre, to to whom a telegraph or letter will secure places 
               without charge for booking.</p>
            <p>And the whole Arranged and Produced under the entire direction of Mr. T. H. HIGGIE, Stage-manager.</p>
         </div>
         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
