<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Harlequin and friar Bacon</title>
            <author>Francesco Frost</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Bonnie Ha, Cassidy Fallon Vierling, Echo Yu</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Seattle, WA</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>University of Washington, Seattle</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2024-02​-XX</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>We were able to read the pamphlet in the collection classroom located on the base level
            of Allen Library North. 
               <bibl>
                  <title>Harlequin and Friar Bacon</title>
                  <author>Francesco Frost</author>
                  <publisher>The Music-Publishing Company</publisher>
                  <date>1863 </date>
                  <pubPlace>London: 19 Peter's Hill, St. Paul's</pubPlace>
               </bibl>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>
            <p>Editorial notes in the 1863's edition have not been reproduced</p>
         </samplingDecl>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization method="silent">
               <p>Original punctuation conventions in the 1863's edition will be retained as much as possible</p>
            </normalization>
            <interpretation>
               <p>Italics will be recorded without interpretation</p>
            </interpretation>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition>caps, italics, bold</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>“Harlequin and Friar Bacon” is a British pantomime play from the collection of Glenn Hughes who used the collection in the 1930s and 1940s as a tool for research and teaching his students in the drama program at the University of Washington. It comes from a collection of over 3,000 plays, the majority British. It is likely that “Harlequin and Friar Bacon” belongs to the subset within the collection of works added from a single contributing collection, all of which were made as sales or gifts to the audience of a performance, mainly consisting of Christmas extravaganzas, pantomimes, and burlesques. Pantomimes are usually performed around Christmas and are comedies that often include slapstick humor, jokes, innuendos, magic, fairies, and gender reversal.</p>
	 <p>The focus of our edition of “Harlequin and Friar Bacon” is digitizing the original play to become accessible to actors and students who are interested in its content, whether that be for purposes of studying drama or gleaning an understanding of the content of historical plays. Pantomimes are still performed in the United States but with less frequency and popularity than in England, so the edition will also function to introduce actors to studies of plays on a global scale.</p>
	 <p>Our edition features a transcription which is intended to maintain as much of the original content as possible, including preserving the British spellings for words as opposed to Americanizing them. Racial slurs have been redacted and given note in the end notes if relevant to understanding the passage. Any italics and bold are preserved as they are displayed in the original play. In the original print, advertisements line the jacket and are interspersed throughout the text, which have not been preserved in this digital edition because it is not intended for viewing by audiences but by actors.</p>
         <div type='editorial'>
            <listPerson>
               <!-- GT: good! Is this a cast list? You could also use the TEI element <castList>: https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-castList.html
                  The other thing I'd suggest is giving more evocative xml:id's. Eg. for the first one: @xml:id="goodfellows" , etc. 
                  The notes are terrific. Nice job. -->
               <person xml:id="char1" role="fictional">
                  <persName>
                     <surname>Goodfellows</surname>
                     <forename>Robin</forename>
                     <!-- GT: here you don't need <choice>. You only use <choice> when you present 2 options. Here there's just one -->
                     <choice>
                        <orig>The Puck</orig>
                     </choice>
                  </persName>
                  <note>
                     <p>In English folklore, The Puck, also known as Goodfellows, are/is a domestic and nature sprite, demon, or fairy.</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="char2" role="fictional" sex="m">
                  <persName>Oberon</persName>
                  <note>
                     <p>Oberon is a king of the fairies in medieval and Renaissance literature. He is best known as a character in William 
                        Shakespeare's play A Midsummer Night's Dream, in which he is King of the Fairies and spouse of Titania, Queen of 
                        the Fairies.</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="char3" role="fictional" sex="m">
                  <persName>Harry Bailly or Harry Bailey</persName>
                  <note>
                     <p>The Host is a character who plays a key role in and throughout Geoffrey Chaucer's The Canterbury Tales. He is the 
                        owner of the Tabard Inn in London, where the pilgrimage begins and he agrees to travel on the pilgrimage, and promises to judge both the tales the pilgrims tell, and disputes among the pilgrims.</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="char4" role="real" sex="m">
                  <persName>Geoffrey Chaucer</persName>
                  <birth>1340s</birth>
                  <death>25 October 1400</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>Geoffrey Chaucer was an English poet, author, and civil servant best known for The Canterbury Tales. He has been 
                        called the "father of English literature", or, alternatively, the "father of English poetry".</p>
                  </note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="char5" role="real" sex="m">
                  <persName>
                     John of Gaunt
                  </persName>
                  <birth>6 March 1340</birth>
                  <death>3 February 1399</death>
                  <note>
                     <p>John of Gaunt, Duke of Lancaster was an English royal prince, military leader, and statesman. He was the fourth son of 
                        King Edward III of England, and the father of King Henry IV. </p>
                  </note>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
            
            <bibl n="1">
               <title>Puck (folklore)</title>
               <!-- GT: use the @when attribute with <date> -->
               <date>This page was last edited on 26 January 2024, at 15:00 (UTC).</date>
               <!-- GT: And use <ptr/> if there's no content:
                  <ptr target="URL"/> -->
               <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Puck_(folklore)"/>
            </bibl>
            
            <bibl n="2">
               <title>Oberon</title>
               <date>This page was last edited on 21 January 2024, at 15:31 (UTC).</date>
               <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oberon"/>
            </bibl>
            
            <bibl n="3">
               <title>The Host (Canterbury Tales)</title>
               <date>This page was last edited on 25 January 2022, at 13:16 (UTC).</date>
               <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Host"/>
            </bibl>
            
            <bibl n="4">
               <title>Geoffrey Chaucer</title>
               <date>This page was last edited on 7 February 2024, at 09:54 (UTC).</date>
               <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geoffrey_Chaucer"/>
            </bibl>
            
            <bibl n="5">
               <title>John of Gaunt</title>
               <date>This page was last edited on 8 February 2024, at 16:06 (UTC).</date>
               <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_of_Gaunt"/>
            </bibl>
		 
	    <bibl n="6">
		<title>19th century acting editions collection, 1762-1946</title>
		<date>Historical note and collection information added 2017</date>
		<ref target="https://archiveswest.orbiscascade.org/ark:80444/xv656279"/>

	    <bibl n="7">
		<title>A Complete Guide to Pantomime</title>
		<date>03 June 2022</date>
		<ref target="https://www.blackpoolgrand.co.uk/complete-guide-to-pantomime"/>
         </div><!-- GT: I think you're missing a closing </bibl> here... -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
