<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Shakespeare Club of Port Gamble, Washington</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This edition covers the daybook's entries from December 14 1896 to January 11 1987.
               Residents of Port Gamble, Washington may be interested in reading this edition,
               particularly the descendants of the Gove family. Upon doing research, our group
               realized that the Gove family may have been an important family in the town that
               worked in tugboat service, which was essential in Kitsap County. There is even a
               historical house/landmark in town called the Gove House. We imagine that the
               residents of Port Gamble and descendants of the Gove family would be interested in
               this edition as it gives a glimpse into what life and leisure was like in the late
               1800s. </p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The manuscript are meeting minutes contained within a “Day Book” ruled planner of 150
               pages. The minutes are handwritten and contain descriptive paragraphs interspersed
               with cast lists for their reading assignments. Included are two loose-leaf pages of
               handwritten letters to the club president. 
               <bibl>
                  <title>Special Collections Manuscripts and Archives, University of Washington Libraries; Shakespeare Club Records</title>
                  <author>Mrs. Ames</author>
                  <date> December 14, 1896 to January 11, 1987</date>
                     <msIdentifier>
                          <settlement>Seattle</settlement>
                          <repository>Special Collections Manuscripts and Archives, University og Washington Libraries</repository>
                          <idno type ="OCLC">23949118</idno>
                     </msIdentifier>
               </bibl>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Some text here.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
