<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Jasper N. Bertram Personal Documents and Correspondance</title>
            <author>Various Authors</author>
            <editor>Jules Lockett, Sofia Posada, Nic Staley</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information - how we are publishing in the context of our class</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is where you talk about your source: i.e. the pamphlet itself. You can describe
               in your own terms some info about it: where and how you were able to read it; you can
               say anything you want here, about the physical document, if you'd like. No need for
               full context, since you'll discuss that in your editorial intro. Then list the full
               bibliographic info. Keep it all inside the paragraph tags, or you'll get an error.
               
               The J.N. Bertram letters are a collection of letters that include personal
               corrisponse, business corrispondece, and newspaper clippings. The material
               transcribed in this edition is a sample from those three categories, including
               handwritten letters, typewritten corrispondece, and newpaper clippings. 
         <bibl> 
            <title>Jasper N. Bertram Letters</title>
            <author>Various</author>
            <publisher>Personal archives, unpublished</publisher>
            <date>date</date>
            <idno type="Accession_No">4215-001</idno>
                </bibl> 
            </p> 
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>All spellings were taken directly from the source, with no editing.</p>
            </normalization>
            <punctuation>
               <p>info about punctuation</p>
            </punctuation>
            <quotation>
               <p>info about how you approached quoted text</p>
            </quotation>
            <correction>
               <p>If you discovered errors in your text, you can talk here about where you decided
                  to correct them or not - Errors were left unedited; any mispellings that appear in
                  the text were directly from the source.</p>
            </correction>
            <interpretation>
               <p>You can add interpretive info here.</p>
            </interpretation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Some text here.</p>
         <p>This is Nic trying to use GitHub, send <hi rend="caps">help</hi></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
