<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Jasper N. Bertram Personal Documents and Correspondance</title>
            <author>Various Authors</author>
            <editor>Jules Lockett, Sofia Posada, Nic Staley</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>While these documents represent a small fraction of the materials present within
               archive of Jasper N. Bertram, we hope to attach this TEI encoding to the archival
               record so that it may aid in distribution and availability of these materials
               digitally.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p> The J.N. Bertram letters are a collection of letters that include personal
               correspondence, business correspondence, and newspaper clippings. The material
               transcribed in this edition is a sample from those three categories, including
               handwritten letters, typewritten correspondences, and newspaper clippings. 
               <bibl>
                  <title>Jasper N. Bertram Papers</title>
                  <author>Various</author>
                  <publisher>Personal archives, unpublished</publisher>
                  <date>Early 1900's: 1902-1909</date>
                  <idno type="Accession_No">4215-001</idno>
                  <idno type="box_#">3 of 7</idno>
                  <idno type="folder_#">3-2 "General Correspondance"</idno>
               </bibl>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>In an effort to preserve authorial intent of manuscript documents, primarily
                  comprised of letters of correspondence, we have chosen to leave all spelling and
                  grammar errors. This choice was done in order for our edition to reflect the
                  people composing the documents and the time period in which they were written.</p>
            </normalization>
            <punctuation>
               <p>Some letters contain no punctuation at all. No corrections were made to preserve
                  authorial voice.</p>
            </punctuation>
            <correction>
               <p>Errors were left unedited; any misspellings or odd capitalizations that appear in
                  the text were directly from the source. Places where text is unidentifiable will
                  be marked &lt;gap/&gt;</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Some text here.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
