<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Jasper N. Bertram Papers</title>
            <author>Various Authors</author>
            <editor>Jules Lockett, Sofia Posada, Nic Staley</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>While these documents represent a small fraction of the materials present within
               archive of Jasper N. Bertram, we hope to attach this TEI encoding to the archival
               record so that it may aid in distribution and availability of these materials
               digitally.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p> The Jasper N. Bertram papers are a collection of letters that include personal
               correspondence, business correspondence, and newspaper clippings. The material
               transcribed in this edition is a sample from those three categories, including
               handwritten letters, typewritten correspondences, and newspaper clippings. <bibl>
                  <title>Jasper N. Bertram Papers</title>
                  <author>Various</author>
                  <publisher>Personal archives, unpublished</publisher>
                  <date>Early 1900's: 1902-1909</date>
                  <idno type="Accession_No">4215-001</idno>
                  <idno type="box_#">3 of 7</idno>
                  <idno type="folder_#">3-2 "General Correspondance"</idno>
               </bibl>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>In an effort to preserve authorial intent of manuscript documents, we have chosen
                  to leave all spelling and grammatical errors unedited. This choice was made in
                  order for our edition to reflect authorial voices of the various persons
                  represented in this collection, and the time period in which the documents were
                  written.</p>
            </normalization>
            <punctuation>
               <p>Some letters contain no punctuation. No corrections were made to preserve
                  authorial voice.</p>
            </punctuation>
            <correction>
               <p>Errors were left unedited; any misspellings or odd capitalizations that appear in
                  the text were directly from the source. Places where text is unidentifiable will
                  be marked &lt;gap/&gt;</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <titlePage>
            <titlePart>...</titlePart>
         </titlePage>
         <div type="editorial_intro">
            <p>The present documents reflect a small sample of the corpus known as the Jasper N.
               Bertram papers. These papers contain an eclectic mix of letters, newspaper clippings,
               business documents, greeting cards, pamphlets, personal correspondences, and notes.
               The documents are printed, typewritten, and handwritten; some contain a mix of text
               types. The archive within the University of Washington Special Collections provides a
               brief <ref type="note" target="#n1">biographical overview</ref> of Jasper N.
               Bertram's life.</p>
            <p>While these documents represent a small fraction of the materials present within the
               archive of Jasper N. Bertram, we hope to attach this TEI encoding to the archival
               record so that it may aid in distribution and availability of these materials
               digitally. The duration of Jasper N. Bertram's life encompasses a critical time in
               our nation's history, from the Civil War, through the Industrial Revolution and the
               First World War, to his death during the Roaring Twenties. The chosen documents
               provide readers with a unique historical perspective of an individual with interests
               rooted in Seattle and beyond.</p>
            <p>In an effort to preserve authorial intent of manuscript documents, we have chosen to
               leave all spelling and grammatical errors unedited. This choice was made in order for
               our edition to reflect authorial voices of the various persons represented in this
               collection, and the time period in which the documents were written. The excerpts
               chosen represent the interests of the editors while also serving to present a sample
               of multiple document types found throughout the collection.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p>Main text.<ref type="note" target="#n2">John C. Winston Company</ref>.</p>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="endnotes">
            <note xml:id="n1">"Jasper N. Bertram (1840-1928) was born in Wayne, Kentucky. He
               enlisted in the Civil War with the Kentucky Volunteers, 9th Regiment, 3rd Division,
               1862-1864. He married Mary Ann Garrett on January 1, 1866, in Overton, Tennessee and
               they had five children. He was listed as a school teacher in Kentucky in 1873 and a
               Republican Party worker in 1882 in the 3rd Congressional District. After his first
               wife died in 1888, he moved to Seattle where he was district manager and salesman. He
               married Mary Huselby in 1896. He died on July 1, 1928 in Seattle, Washington." <ref
                  type="biblio" target="#source1">See source 1</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2">"Philedelphia book publisher, 1884 to 1960, original specialty
               Bibles." <ref type="biblio" target="#source2">See source 2</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3"> Chelan county is located in central Washington <ref type="biblio" target="#source3">See source 3</ref></note>
            <note xml:id="n4">Lakeside an unincorporated community located in Chelan County <ref type="biblio" target="#source4">See source 3</ref></note>
         </div>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="source1">
                  <title>Jasper N. Bertram papers</title>
                  <ref target="https://archiveswest.orbiscascade.org/ark:/80444/xv10931"/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="source2">
                  <title>John C. Winston Company</title>
                  <ref target="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q21808712"/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="source3">
                  <title>Chelan County</title>
                  <ref target="https://www.co.chelan.wa.us/"/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="source4">
                  <title>Lakeside</title>
                  <ref target="https://edits.nationalmap.gov/apps/gaz-domestic/public/search/names/1521865"/>
               </bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
