<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="teibp.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <!--Use this as the master doc for our final portfolio-->
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Jasper N. Bertram Papers</title>
            <author>Various Authors</author>
            <editor>Jules Lockett, Sofia Posada, Nic Staley</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>While these documents represent a small fraction of the materials present within
               archive of Jasper N. Bertram, we hope to attach this TEI encoding to the archival
               record so that it may aid in distribution and availability of these materials
               digitally.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p> The Jasper N. Bertram papers are a collection of letters that include personal
               correspondence, business correspondence, and newspaper clippings. The material
               transcribed in this edition is a sample from those three categories, including
               handwritten letters, typewritten correspondences, and newspaper clippings. <bibl>
                  <title>Jasper N. Bertram Papers</title>
                  <author>Various</author>
                  <publisher>Personal archives, unpublished</publisher>
                  <date>Early 1900's: 1902-1909</date>
                  <idno type="Accession_No">4215-001</idno>
                  <idno type="box_#">3 of 7</idno>
                  <idno type="folder_#">3-2 "General Correspondance"</idno>
               </bibl>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>In an effort to preserve authorial intent of manuscript documents, we have chosen
                  to leave all spelling and grammatical errors unedited. This choice was made in
                  order for our edition to reflect authorial voices of the various persons
                  represented in this collection, and the time period in which the documents were
                  written.</p>
            </normalization>
            <punctuation>
               <p>Some letters contain no punctuation. No corrections were made to preserve
                  authorial voice.</p>
            </punctuation>
            <correction>
               <p>Errors were left unedited; any misspellings or odd capitalizations that appear in
                  the text were directly from the source. Places where text is unidentifiable will
                  be marked &lt;gap/&gt;</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <titlePage>
            <titlePart>...</titlePart>
         </titlePage>
         <div type="editorial_intro">
            <p>The present documents reflect a small sample of the corpus known as the Jasper N.
               Bertram papers. These papers contain an eclectic mix of letters, newspaper clippings,
               business documents, greeting cards, pamphlets, personal correspondences, and notes.
               The documents are printed, typewritten, and handwritten; some contain a mix of text
               types. The archive within the University of Washington Special Collections provides a
               brief <ref type="note" target="#n1">biographical overview</ref> of Jasper N.
               Bertram's life.</p>
            <p>While these documents represent a small fraction of the materials present within the
               archive of Jasper N. Bertram, we hope to attach this TEI encoding to the archival
               record so that it may aid in distribution and availability of these materials
               digitally. The duration of Jasper N. Bertram's life encompasses a critical time in
               our nation's history, from the Civil War, through the Industrial Revolution and the
               First World War, to his death during the Roaring Twenties. The chosen documents
               provide readers with a unique historical perspective of an individual with interests
               rooted in Seattle and beyond.</p>
            <p>In an effort to preserve authorial intent of manuscript documents, we have chosen to
               leave all spelling and grammatical errors unedited. This choice was made in order for
               our edition to reflect authorial voices of the various persons represented in this
               collection, and the time period in which the documents were written. The excerpts
               chosen represent the interests of the editors while also serving to present a sample
               of multiple document types found throughout the collection.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text>
            <body>
               <opener>
                  <orgName ref="#Cralle"><hi rend="caps">J B. Cralle &amp; Co.</hi></orgName>
                  <dateline><date when="1907-04-30"><hi rend="caps">Apr</hi> 30
                     1907</date></dateline>
                  <stamp rend="caps">Atty's.</stamp>
                  <salute>Dear Sir:</salute></opener>

               <!-- GT: This is another small detail but potentially a headache down the line. Since you encode the <lb>, you might think about how to deal with
		    the hyphen. The problem is if you want to output this without the line-break, the hyphen will be there. So you idea would be to 
		    encode the hyphen as well. Sometimes you see something like: <pc type="EOLhyphen"-</pc>. <pc> = punctuation character. This way,
		    if you don't output the <lb>, you can also withhold the hyphen from the output -->

               <p>We have recieved and filled your claim with the proper offi-<lb/>cial of the
                  Government, and will prosecute it to a final settlement.<lb/></p>

               <p>Prior to <date when="1900-06-06">June 6, 1900</date>, attorneys' fee were deducted
                  and<lb/> paid them by the Government upon the allowance of claims, but this
                  <lb/>practice in reagrd to fees as follows:<lb/></p>

               <p>"<hi rend="caps">Provided</hi>, That in the settlement of claims of officers,<lb/>
                  soldiers, sailors, and marines, of their repreentatives,<lb/> and all other claims
                  for pay and allowances within the jurisdiction<lb/> of the Auditor for the
                  <lb/>War Department or the Auditor for the Navy Department, presented and filed
                  hereafter in which it is<lb/> the present practice to make deductions of
                  attorneys' fees from<lb/> the amound found due, no deductions of fees for
                  attorneys or <lb/>agents shall hereafter be made, but the draft, check or
                  warrant<lb/> for the full amount found due shall be delivered the payee<lb/> in
                  person or sent to his bona fide post office adress (residence <lb/>of place of
                  business.)"<lb/></p>

               <p>Under this act fees are held to be a matter of adjust-<lb/>ment between claimants
                  and attorneys, and the Government <hi rend="caps">does not <lb/>now deduct and pay
                     fees to attorneys as formerly</hi> in any of the above <lb/>described claims
                  filed since the Act of Congress approved <date when="1900-06-06">June 6,<lb/>
                     1900</date>.<lb/></p>

               <p>The former practice of the Government in deducting and <lb/>paying the attorney
                  fees upon settlement with the claimants was <lb/>greatly preferred by us, but the
                  law javing changed this method as <lb/>stated, we are obliged to meet the new
                  order of things.<lb/></p>

               <p>You will, therefore, please remit us the sum of two dollars <lb/>($2) immediately
                  upon receipt of this letter, to be applied to the <lb/>fee in your case, for
                  bounty pay and other dues.<lb/></p>

               <p>We must ask that you comply with this request at once!<lb/></p>

               <closer>
                  <salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
                  <signed><orgName ref="#Cralle">J. B Cralle &amp; Co</orgName></signed>
               </closer>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="endnotes">
                  <note>
                     <note xml:id="Cralle">JB Cralle &amp; Co were claim and pension attorneys.
                        Their firm was located in Washington DC.<ref type="biblio" target="#source6"
                        />See source 6</note>
                  </note>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text>
            <body>
               <opener rend="cursive">
                  <placeName>B Green KY</placeName>
                  <dateline><date when="1903-10-18">Oct 18th 03</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <persName ref="#JN_Bertram">J. N</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Mary_Bertram"
                     >Marry Bertram</persName>
                  <salute>Dear brother &amp; Sister</salute>
               </opener>
               <div rend="cursive">
                  <p>After waiting a long time we received your nice letter and was so proud of it,
                     yes I tried to have the family reunion at any of our houses but failed hence
                     the disapointment to all</p>
                  <p>No <persName>John Green</persName> has never been for the medisan that you left
                     for him his only child is it The faint of death if not dead So I guess he won't
                     want it</p>
                  <p>I have never seen your discharge you must to have lost them before you came
                     here</p>
                  <p>We shall be so proud if you</p>
                  <p>will stop with us on your way to <placeName type="state">Washington</placeName>
                     we shall expect it and write us at once or as Soon as your can aseertain the
                     facts </p>
                  <p><persName ref="#Mary_Bertram">Mary</persName> we have got to be <add
                        place="above">^one</add> of the uppertens since you was here Street cars are
                     running out by our house you can get on, at the depo and get off at our gate
                     the cars run to the cemetry boatlanding &amp; fairground</p>
                  <p>We are getting along the best kind we have a change of diet every day bread and
                     meat one day &amp; meat and bread the next so when you come you Shall Share
                     with us</p>
                  <p>We are having Scarlett feaver &amp; diptheria have had several deths</p>
                  <p>have had Several deths we have a very Serious case close to us it <persName>J.
                        H. Hollands</persName> his 12 year <add place="below">^old </add>boy but is
                     on the rode to helth again</p>
                  <p>no new calls that I know of brother Sister be shure to spend a while with us us
                     you <add place="below">^go</add> North or Northwest feeal that that will be our
                     last meeting and parting without Sum unexcpected change ___
                        <persName>Omar</persName> is at <placeName>Birm-ingham</placeName>
                     <persName>Ala Bruce</persName> at <placeName>Indiana-polis</placeName>
                     <persName>Hial</persName> excpects to go to <persName>Omar</persName> &amp;
                        <persName>Carol</persName> is getting a long as usual has two pet Squieruls
                     and a fish his little gray man got her high braK(unintelligible scribble and
                     struckout) the <date when="1903-07-01">first of July</date> and hasent used her
                     any Since but think he can use her in a few days now write us as soon as you
                     can</p>
               </div>
               <closer>
                  <salute>as ever your Brother</salute>
                  <signed><persName ref="#DH_Bertram">DH Bertram</persName></signed>
               </closer>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="endnotes">
                  <note xml:id="JN_Bertram">"Jasper N. Bertram (1840-1928) was born in Wayne,
                     Kentucky. He enlisted in the Civil War with the Kentucky Volunteers, 9th
                     Regiment, 3rd Division, 1862-1864. He married Mary Ann Garrett on January 1,
                     1866, in Overton, Tennessee and they had five children. He was listed as a
                     school teacher in Kentucky in 1873 and a Republican Party worker in 1882 in the
                     3rd Congressional District. After his first wife died in 1888, he moved to
                     Seattle where he was district manager and salesman. He married Mary Huselby in
                     1896. He died on July 1, 1928 in Seattle, Washington." <ref type="biblio"
                        target="#source1">See source 1</ref>.</note>
                  <note xml:id="Mary_Bertram"/>
                  <note xml:id="Diptheria">Diphtheria is a bacterial respiratory illness that
                     primarily affects children under 5. The disease was considered highly
                     contagious and deadly during its height, at the end of the 19th and beginning
                     of the 20th century. Before the first vaccine was created in the 1890s, 1 out
                     of 10 children infected by the disease died. Although, the vaccine was not
                     widely distributed until the 1920s. <ref type="biblio" target="#source5">See
                        source 5</ref></note>
                  <note xml:id="DH_Bertram">DH Bertam was the brother of Jasper N. Bertram</note>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
      <back>
         <div type="endnotes">
            <note xml:id="n1">"Jasper N. Bertram (1840-1928) was born in Wayne, Kentucky. He
               enlisted in the Civil War with the Kentucky Volunteers, 9th Regiment, 3rd Division,
               1862-1864. He married Mary Ann Garrett on January 1, 1866, in Overton, Tennessee and
               they had five children. He was listed as a school teacher in Kentucky in 1873 and a
               Republican Party worker in 1882 in the 3rd Congressional District. After his first
               wife died in 1888, he moved to Seattle where he was district manager and salesman. He
               married Mary Huselby in 1896. He died on July 1, 1928 in Seattle, Washington." <ref
                  type="biblio" target="#source1">See source 1</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2">"Philedelphia book publisher, 1884 to 1960, original specialty
               Bibles." <ref type="biblio" target="#source2">See source 2</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3"> Chelan county is located in central Washington <ref type="biblio"
                  target="#source3">See source 3</ref></note>
            <note xml:id="n4">Lakeside an unincorporated community located in Chelan County <ref
                  type="biblio" target="#source4">See source 3</ref></note>

         </div>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Bertram_Papers">
                  <title>Jasper N. Bertram papers</title>
                  <ref target="https://archiveswest.orbiscascade.org/ark:/80444/xv10931"/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Winston_Company">
                  <title>John C. Winston Company</title>
                  <ref target="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q21808712"/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Chelan_County">
                  <title>Chelan County</title>
                  <ref target="https://www.co.chelan.wa.us/"/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Lakeside">
                  <title>Lakeside</title>
                  <ref
                     target="https://edits.nationalmap.gov/apps/gaz-domestic/public/search/names/1521865"
                  />
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Diphtheria">
                  <title>Diphtheria</title>
                  <ref
                     target="https://artsci.case.edu/dittrick/2014/04/29/deadly-diphtheria-the-childrens-plague/"
                  />
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Cralle_Co">
                  <title>JB Cralle &amp; Co</title>
                  <ref
                     target="https://www.nps.gov/common/uploads/teachers/lessonplans/General%20Affadavit%201905.pdf"
                  /></bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
