<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hypontism and Hypnotic Suggestion</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed by</resp>
               <name xml:id="JS">Jake Short</name>
               <name xml:id="LD">Lilly Durham</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>
               <name ref="#JS">Jake Short</name>
               <name ref="#LD">Lilly Durham</name>
            </authority>
            <pubPlace>Seattle, WA</pubPlace>
            <date when="2024-02-12">2024-02​-12</date>
            <availability>
               <p>Available for purposes of academic research and teaching only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p> 
            <bibl>
               <title type="main">HYPNOTISM AND HYPNOTIC SUGGESTION</title>
               <title type="subordinate">A SCIENTIFIC TREATISE OF THE USES AND POSSIBILITIES OF HYPNOTISM, SUGGESTION AND ALLIED PHENOMENA.</title>
               <editor>
                  <name>E. VIRGIL NEAL, A. M., LL. D.</name>
                  <name>CHARLES S. CLARK, M.A.</name>
               </editor>
               <publisher>New York State Publishing Company</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
               <idno type="lc">BD 1121 H6 1900 pt.1. pt.4</idno>
            </bibl>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Original punctuation conventions have been retained.</p>
            </normalization>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Hyphenated words that appear at the end of the line have been reformed.</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <interpretation>
               <p>Emphasis throughout text, including titles and headings, has been recorded and retained.</p>
            </interpretation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="introduction">
            <head><emph rend="bold"><title type="book">SUGGESTIONS AND DIRECTIONS FOR THE STUDY OF PERSONAL MAGNETISM
               AND HYPNOTISM.</title></emph></head>
            <head>By X. LA MOTTE SAGE, A. M., Ph. D., LL. D., formerly Professor in Pieree College,
               Philadelphia, Pa.</head>
            <head><emph rend="bold">READ THE INSTRUCTIONS VERY CAREFULLY.</emph></head>
            <p>Be sure that you thoroughly understand just what to do before attempting to hypnotize
               anyone.</p>
            <p>If you stop and hesitate and wonder what to do next, you will never influence
               anybody. Go about your work in a business-like way and show people by your actions
               that you thoroughly understand what you are doing.</p>
            <p>You must not expect to hypnotize everybody you try. Remember all successful operators
               and noted hypnotists came to be such only by long practical experience.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <l><emph rend="bold">PERSEVERANCE.</emph></l>
            <p>If you do not succeed with the first five or ten that you try, do not give up, but
               continue trying. Try twenty or thirty different persons, or more if necessary, and
               just as sure as the sun shines you will find someone whom you can hypnotize. You
               cannot fail if you persevere and read our instructions carefully. After you hypnotize
               one or two, it will be easy, and soon you can affect the majority of those whom you
               try; and with still more practice will be able readily to hypnotize 70 or 90 per
               cent.</p>
            <p>Determine to succeed and you will succeed. If you undertake this study in a
               half-hearted way, if you go about it in a perfunctory sort of manner it were better a
               thousand times over that you never undertook it. The greater your deficiencies in
               personal magnetism the more difficult will it be for you to master these sciences,
               and the more evident your need of further knowledge of this mysterious power. Bear in
               mind that perseverance is the price of success; knowledge does not come unsought.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <l><emph rend="bold">THE STUMBLING BLOCK</emph></l>
            <p>is hypnotizing the first one. Then remember that a good hypnotist might possibly try
               ten people and not hypnotize any of' them, because they resist. They may say they do
               not, though they do. With different people the whole ten might be affected. You
               should make due allowance for this. Should you not meet with the success you
               anticipate, it will probably be because you do not follow our directions. Many think
               they are doing just as the instructions direct, when in reality they are doing
               nothing of the kind. Read the instructions carefully and slowly a number of times and
               study them well until you know each step as well as you know your A, B, C's, and if
               you have any determination or perseverance whatever, you cannot possibly make a
               failure. You are as certain to succeed as one and one are two. After the ice is
               broken, that is, after you have hypnotized the first one or two, you will have
               confidence, and you yourself will be'surprised and mystified at your work.</p>
            <l><emph rend="bold">SUGGESTIONS.</emph></l>
            <p>You must be sure to give all your suggestions in a very positive tone. A feeble,
               whining way of speaking never accomplishes anything. Be a person of some force of
               character. Speak positively and directly to your subject, and influence is certain.
               Do not give up until you have tried at least fifty persons between the ages of 15 and
               30, and be sure while trying each one that you do just as the instructions direct. We
               ask you to do this because we know positively that after you hypnotize one, the work
               will be very easy and you can influence a large percentage. There is a certain knack
               required, and while nearly all persons get this knack very readily from our
               instructions and can soon hypnotize, still there is occasionally a person who has to
               try over and over before he acquires just the proper method of procedure. Many,
               however, who find the work a little difficult at first, make the finest
               hypnotists.</p>
            <l><emph rend="bold">CONFIDENCE.</emph></l>
            <p>To be successful in influencing people one must have confidence and perseverance. A
               weak, vacillating disposition never accomplishes anything. People will influence you
               or you will iiffuence them; it is for you to decide whether you will direct or be
               directed, whether you will be a master or a servant. Self-esteem, stubbornness, and
               an arrogant, haughty disposition are not the necessary elements with which to control
               people.</p>
            <l><emph rend="bold">INBORN POWER.</emph></l>
            <p>There is a subtle, unseen force by which people are influenced, and the minds of the
               multitude swayed. This secret power may ,be acquired by everyone who is willing to
               take the time and trouble to develop it. An all-wise Creator has not given it to the
               few, it is inborn in every person, and it is only necessary for one to put forth a
               proper effort to achieve the success which God intended.</p>
            <l><emph rend="bold">PERSONAL INFLUENCE.</emph></l>
            <p>In taking up the study of these subjects you are entering a new field of science, a
               new sphere of life, you are taking a very important step; your success in these
               studies means much to you; in fact, it determines the position in life which you will
               hereafter occupy; it matters not what your other capabilities or intellectual
               attainments are, if you lack the power and ability to influence people you will never
               achieve your full measure of success.</p>
            <p>If you master the sciences 'of personal magnetism and hypnotism you will have a
               thorough knowledge of the philosophy of personal influence, of the laws by which the
               human mind is molded and swayed, of that intangible and subtle power which controls
               where bayonets fail.</p>
            <l><emph rend="bold">IMPORTANT TRIFLES.</emph></l>
            <p>It matters not how unimportant the instructions may seem to you, or how simple they
               are, make up your mind to follow them in every detail; do not pass judgment upon
               anything until you have given it a fair trial; remember the greatest things in life
               are often the simplest. It may seem to you that the instructions are too simple to
               produce the astounding results which are claimed for them, but, if you will master
               them, if you will only give them a thorough trial, you will be more enthusiastic in
               their praises than the authors of this course. </p>
         </div>


      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
