<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hypontism and Hypnotic Suggestion</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed by</resp>
               <name xml:id="JS">Jake Short</name>
               <name xml:id="LD">Lilly Durham</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>
               <name ref="#JS">Jake Short</name>
               <name ref="#LD">Lilly Durham</name>
            </authority>
            <pubPlace><placeName><settlement>Seattle</settlement>,
               <region>WA</region></placeName></pubPlace>
            <date when="2024-02-12">2024-02​-12</date>
            <availability>
               <p>Available for purposes of academic research and teaching only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="main">HYPNOTISM AND HYPNOTIC SUGGESTION</title>
                  <title type="subordinate">A SCIENTIFIC TREATISE OF THE USES AND POSSIBILITIES OF
                     HYPNOTISM, SUGGESTION AND ALLIED PHENOMENA.</title>
                  <editor>
                     <name>E. VIRGIL NEAL, A. M., LL. D.</name>
                     <name>CHARLES S. CLARK, M.A.</name>
                  </editor>
                  <publisher>New York State Publishing Company</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
                  <idno type="lc">BD 1121 H6 1900 pt.1. pt.4</idno>
               </bibl>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Original punctuation conventions have been retained.</p>
            </normalization>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Hyphenated words that appear at the end of the line have been reformed.</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <interpretation>
               <p>Emphasis throughout text, including titles and headings, has been recorded and
                  retained.</p>
            </interpretation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="introduction">
            <head><emph rend="bold"><title type="book">SUGGESTIONS AND DIRECTIONS FOR THE STUDY OF
                     PERSONAL MAGNETISM AND HYPNOTISM.</title></emph> By <name type="person">X. LA MOTTE SAGE, A.
                  M., Ph. D., LL. D.</name>, formerly Professor in <name type="place">Pieree College</name>,
                     <placeName><settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>,
                  <region>Pa</region></placeName>.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head><emph rend="bold">READ THE INSTRUCTIONS VERY CAREFULLY.</emph></head>
               <p>Be sure that you thoroughly understand just what to do before attempting to
                  hypnotize anyone.</p>
               <p>If you stop and hesitate and wonder what to do next, you will never influence
                  anybody. Go about your work in a business-like way and show people by your actions
                  that you thoroughly understand what you are doing.</p>
               <p>You must not expect to hypnotize everybody you try. Remember all successful
                  operators and noted hypnotists came to be such only by long practical
                  experience.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><emph rend="bold">PERSEVERANCE.</emph></head>
               <p>If you do not succeed with the first five or ten that you try, do not give up, but
                  continue trying. Try twenty or thirty different persons, or more if necessary, and
                  just as sure as the sun shines you will find someone whom you can hypnotize. You
                  cannot fail if you persevere and read our instructions carefully. After you
                  hypnotize one or two, it will be easy, and soon you can affect the majority of
                  those whom you try; and with still more practice will be able readily to hypnotize
                  70 or 90 per cent.</p>
               <p>Determine to succeed and you will succeed. If you undertake this study in a
                  half-hearted way, if you go about it in a perfunctory sort of manner it were
                  better a thousand times over that you never undertook it. The greater your
                  deficiencies in personal magnetism the more difficult will it be for you to master
                  these sciences, and the more evident your need of further knowledge of this
                  mysterious power. Bear in mind that perseverance is the price of success;
                  knowledge does not come unsought.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><emph rend="bold">THE STUMBLING BLOCK</emph></head>
               <p>is hypnotizing the first one. Then remember that a good hypnotist might possibly
                  try ten people and not hypnotize any of' them, because they resist. They may say
                  they do not, though they do. With different people the whole ten might be
                  affected. You should make due allowance for this. Should you not meet with the
                  success you anticipate, it will probably be because you do not follow our
                  directions. Many think they are doing just as the instructions direct, when in
                  reality they are doing nothing of the kind. Read the instructions carefully and
                  slowly a number of times and study them well until you know each step as well as
                  you know your A, B, C's, and if you have any determination or perseverance
                  whatever, you cannot possibly make a failure. You are as certain to succeed as one
                  and one are two. After the ice is broken, that is, after you have hypnotized the
                  first one or two, you will have confidence, and you yourself will be'surprised and
                  mystified at your work.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><emph rend="bold">SUGGESTIONS.</emph></head>
               <p>You must be sure to give all your suggestions in a very positive tone. A feeble,
                  whining way of speaking never accomplishes anything. Be a person of some force of
                  character. Speak positively and directly to your subject, and influence is
                  certain. Do not give up until you have tried at least fifty persons between the
                  ages of 15 and 30, and be sure while trying each one that you do just as the
                  instructions direct. We ask you to do this because we know positively that after
                  you hypnotize one, the work will be very easy and you can influence a large
                  percentage. There is a certain knack required, and while nearly all persons get
                  this knack very readily from our instructions and can soon hypnotize, still there
                  is occasionally a person who has to try over and over before he acquires just the
                  proper method of procedure. Many, however, who find the work a little difficult at
                  first, make the finest hypnotists.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><emph rend="bold">CONFIDENCE.</emph></head>
               <p>To be successful in influencing people one must have confidence and perseverance.
                  A weak, vacillating disposition never accomplishes anything. People will influence
                  you or you will iiffuence them; it is for you to decide whether you will direct or
                  be directed, whether you will be a master or a servant. Self-esteem, stubbornness,
                  and an arrogant, haughty disposition are not the necessary elements with which to
                  control people.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><emph rend="bold">INBORN POWER.</emph></head>
               <p>There is a subtle, unseen force by which people are influenced, and the minds of
                  the multitude swayed. This secret power may ,be acquired by everyone who is
                  willing to take the time and trouble to develop it. An all-wise Creator has not
                  given it to the few, it is inborn in every person, and it is only necessary for
                  one to put forth a proper effort to achieve the success which God intended.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><emph rend="bold">PERSONAL INFLUENCE.</emph></head>
               <p>In taking up the study of these subjects you are entering a new field of science,
                  a new sphere of life, you are taking a very important step; your success in these
                  studies means much to you; in fact, it determines the position in life which you
                  will hereafter occupy; it matters not what your other capabilities or intellectual
                  attainments are, if you lack the power and ability to influence people you will
                  never achieve your full measure of success.</p>
               <p>If you master the sciences 'of personal magnetism and hypnotism you will have a
                  thorough knowledge of the philosophy of personal influence, of the laws by which
                  the human mind is molded and swayed, of that intangible and subtle power which
                  controls where bayonets fail.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><emph rend="bold">IMPORTANT TRIFLES.</emph></head>
               <p>It matters not how unimportant the instructions may seem to you, or how simple
                  they are, make up your mind to follow them in every detail; do not pass judgment
                  upon anything until you have given it a fair trial; remember the greatest things
                  in life are often the simplest. It may seem to you that the instructions are too
                  simple to produce the astounding results which are claimed for them, but, if you
                  will master them, if you will only give them a thorough trial, you will be more
                  enthusiastic in their praises than the authors of this course. </p>
            </div>
         </div>

         <div type="part">
            <head><emph rend="bold">HOW TO HYPNOTIZE</emph> By <name type="person">L. E. KASSEALL.</name></head>
            <p>In this article I shall give the student my three favorite methods of producing
               hypnosis, and in doing so I shall endeavor to explain the methods so that the student
               may learn just how to hypnotize and mesmerize.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head><emph rend="bold">METHOD NO. 1.</emph></head>
               <p>Have the subject seated in a comfortable chair or lying on a bed or couch. Place
                  the thumb of the subject’s left hand against your left thumb, with the inside of
                  the thumbs together.</p>
               <p><emph rend="bold">METHOD NO. 1.</emph></p>
               <p> Then grasp, with the fingers of the left hand, the base of the subject’s left
                  thumb, between the thumb and the first finger. The pressure should be firm without
                  hurting the subject. The thumbs should be in a perpendicular position. With your
                  right hand press the subject’s fingers over the back of your thumb and tell him to
                  grasp it firmly, to close his eyes and intently concentrate his mind on the
                  following suggestions: “I am so sleepy—so tired and sleepy—I cannot think of
                  anything but sleep.” After you tell the subject to think of these suggestions,
                  place the three fingers of your right hand, spread apart, on the top of the
                  subject’s head, a little toward the front, with the thumb of the right hand
                  resting on the bridge of the nose, or between the eyebrows. You should exert an
                  inward and downward pressure, being careful not to hurt the subject. Then suggest
                  to the subject in a slow, positive, monotonous tone, “You are becoming
                  drowsy—everything is getting dark to you—you are so tired and sleepy—you cannot
                  hear any sound but my voice—when I count ten you will be sound asleep.
                  One-two-three-four-five-six-seven-eight-nine-ten.” You should count slowly and
                  distinctly. As you finish counting ten, continue to suggest, “You are so
                  sleepy—you are breathing deeper—you are breathing heavier—you cannot hear any
                  sound but my voice—if anyone should call you, you will not answer. You cannot hear
                  anything but my voice.” These suggestions should be repeated until the subject is
                  fast asleep. If you do not get the subject to sleep the first time you try him,
                  arrange a sitting for another day. He should be treated daily, giving him at least
                  a half hour’s trial at each sitting.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><emph rend="bold">METHOD NO. 2.</emph></head>
               <p>Have the subject seated in a common kitchen chair, so that the shoulders are above
                  the back of the chair. Tell the subject to sit with his feet flat on the floor, to
                  rest, hands on knees, to relax all of his muscles, to close his eyes and intently
                  think of sleep. Stand on the subject’s right side, place the thumb of the right
                  hand on the subject’s right temple, and the first three fingers of the right hand
                  on the subject’s left temple; the pressure should be light. With the left hand
                  grasp the subject at the back of the neck, the idea being to prevent the
                  circulation of blood in the head as much as possible. Do not grasp the neck so as
                  to hurt the subject, though the pressure should be firm. Take as much of the neck
                  in your hand as possible, then tell the subject to relax his muscles, especially
                  those of the neck. Then roll the subject’s head to the right, making as large a
                  circle as possible; the movement should be slow. All the time you are doing this,
                  suggest to</p>
               <p><emph rend="bold">METHOD NO. 2.</emph></p>
               <p>the subject the same sleep formulas give in Method No. 1. After you have rolled
                  the head for five or ten minutes, gradually make the circle less until it stops
                  altogether. Keep the left hand in the original position, but drop the right hand
                  to the subject’s breast and as he exhales his breath, press inward; as he inhales
                  relax the pressure, and at the same time suggest, “You are breathing deeper—you
                  are breathing heavier—you are breathing deeper—you are breathing heavier.” These
                  suggestions should be repeated for two or three minutes, then the subject is
                  prepared to receive the suggestions you wish to give him. The head should be
                  rolled in the direction the hands of a clock move, if placed face upward on the
                  top of the subject’s head. I have found this method superior to any other which I
                  have tried, altogether others will often produce the effect when this one will
                  not, and vice versa.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><emph rend="bold">METHOD NO. 3.</emph></head>
               <p><emph rend="bold">METHOD NO. 3.</emph></p>
               <p>Have the subject lie down on a couch or bed, tell him to close his eyes, think of
                  sleep and relax all of his muscles. Tell him to try to give up the suggestions
                  which you are about to make. Have the arms lying straight down from the sides. You
                  should place the three fingers of both hands in the center of the forehead, making
                  a pass with both hands at the same time from the forehead down over the temples to
                  and off the cheek bones to the shoulders, then on down over the arms, and off the
                  tips of the subject's fingers. The pressure should be very light. This pass should
                  be made slowly, and at the same time, you should suggest, "You are becoming
                  drowsy—everything is getting dark to you—you are so tired and sleepy—you cannot
                  hear sound but my voice—when I count ten you will be sound asleep.
                  One-two-three-four-five-six-seven-eight-nine-ten."</p>
               <p>The passes should be made for fifteen or twenty minutes. The subject is then ready
                  to receive the suggestions you wish to give him. At the end of each pass, your
                  hands should close, coming back in a circle, and the fingers should not open until
                  ready to be placed upon the forehead the next time. This is an excellent method to
                  use upon sick persons or those who are lying down. In many cases the student will
                  place the subject under hypnosis at the first sitting, but sometimes it is
                  necessary to continue these sittings for a long time. It depends entirely upon the
                  subject; if he is amenable to your suggestions the effects are quickly produced.
                  After you succeed in getting the subject hypnotized once, it is much easier to do
                  so the second time, and you can make the subject act out any scene as described by
                  another author under the head of "How To Give Hypnotic Entertainments." After you
                  put on a few mental scenes, (or scenes where the subject is unconscious), it is
                  not necessary to re-hypnotize the subject to put on the next scene. Simply tell
                  him to close his eyes, place the fingers of your left hand on top of his head with
                  the thumb resting on the bridge of the subject's nose, between the eyebrows, and
                  say to him, "Now, when you open your eyes you will see so-and-so." For instance,
                  if you were going to make the subject believe he is fishing, you would say to him,
                  "Now, when you open your eyes you will see a beautiful stream of water. You are
                  sitting upon the bank of this stream and you want to fish. I will give you a
                  fishing-rod, you can bait your hook and have a splendid time." Then say to the
                  subject, "Open your eyes." Just the moment his eyes open, your right hand should
                  be ready to direct his gaze to the stream of water and at the same time say, "Do
                  you see that stream of water?" making a gesture toward the stream with your right
                  hand. If he says no, make the gesture over and over again, until he sees it. It
                  does not, as a rule, take more than four or five of these passes to make the
                  subject see the water, then you can give him the other suggestions, relative to
                  the fishing-rod, etc</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
