<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="teibp.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="book">Hypontism and Hypnotic Suggestion</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcribed by</resp>
               <name type="person" xml:id="JS">Jake Short</name>
               <name type="person" xml:id="LD">Lilly Durham</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>
               <name type="person" ref="#JS">Jake Short</name>
               <name type="person" ref="#LD">Lilly Durham</name>
            </authority>
            <pubPlace><placeName><settlement>Seattle</settlement>,
               <region>WA</region></placeName></pubPlace>
            <date when="2024-02-12">2024-02​-12</date>
            <availability>
               <p>Available for purposes of academic research and teaching only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="main">HYPNOTISM AND HYPNOTIC SUGGESTION</title>
                  <title type="subordinate">A SCIENTIFIC TREATISE OF THE USES AND POSSIBILITIES OF
                     HYPNOTISM, SUGGESTION AND ALLIED PHENOMENA.</title>
                  <editor>
                     <name type="person">E. VIRGIL NEAL, A. M., LL. D.</name>
                     <name type="person">CHARLES S. CLARK, M.A.</name>
                  </editor>
                  <publisher>New York State Publishing Company</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
                  <idno type="lc">BD 1121 H6 1900 pt.1. pt.4</idno>
               </bibl>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>Original punctuation conventions have been retained.</p>
            </normalization>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Hyphenated words that appear at the end of the line have been reformed.</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <interpretation>
               <p>Emphasis throughout text, including titles and headings, has been recorded and
                  retained.</p>
            </interpretation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="editorial_intro">
            <p>At the turn of the twentieth century, the concept of hypnotism experienced a surge in
               public interest and experimentation from areas such as scientific inquiry,
               entertainment, and therapeutic applications (LoC). The lead editor of this text, E.
               Virgil Neal, capitalized on this cultural fascination towards hypnosis as another of
               his various entrepreneurial endeavors; he began giving hypnosis demonstrations in the
               mid-1890s (Conroy, 70), and in 1897, he wrote a book titled Hypnotism As It Is, which
               set the stage for Hypnotism and Hypnotic Suggestion (Conroy, 35). Hypnotism and
               Hypnotic Suggestion covers various uses of hypnosis, from the medical to religious,
               but Neal and Clark personally contributed work which emphasized the more practical
               and business related uses of hypnosis (Conroy, 41). The other 28 authors of Hypnotism
               and Hypnotic Suggestion were considered specialists in the field, coming from
               universities such as Harvard and Yale (Conroy, 41).</p>

            <p>Hypnotism and Hypnotic Suggestion was intended to be instructional, aimed towards
               students of Neal, Clark, and their other colleagues in the New York Institute of
               Science, namely Thomas Adkin (Conroy, 70). The New York Institute of Science, which
               was a mail-order company selling fraudulent degrees and courses relating to hypnotism
               and personal magnetism, only operated from 1899 until 1912, because it was shut down
               by the U.S. government (New York Tribune, pages 18 &amp; 11). According to the 1913
               indictment, the co-editors and Adkin had collaborated in a fraudulent hypnotic
               suggestion mail-order scheme, of which this text was a part (New York Tribune, pages
               18 &amp; 11). Given this, we hope readers can read this edition for entertainment
               purposes, but not for educational purposes. With its fraudulent nature, this edition
               can be used by students to learn more about a "scam" during this time period, or to
               use the activities in the text for fun.</p>

            <p>When transcribing and editing this text, we chose to keep the text as close to the
               original as possible, except for some visual aspects that don’t affect the reading of
               the text (such as omitting specific line breaks and page breaks). We did not update
               spellings, vocabulary, or other textual parts of the book.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="introduction">
            <head>
		    <!-- GT: looks great overall. My one general comment is you transcribe a lot of titles with caps.
		    I think as a general rule, it's better to describe the formatting with XML and transcribe as 
		    unformatted text. But what you have is fine: you can always transform ths caps back into lowercase
		    in various ways -->
               <hi rend="bold"><title type="book">SUGGESTIONS AND DIRECTIONS FOR THE STUDY OF
                     PERSONAL MAGNETISM AND HYPNOTISM.</title></hi>
               <note n="1" type="editorial">"Personal Magnetism" is in reference to a speaking style
                  more common during this time, used by people such as politicians for influence
                     <ref target="#young">(Young)</ref>.</note> By <name type="person">X. LA MOTTE
                  SAGE, A. M., Ph. D., LL. D.</name>, formerly Professor in <name type="place"
                  >Pieree College</name>, <placeName><settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>,
                     <region>Pa</region></placeName>. <note n="2" type="editorial">"X. La Motte
                  Sage" is an alias used by Neal <ref target="#conroy">(Conroy)</ref>.</note>
            </head>
            <div type="section">
               <head><hi rend="bold">READ THE INSTRUCTIONS VERY CAREFULLY.</hi></head>
               <p>Be sure that you thoroughly understand just what to do before attempting to
                  hypnotize anyone.</p>
               <p>If you stop and hesitate and wonder what to do next, you will never influence
                  anybody. Go about your work in a business-like way and show people by your actions
                  that you thoroughly understand what you are doing.</p>
               <p>You must not expect to hypnotize everybody you try. Remember all successful
                  operators and noted hypnotists came to be such only by long practical
                  experience.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><hi rend="bold">PERSEVERANCE.</hi></head>
               <p>If you do not succeed with the first five or ten that you try, do not give up, but
                  continue trying. Try twenty or thirty different persons, or more if necessary, and
                  just as sure as the sun shines you will find someone whom you can hypnotize. You
                  cannot fail if you persevere and read our instructions carefully. After you
                  hypnotize one or two, it will be easy, and soon you can affect the majority of
                  those whom you try; and with still more practice will be able readily to hypnotize
                  70 or 90 per cent.</p>
               <p>Determine to succeed and you will succeed. If you undertake this study in a
                  half-hearted way, if you go about it in a perfunctory sort of manner it were
                  better a thousand times over that you never undertook it. The greater your
                  deficiencies in personal magnetism the more difficult will it be for you to master
                  these sciences, and the more evident your need of further knowledge of this
                  mysterious power. Bear in mind that perseverance is the price of success;
                  knowledge does not come unsought.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><hi rend="bold">THE STUMBLING BLOCK</hi></head>
               <p>is hypnotizing the first one. <note n="3" type="editorial">The beginning of this
                     sentence is a direct transcription, not an error (including the
                     capitalization). It may be a continuation of the title. This stylistic choice
                     is repeated in the subsequent section: "To Be A Good Hypnotist.", though the
                     latter has a period in the title, whereas this one does not.</note> Then
                  remember that a good hypnotist might possibly try ten people and not hypnotize any
                  of them, because they resist. They may say they do not, though they do. With
                  different people the whole ten might be affected. You should make due allowance
                  for this. Should you not meet with the success you anticipate, it will probably be
                  because you do not follow our directions. Many think they are doing just as the
                  instructions direct, when in reality they are doing nothing of the kind. Read the
                  instructions carefully and slowly a number of times and study them well until you
                  know each step as well as you know your A, B, C's, and if you have any
                  determination or perseverance whatever, you cannot possibly make a failure. You
                  are as certain to succeed as one and one are two. After the ice is broken, that
                  is, after you have hypnotized the first one or two, you will have confidence, and
                  you yourself will be surprised and mystified at your work.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><hi rend="bold">SUGGESTIONS.</hi></head>
               <p>You must be sure to give all your suggestions in a very positive tone. A feeble,
                  whining way of speaking never accomplishes anything. Be a person of some force of
                  character. Speak positively and directly to your subject, and influence is
                  certain. Do not give up until you have tried at least fifty persons between the
                  ages of 15 and 30, and be sure while trying each one that you do just as the
                  instructions direct. We ask you to do this because we know positively that after
                  you hypnotize one, the work will be very easy and you can influence a large
                  percentage. There is a certain knack required, and while nearly all persons get
                  this knack very readily from our instructions and can soon hypnotize, still there
                  is occasionally a person who has to try over and over before he acquires just the
                  proper method of procedure. Many, however, who find the work a little difficult at
                  first, make the finest hypnotists.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><hi rend="bold">CONFIDENCE.</hi></head>
               <p>To be successful in influencing people one must have confidence and perseverance.
                  A weak, vacillating <note n="4" type="editorial">(always changing)</note>
                  disposition never accomplishes anything. People will influence you or you will
                  influence them; it is for you to decide whether you will direct or be directed,
                  whether you will be a master or a servant. Self-esteem, stubbornness, and an
                  arrogant, haughty disposition are not the necessary elements with which to control
                  people.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><hi rend="bold">INBORN POWER.</hi></head>
               <p>There is a subtle, unseen force by which people are influenced, and the minds of
                  the multitude swayed. This secret power may be acquired by everyone who is willing
                  to take the time and trouble to develop it. An all-wise Creator has not given it
                  to the few, it is inborn in every person, and it is only necessary for one to put
                  forth a proper effort to achieve the success which God intended.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><hi rend="bold">PERSONAL INFLUENCE.</hi></head>
               <p>In taking up the study of these subjects you are entering a new field of science,
                  a new sphere of life, you are taking a very important step; your success in these
                  studies means much to you; in fact, it determines the position in life which you
                  will hereafter occupy; it matters not what your other capabilities or intellectual
                  attainments are, if you lack the power and ability to influence people you will
                  never achieve your full measure of success.</p>
               <p>If you master the sciences of personal magnetism and hypnotism you will have a
                  thorough knowledge of the philosophy of personal influence, of the laws by which
                  the human mind is molded and swayed, of that intangible and subtle power which
                  controls where bayonets fail.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><hi rend="bold">IMPORTANT TRIFLES.</hi></head>
               <p>It matters not how unimportant the instructions may seem to you, or how simple
                  they are, make up your mind to follow them in every detail; do not pass judgment
                  upon anything until you have given it a fair trial; remember the greatest things
                  in life are often the simplest. It may seem to you that the instructions are too
                  simple to produce the astounding results which are claimed for them, but, if you
                  will master them, if you will only give them a thorough trial, you will be more
                  enthusiastic in their praises than the authors of this course. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><hi rend="bold">TACT.</hi></head>
               <p>If you wish to exert a lasting influence over a person, you must influence him in
                  such a manner that he does not dream that you are affecting him. He must think
                  that he is performing every act of his own free will and accord. In controlling
                  people use tact and judgment; study human nature. No two persons are exactly
                  alike; what will influence one person will not always influence another, but all
                  persons may be influenced. We do not hope to teach' you in a few days how to
                  influence every person with whom you come in contact, but if you follow the
                  instructions implicitly we shall develop in you a strong personality, and we shall
                  increase to a marvelous extent your present ability to influence people,-in fact,
                  the instructions will positively enable you to influence to a greater or less
                  degree 90 per cent. of those with whom you come in contact. The longer you
                  practice the more proficient you will become, and the greater the influence you
                  will be able to exert.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><hi rend="bold">SIMPLE TESTS.</hi></head>
               <p>For the purpose of developing the power of personal magnetism we have devised some
                  very simple tests. If you can succeed with these little things, you can succeed
                  with greater things. If you can successfully perform the first four tests given on
                  pages 12 to 22 your success with personal magnetism and hypnotism is assured and
                  your complete mastery of these sciences is only a question of a very short
                  time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><hi rend="bold"> METHOD OF STUDY.</hi></head>
               <p>Take the tests in order and study each one thoroughly. Do not read the last part
                  of the instructions until you have learned the first part. It is time worse than
                  wasted to study the lessons in the back part of an arithmetic before you have
                  mastered those in the front part. You cannot learn cube root before you learn
                  addition; you cannot learn mensuration before division. For this reason the
                  fundamental principles of personal magnetism and hypnotism have been purposely
                  placed in the first part of the course, and the instructions relating to the
                  practical application of these sciences have been placed in the other parts.
                  Without a thorough knowledge of the fundamental principles of any science, higher
                  instruction is useless.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><hi rend="bold">PREPARATORY.</hi></head>
               <p>The first part of the course is the notation, numeration, addition and subtraction
                  of personal magnetism, hypnotism, suggestive therapeutics and magnetic healing. It
                  is the key, without which you can do absolutely nothing. Master it well and your
                  complete success is certain.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><hi rend="bold">PLAN OF TEACHING.</hi></head>
               <p>The majority of those who teach hypnotism instruct you to put the subject asleep
                  first, but such a method is generally impracticable. Most people who are
                  unacquainted with hypnotism dread going into an unconscious condition. By the
                  methods which I employ, you commence with the subjects on tests in which they are
                  not hypnotized. Then you produce light hyp- notic effects and lead them from these
                  slight effects into the deeper stages of hypnosis.</p>
               <p>It is entirely unnecessary to put one asleep to fasten his hands together,
                  although this is the instruction which most teachers give. It is contrary to
                  reason to undertake to throw the majority of people into an unconscious condition
                  upon the first trial, because they naturally resist such a mode of procedure. By
                  such methods it is entirely impossible to go into a promiscuous audience and give
                  uniformly successful hypnotic demonstrations without subjects whom you have
                  previously hypnotized.</p>
               <p>I have given a large number of demonstrations before colleges and universities. I
                  made it a point to use as subjects none but students. I have also given a large
                  number of demonstrations before clubs, using in every case for my experiments,
                  members of the clubs. I have never made a failure in a single instance. I
                  attribute this to my method of hypnotizing in the waking state which is explained
                  on page 12.</p>
               <p>Again, by using the physical tests first, you give the subject confidence in your
                  ability and gain corresponding confidence in yourself. These are also the tests
                  with which you develop the real power of personal magnetism-you learn how to
                  influenoe people without putting them to sleep.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><hi rend="bold">OCCULT SCIENCES.</hi></head>
               <p>The science of hypnotism unfolds the secret law. of all personal influence. A man
                  who sways multitudes by the charm of his voice uses no less of hypnotism than he
                  who fastens another's hands together and makes his arm stiff and rigid so that he
                  cannot bend it. Both act under the same law. It is merely a difference.in the
                  application of that law. Hypnotism is the foundation of personal magnetism. It
                  bears the same relation to personal magnetism that grammar does to language. There
                  is no better way of developing the higher power of personal magnetism than by
                  practicing simple hypnotic tests.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><hi rend="bold">TO BE A GOOD HYPNOTIST.</hi></head>
               <p>you must be positive, you must persevere. Persevere and you will learn how to be
                  positive; hence, the only essential conditions are perseverance and a desire to
                  learn. A man who gives up simply because lie does not succeed upon the first few
                  trials, Will never be brilliantly successful at anything. There are many persons
                  of this kind in the world. Such persons will never learn how to use personal
                  magnetism; they will never occupy positions of trust and responsibility unless
                  they first acquire that necessary prerequisite, perseverance.</p>
            </div>
         </div>

         <div type="part">
            <head><hi rend="bold">HOW TO HYPNOTIZE</hi> By <name type="person">L. E.
                  KASSEALL.</name></head>
            <note n="5" type="editorial">At the time of publishing, Lulu Elizabeth Kasseall was the
               treasurer of the American College of Sciences <ref target="#dem_chronicle">(Democrat
                  and Chronicle)</ref>.</note>
            <p>In this article I shall give the student my three favorite methods of producing
               hypnosis, and in doing so I shall endeavor to explain the methods so that the student
               may learn just how to hypnotize and mesmerize.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head><hi rend="bold">METHOD NO. 1.</hi></head>
               <p>Have the subject seated in a comfortable chair or lying on a bed or couch. Place
                  the thumb of the subject’s left hand against your left thumb, with the inside of
                  the thumbs together.</p>
               <figure xml:id="figure1" type="example">
                  <graphic url="images/figure1.png"/>
                  <p><hi>METHOD NO. 1.</hi></p>
                  <figDesc> Man standing over another man sitting in a chair. Standing man has right
                     hand pressed against forehead of sitting man. Left thumbs of both men are
                     pressed together. </figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p> Then grasp, with the fingers of the left hand, the base of the subject’s left
                  thumb, between the thumb and the first finger. The pressure should be firm without
                  hurting the subject. The thumbs should be in a perpendicular position. With your
                  right hand press the subject’s fingers over the back of your thumb and tell him to
                  grasp it firmly, to close his eyes and intently concentrate his mind on the
                  following suggestions: “I am so sleepy—so tired and sleepy—I cannot think of
                  anything but sleep.” After you tell the subject to think of these suggestions,
                  place the three fingers of your right hand, spread apart, on the top of the
                  subject’s head, a little toward the front, with the thumb of the right hand
                  resting on the bridge of the nose, or between the eyebrows. You should exert an
                  inward and downward pressure, being careful not to hurt the subject. Then suggest
                  to the subject in a slow, positive, monotonous tone, “You are becoming
                  drowsy—everything is getting dark to you—you are so tired and sleepy—you cannot
                  hear any sound but my voice—when I count ten you will be sound asleep.
                  One-two-three-four-five-six-seven-eight-nine-ten.” You should count slowly and
                  distinctly. As you finish counting ten, continue to suggest, “You are so
                  sleepy—you are breathing deeper—you are breathing heavier—you cannot hear any
                  sound but my voice—if anyone should call you, you will not answer. You cannot hear
                  anything but my voice.” These suggestions should be repeated until the subject is
                  fast asleep. If you do not get the subject to sleep the first time you try him,
                  arrange a sitting for another day. He should be treated daily, giving him at least
                  a half hour’s trial at each sitting.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><hi rend="bold">METHOD NO. 2.</hi></head>
               <p>Have the subject seated in a common kitchen chair, so that the shoulders are above
                  the back of the chair. Tell the subject to sit with his feet flat on the floor, to
                  rest, hands on knees, to relax all of his muscles, to close his eyes and intently
                  think of sleep. Stand on the subject’s right side, place the thumb of the right
                  hand on the subject’s right temple, and the first three fingers of the right hand
                  on the subject’s left temple; the pressure should be light. With the left hand
                  grasp the subject at the back of the neck, the idea being to prevent the
                  circulation of blood in the head as much as possible. Do not grasp the neck so as
                  to hurt the subject, though the pressure should be firm. Take as much of the neck
                  in your hand as possible, then tell the subject to relax his muscles, especially
                  those of the neck. Then roll the subject’s head to the right, making as large a
                  circle as possible; the movement should be slow. All the time you are doing this,
                  suggest to</p>
               <figure xml:id="figure2" type="example">
                  <graphic url="images/figure2.png"/>
                  <p><hi>METHOD NO. 2.</hi></p>
                  <figDesc> Man standing over another man sitting in a chair. Standing man has right
                     hand cupped around the forehead of the sitting man. Standing man has left hand
                     grasping the back of the sitting man's neck.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>the subject the same sleep formulas give in Method No. 1. After you have rolled
                  the head for five or ten minutes, gradually make the circle less until it stops
                  altogether. Keep the left hand in the original position, but drop the right hand
                  to the subject’s breast and as he exhales his breath, press inward; as he inhales
                  relax the pressure, and at the same time suggest, “You are breathing deeper—you
                  are breathing heavier—you are breathing deeper—you are breathing heavier.” These
                  suggestions should be repeated for two or three minutes, then the subject is
                  prepared to receive the suggestions you wish to give him. The head should be
                  rolled in the direction the hands of a clock move, if placed face upward on the
                  top of the subject’s head. I have found this method superior to any other which I
                  have tried, altogether others will often produce the effect when this one will
                  not, and vice versa.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><hi rend="bold">METHOD NO. 3.</hi></head>
               <figure xml:id="figure3" type="example">
                  <graphic url="images/figure3.png"/>
                  <p><hi>METHOD NO. 3.</hi></p>
                  <figDesc> Man standing over another man laying down, face-up, on a table with a
                     sheet on it. Standing man is holding his open-faced palms over the eyes of the
                     man lying down.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Have the subject lie down on a couch or bed <note n="6" type="editorial">From the
                     picture, they should lie down face-up.</note>, tell him to close his eyes,
                  think of sleep and relax all of his muscles. Tell him to try to give up the
                  suggestions which you are about to make. Have the arms lying straight down from
                  the sides. You should place the three fingers of both hands in the center of the
                  forehead, making a pass with both hands at the same time from the forehead down
                  over the temples to and off the cheek bones to the shoulders, then on down over
                  the arms, and off the tips of the subject's fingers. The pressure should be very
                  light. This pass should be made slowly, and at the same time, you should suggest,
                  "You are becoming drowsy—everything is getting dark to you—you are so tired and
                  sleepy—you cannot hear sound but my voice—when I count ten you will be sound
                  asleep. One-two-three-four-five-six-seven-eight-nine-ten."</p>
               <p>The passes should be made for fifteen or twenty minutes. The subject is then ready
                  to receive the suggestions you wish to give him. At the end of each pass, your
                  hands should close, coming back in a circle, and the fingers should not open until
                  ready to be placed upon the forehead the next time. This is an excellent method to
                  use upon sick persons or those who are lying down. In many cases the student will
                  place the subject under hypnosis at the first sitting, but sometimes it is
                  necessary to continue these sittings for a long time. It depends entirely upon the
                  subject; if he is amenable to your suggestions the effects are quickly produced.
                  After you succeed in getting the subject hypnotized once, it is much easier to do
                  so the second time, and you can make the subject act out any scene as described by
                  another author under the head of "How To Give Hypnotic Entertainments." After you
                  put on a few mental scenes, (or scenes where the subject is unconscious), it is
                  not necessary to re-hypnotize the subject to put on the next scene. Simply tell
                  him to close his eyes, place the fingers of your left hand on top of his head with
                  the thumb resting on the bridge of the subject's nose, between the eyebrows, and
                  say to him, "Now, when you open your eyes you will see so-and-so." For instance,
                  if you were going to make the subject believe he is fishing, you would say to him,
                  "Now, when you open your eyes you will see a beautiful stream of water. You are
                  sitting upon the bank of this stream and you want to fish. I will give you a
                  fishing-rod, you can bait your hook and have a splendid time." Then say to the
                  subject, "Open your eyes." Just the moment his eyes open, your right hand should
                  be ready to direct his gaze to the stream of water and at the same time say, "Do
                  you see that stream of water?" making a gesture toward the stream with your right
                  hand. If he says no, make the gesture over and over again, until he sees it. It
                  does not, as a rule, take more than four or five of these passes to make the
                  subject see the water, then you can give him the other suggestions, relative to
                  the fishing-rod, etc</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="neal_clark">
                  <title type="book">HYPNOTISM AND HYPNOTIC SUGGESTION</title>
                  <title type="subordinate">A SCIENTIFIC TREATISE OF THE USES AND POSSIBILITIES OF
                     HYPNOTISM, SUGGESTION AND ALLIED PHENOMENA.</title>
                  <editor>
                     <name>E. VIRGIL NEAL, A. M., LL. D.</name>
                     <name>CHARLES S. CLARK, M.A.</name>
                  </editor>
                  <publisher>New York State Publishing Company</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
                  <idno type="lc">BD 1121 H6 1900 pt.1. pt.4</idno>
               </bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="loc_hypnotism">
                  <title type="main">Hypnotism: Topics in Chronicling America</title>
                  <publisher>Library of Congress (LoC)</publisher>
                  <ref>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-hypnotism</ref>
               </bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="kook">
                  <title>New York Institute of Science</title>
                  <publisher>Kook Science</publisher>
                  <ref>https://hatch.kookscience.com/wiki/New_York_Institute_of_Science</ref>
               </bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="loc_nytribune">
                  <title>New York Tribune</title>
                  <date when="1918-06-23">1918-06-23</date>
                  <pubPlace>New York, N.Y.</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>Library of Congress</publisher>
                  <publisher>Chronicling America: Historic American Newspapers</publisher>
                  <ref>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1918-06-23/ed-1/seq-18/</ref>
                  <ref>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1918-06-23/ed-1/seq-11/</ref>
               </bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="conroy">
                  <title type="book">The cosmetics baron you've never heard of: E. Virgil Neal and
                     Tokalon</title>
                  <date when="1937">1937</date>
                  <edition>Third Edition</edition>
                  <author>
                     <name type="person">Mary Schaeffer Conroy</name>
                  </author>
                  <ref>https://archive.org/details/cosmeticsbaronyo0000conr</ref>
               </bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="dem_chronicle">
                  <title>Democrat and Chronicle</title>
                  <date when="1900-09-01">1900-09-01</date>
                  <pubPlace>Rochester, N.Y.</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>Democrat and Chronicle</publisher>
                  <ref>https://www.newspapers.com/article/democrat-and-chronicle/141734229/</ref>
                  <ref>https://img.newspapers.com/img/img?clippingId=141734229</ref>
               </bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="young">
                  <title>Guest Post: Jeremy C. Young, “James Rush and the Invention of Personal
                     Magnetism”</title>
                  <date when="2017-01-16">2017-01-16</date>
                  <author>
                     <name type="person">Jeremy C. Young</name>
                  </author>
                  <publisher>The Junto</publisher>
                  <ref>https://earlyamericanists.com/2017/01/16/guest-post-jeremy-c-young-james-rush-and-the-invention-of-personal-magnetism/</ref>
               </bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
