<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="teibp.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Poems</title>
            <author>Mary Baker Eddy</author>
            <editor>Emma Hong</editor>
            <editor>Annie Melnick</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This transcription of "Poems" was created as our final project submission for Professor Turnovsky's TXTDS 404 course, "Texts, Publics and Publication" at the University of Washington. Poems was chosen amongst various texts provided by the UW Libraries' Special Collections department. Our intention with this transcription was to preserve the content of Eddy's poetry, and provide through our poem selections and annotations a curated understanding of Eddy's beliefs and life. The literary content of the poems and historical period of time they were written in were a central focus in our transcription efforts. </p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="editorial_intro">
            <p>Mary Baker Eddy’s Poems is a collection of poetry written by Eddy during the course of her life, dated from childhood through her last years. As editors, we found this text notable because we wanted to contextualize Eddy’s poems by researching additional historical and biographical information, therefore deriving and providing more meaning from her work. An aspect of note is that there are varying levels of context provided for each poem. Only a portion of Eddy’s poems have footnotes listing the year and location the work was written. With the help of additional biographical information, we are able to piece together additional context. But many of the poems do not have that level of specificity. Some only list the year or time period in which it was written; many do not provide footnotes at all. This gives us a significant challenge when it comes to contextualizing Eddy’s poems.</p>
            <p>The goal of our project is twofold. The first is to attempt to contextualize some of Eddy’s poems based on clues, seeing if we could utilize stylistic and thematic elements to provide our best guess as to when and where the poem was written. In addition, for the poems with identifying information, we are going to provide annotations with facts about Eddy’s life during the time it was written. Our second goal is to share which poems stood out to us. Our edition only contains ten poems, and we picked our favorites to feature. This could give insight as to which of Eddy’s poems continue to be impactive in the twenty-first century.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="preface" n="1">
            <p></p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" rhyme="aabccb">
            <head><hi rend="uppercase">Meeting Of My Departed Mother And Husband</hi></head>
            <lg type="stanza">
		 <!-- GT: is it both in the source? You can include two values here: rend="italics caps". Or you can combine into one value that will
		 mean italics and caps: rend="caps_ital" , or something similar -->
               <l>Joy for thee, happy friend! thy bark is past</l>
               <l>The dangerous sea, and safely moored at last—</l>
               <l>Beyond rough foam.</l>
               <l>Soft gales celestial, in sweet music bore—</l>
               <l>Spirit emancipate for this far shore—</l>
               <l>Thee to thy home.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza" rhyme="aabccb"><!-- Encode speakers -->
               <l>"You've traveled long, and far from mortal joys,</l>
               <l>To Soul's diviner sense, that spurns such toys,</l>
               <l>Brave wrestler, lone.</l>
               <l>Now see thy ever-self; Life never fled;</l>
               <l>Man is not mortal, never of the dead:</l>
               <l>The dark unknown.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza" rhyme="aabccb">
               <l>"When hope soared high, and joy was eagle-plumed,</l>
               <l>Thy pinions drooped; the flesh was weak, and doomed</l>
               <l>To pass away.</l>
               <l>But faith triumphant round thy death-couch shed</l>
               <l>Majestic forms; and radiant glory sped</l>
               <l>The dawning day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza" rhyme="aabccb">
               <l>"Intensely grand and glorious life's sphere,—</l>
               <l>Beyond the shadow, infinite appear</l>
               <l>Life, Love divine,—</l>
               <l>Where mortal yearnings come not, sighs are stilled,</l>
               <l>And home and peace and hearts are found and filled,</l>
               <l>Thine, ever thine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza" rhyme="aabccb">
               <l>"Bearest thou no tidings from our loved on earth,</l>
               <l>The toiler tireless for Truth's new birth</l>
               <l>All-unbeguiled?</l>
               <l>Our joy is gathered from her parting sigh:</l>
               <l>This hour looks on her heart with pitying eye,—</l>
               <l>What of my child?"</l> <!-- Reference pregnancy when first husband died -->
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza" rhyme="aabccb">
               <l>"When, severed by death's dream, I woke to Life,</l>
               <l>She deemed I died, and could not know the strife</l>
               <l>At first to fill</l>
               <l>That waking with a love that steady turns</l>
               <l>To God; a hope that ever upward yearns,</l>
               <l>Bowed to His will.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza" rhyme="aabccb">
               <l>"Years had passed o'er thy broken household band,</l> <!-- Broken household band? -->
               <l>When angels beckoned me to this bright land,</l>
               <l>With thee to meet.</l>
               <l>She that has wept o'er thee, kissed my cold brow,</l>
               <l>Rears the sad marble to our memory now,</l>
               <l>In lone retreat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza" rhyme="aabccb">
               <l>"By the remembrance of her loyal life,</l>
               <l>And parting prayer, I only know my wife,</l>
               <l>Thy child, shall come—</l>
               <l>Where farewells cloud not o'er our ransomed rest—</l>
               <l>Hither to reap, with all the crowned and blest,</l>
               <l>Of bliss the sum.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza" rhyme="aabccb">
               <l>"When Love's rapt sense the heartstrings gently sweep</l>
               <l>With joy divinely fair, the high and deep,</l>
               <l>To call her home,</l>
               <l>She shall mount upward unto purer skies;</l>
               <l>We shall be waiting, in what glad surprise,</l>
               <l>Our spirits' own!"</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" n="2">
            <head><hi rend="uppercase">I'm Sitting Alone</hi></head>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="aabb">
               <l>I'm sitting alone where the shadows fall</l> <!-- Reference a location where she's sitting -->
               <l>In somber groups at the vesper-call,</l>
               <l>Where tear-dews of night seek the loving rose,</l>
               <l>Her bosom to fill with mortal woes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="aabb">
               <l>I'm waiting alone for the bridal hour</l>
               <l>Of nymph and naiad from woodland bower;</l>
               <l>Till vestal pearls that on leaflets lay,</l>
               <l>Ravished with beauty the eye of day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="aabb"> 
               <l>I'm watching alone o'er the starlit glow,</l>
               <l>O'er the silv'ry moon and ocean flow;</l>
               <l>And sketching in light the heaven of my youth—</l>
               <l>Its starry hopes and its waves of truth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="aabb">
               <l>I'm dreaming alone of its changeful sky—</l>
               <l>What rainbows of rapture floated by!</l>
               <l>Of a mother's love, that no words could speak</l> <!-- Reference the mother -->
               <l>When parting the ringlets to kiss my cheek.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="aabb">
               <l>I'm thinking alone of a fair young bride,</l> <!-- reference which husband -->
               <l>The light of a home of love and pride;</l>
               <l>How the glance of her husband's watchful eye</l>
               <l>Turned to his star of idolatry.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="aabb">
               <l>I'm picturing alone a glad young face,</l>
               <l>Upturned to his mother's in playful grace;</l>
               <l>And the unsealed fountains of grief and joy</l>
               <l>That gushed at the birth of that beautiful boy.</l> <!-- Who's the beautiful boy -->
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="aabb">
               <l>I'm weeping alone that the vision is fled,</l> <!-- Reference event for why the vision is fled -->
               <l>The leaves all faded, the fruitage shed,</l>
               <l>And wishing this earth more gifts from above,</l>
               <l>Our reason made right and hearts all love.</l>
            </lg>
            <note place="footnote">
               Lynn, Mass., <hi rend="italic">September 3, 1866.</hi>
            </note>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" n="3">
            <head><hi rend="uppercase">The New Century</hi></head>
            <lg type="stanza" rhyme="aabbccddee">
               <l>Thou God-crowned, patient century,</l>
               <l>Thine hour hath come! Eternity</l>
               <l>Draws nigh—and, beckoning from above,</l>
               <l>One hundred years, aflame with Love,</l>
               <l>Again shall bid old earth good-by—</l>
               <l>And, lo, the light! far heaven is nigh!</l>
               <l>New themes seraphic, Life divine,</l>
               <l>And bliss that wipes the tears of time</l>
               <l>Away, will enter, when they may,</l>
               <l>And bask in one eternal day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza" rhyme="aabbccddee">
               <l>'Tis writ on earth, on leaf and flower:</l>
               <l>Love hath one race, one realm, one power.</l>
               <l>Dear God! how great, how good Thou art</l>
               <l>To heal humanity's sore heart;</l> <!-- Is this related to teachings? Encode event -->
               <l>To probe the wound, then pour the balm—</l>
               <l>A life perfected, strong and calm.</l>
               <l>The dark domain of pain and sin</l>
               <l>Surrenders—Love doth enter in,</l>
               <l>And peace is won, and lost is vice:</l>
               <l>Right reigns, and blood was not its price.</l> <!-- Encode religious teachings / events -->
            </lg>
            <note place="footnote">
               Pleasant View, Concord, N. H., <hi rend="italic">January, 1901.</hi>
            </note>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" n="4">
            <head><hi rend="uppercase">Constancy</hi></head>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="aabb">     
               <l>When starlight blends with morning's hue,</l>
               <l>I miss thee as the flower the dew!</l> <!-- Who does she miss -->
               <l>When noonday's length'ning shadows flee,</l>
               <l>I think of thee, I think of thee!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="aabb">
               <l>With evening, memories reappear—</l>
               <l>I watch thy chair, and wish thee here;</l>
               <l>Till sleep sets drooping fancy free</l>
               <l>To dream of thee, to dream of thee!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="aabb">
               <l>Since first we met, in weal or woe</l> <!-- Guess an age she wrote this -->
               <l>It hath been thus; and must be so</l>
               <l>Till bursting bonds our spirits part</l>
               <l>And Love divine doth fill my heart.</l>
            </lg>
            <note place="footnote">
               Written many years ago.
            </note>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" n="5">
            <head><hi rend="uppercase">Autumn</hi></head>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>Quickly earth's jewels disappear;</l>
               <l>The turf, whereon I tread,</l>
               <l>Ere autumn blanch another year,</l>
               <l>May rest above my head.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>Touched by the finger of decay</l>
               <l>Is every earthly love;</l>
               <l>For joy, to shun my weary way,</l>
               <l>Is registered above.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>The languid brooklets yield their sighs,</l>
               <l>A requiem o'er the tomb</l>
               <l>Of sunny days and cloudless skies,</l>
               <l>Enhancing autumn's gloom. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>The wild winds mutter, howl, and moan,</l>
               <l>To scare my woodland walk,</l> <!-- Encode a place -->
               <l>And frightened fancy flees, to roam</l>
               <l>Where ghosts and goblins stalk.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>The cricket's sharp, discordant scream</l>
               <l>Fills mortal sense with dread;</l>
               <l>More sorrowful it scarce could seem;</l>
               <l>It voices beauty fled.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>Yet here, upon this faded sod,—</l>
               <l>O happy hours and fleet,—</l>
               <l>When songsters' matin hymns to God</l>
               <l>Are poured in strains so sweet,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>My heart unbidden joins rehearse,</l>
               <l>I hope it's better made,</l>
               <l>When mingling with the universe,</l>
               <l>Beneath the maple's shade.</l>
            </lg>
            <note place="footnote">
               Written in girlhood, in a maple grove.
            </note>      
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
   <!-- GT: excellent work on everything below -->
   <standOff>
      <!-- GT: this is a great way to do the notes. It changes their status, in a way: they're separate from the text rather than part of the text. Everything in <standOff> is considered like an associated database or appendix... -->
      <listAnnotation>
         <!-- GT: normally you'd give notes enumerating XML:ids, as in n1, n2, n3, etc... I think that's because you might want at some point to cycle or loop through them: maybe you want to represent them as numbered end notes...-->
         <annotation xml:id="ice_fall" target="editorial_stmt" motivation="commenting">
            <note>
               In 1866, Mary experienced an injurous fall in Lynn Massachusetts, having slipped on a patch of ice. The treatment of this injury involved morphine doses, which Mary continued taking through the end of her life. The fall marked a moment of spiritual revelation for Eddy, who attributed her recovery to teachings from the Bible and subsequently delved further into spititualism and the foundation of Christian Science.
            </note>
         </annotation>
         <annotation xml:id="christian_science" target="editorial_stmt" motivation="commenting">
            <note>
               Christian Science is the religion founded by Mary Baker Eddy. Its followers believe in healing and transformation through spirituality,  specifically through the doctrines and teachings of the Bible. After experiencing her own accident and divine healing, Mary spread her doctrines through her foundational textbook Christian Science and the Church itself. Founded in 1879, Christian Science is still a religion today.
            </note>
         </annotation>
         <annotation xml:id="science_and_health" target="editorial_stmt" motivation="commenting">
            <note>
               Science and Health is the foundation scripture of Christian Science, written by Mary Baker Eddy from 1872-1975. The text is 500 pages long, was published by Christian Science Publishing Co., and is available through the organization's website. Christian Scientists refer to Science and Health alongside the Bible within their sermons, the teachings of both being integral to their religion. 
            </note>
         </annotation>
         <annotation xml:id="line_break" target="poems" motivation="commenting">
            <note>There are two types of line breaks seen in Mary's poetry. An End-Stop is when a line of poetry ends on a period or natural break in the sentence. An Enjambment is when a sentence continues across multiple poetic lines.
            </note>
         </annotation>
         <annotation xml:id="meter" target="poems" motivation="commenting">
            <note>
               Poetic meter refers to the pattern of stressed and unstressed syllables in a line of poetry. Feet contain the repeated pattern of stressed sylablles, and can contain two or three syllables per feet. 
               Two-syllable feet include Iambs (unstressed / stressed), Trochee (stressed / unstressed), and Spondee (stressed / stressed). Three-syllable feet include Anapests (unstressed / unstressed / stressed) and Dactyls (stressed / unstressed / unstressed). 
            </note>
            <!-- Annotations will be marked with xml:id references and bibliographic information, but first need to figure out what tags can be used for such purposes -->
            <!-- GT: I'm not sure if this is what you're looking for here, but you can use <ref> or <ptr/> to point to the bilbiographic entries below -->
         </annotation>
      </listAnnotation>
      <listPerson>
         <head>
            <s>Important People</s>
         </head>
         <person xml:id="mary_baker_eddy">
            <persName>
               <forename>Mary</forename>
               <surname>Baker</surname>
               <surname>Eddy</surname>
            </persName>
            <birth when="1821-07-16"> 16 July 1821 
               <placeName>
                  <settlement type="town">Bow</settlement>
                  <region type="state">New Hampshire</region>
               </placeName>
            </birth>
            <death when="1910-12-03"> 3 December 1910
               <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Newton</settlement>
                  <region type="state">Massachusetts</region>
               </placeName>
            </death>
            <note>Went by Mary Baker up until age 21</note>
            <note>Went by Mary Glover froma ages 22 to 31</note>
            <note>Went by Mary Patterson from ages 32 to 51</note>
            <note>Went by Mary Eddy from ages 56 to 89</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="albert_baker">
            <persName>
               <forename>Albert</forename>
               <surname>Baker</surname>
            </persName>
            <birth when="1810-02-05"> 5 February 1810 
               <placeName>
                  <settlement type="town">Bow</settlement>
                  <region type="state">New Hampshire</region>
               </placeName>
            </birth>
            <death when="1841-10-17"> 17 October 1841
               <placeName>
                  <settlement type="town">Hillsborough</settlement>
                  <region type="state">New Hampshire</region>
               </placeName>
            </death>
            <note>Credited with teaching and mentoring Mary in youth.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="george_washington_glover">
            <persName>
               <forename>George</forename>
               <surname>Washington</surname>
               <surname>Glover</surname>
            </persName>
            <birth when="1811-08-02"> 2 August 1811</birth>
            <death when="1844-06-27"> 27 June 1844
               <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Wilmington</settlement>
                  <region type="state">North Carolina</region>
               </placeName>
            </death>
            <note>Mary's first husband, who died 6 months into their marriage of a fever.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="abigail_baker">
            <persName>
               <forename>Abigail</forename>
               <surname>Baker</surname>
            </persName>
            <birth when="1784-04-18"> 18 April 1784</birth>
            <death when="1849-11-21"> 21 November 1849</death>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="daniel_patterson">
            <persName>
               <forename>Daniel</forename>
               <surname>Patterson</surname>
            </persName>
            <death when="1896-08-14"> 14 August 1896
               <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Saco</settlement>
                  <region type="state">Maine</region>
               </placeName>
            </death>
            <note>Mary separated from Patterson in 1866, due to his desertion and adultery. Their divorce was finalized in 1873, 20 years after they married.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="asa_gilbert_eddy">
            <persName>
               <forename>Asa</forename>
               <surname>Gilbert</surname>
               <surname>Eddy</surname>
            </persName>
            <birth when="1832"> 1832</birth>
            <death when="1882-06-02"> 2 June 1882</death>
            <note>Mary met Asa when he was a student in her class on the teachings of Christian Science. He was her last husband, and they were married until his death.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="george_washington_glover_ii">
            <persName>
               <forename>George</forename>
               <surname>Washington</surname>
               <surname>Glover II</surname>
            </persName>
            <birth when="1844-09-12"> 12 September 1844
               <placeName>
                  <settlement type="town">Sanbornton</settlement>
                  <region type="state">New Hampshire</region>
               </placeName>
            </birth>
            <death when="1915-12-26"> 26 December 1915
               <placeName>
                  <settlement type="county">Lawrence</settlement>
                  <region type="state">South Dakota</region>
               </placeName>
            </death>
            <note>Mary and her son were separated from 1856 to 1879, as he was told she had died. He visited her occasionally after reuniting.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="phineas_parkhurst_quimby">
            <persName>
               <forename>Phineas</forename>
               <surname>Parkhurst</surname>
               <surname>Quimby</surname>
            </persName>
            <birth when="1802-02-16"> 16 February 1802</birth>
            <death when="1866-01-16"> 16 January 1866
               <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Belfast</settlement>
                  <region type="state">Maine</region>
               </placeName>
            </death>
            <note>Quimby treated Mary of her physical ailments in the 60s, and the two discussed healing practices together.</note>
         </person>
      </listPerson>
      <listPlace>
         <head>
            <s>Important Places</s>
         </head>
         <place xml:id="Bow">
            <placeName>
               <settlement type="town">Bow</settlement>
               <region type="state">New Hampshire</region>
            </placeName>
            <note>Where the Baker Home is located, birthplace of Mary and her siblings.</note>
         </place>
         <place xml:id="Sanbornton">
            <placeName>
               <settlement type="town">Sanbornton Bridge</settlement>
               <region type="state">New Hampshire</region>
            </placeName>
            <note>Where the Baker family moved to during Mary's youth and continued to live throughout her adulthood.</note>
         </place>
         <place xml:id="Lynn">
            <placeName>
               <settlement type="town">Lynn</settlement>
               <region type="state">Massachusetts</region>
            </placeName>
            <note>Where Mary lived with Daniel Patterson, and established the Christian Science ptactice later in her life.</note>
         </place>
         <place xml:id="Newton">
            <placeName>
               <settlement type="town">Newton</settlement>
               <region type="state">Massachusetts</region>
            </placeName>
            <note>Where Mary died in 1910.</note>
         </place>
      </listPlace>
      <listEvent>
         <event xml:id="birthday" when="1821-07-16">
            <label>birthday</label>
         </event>
         <!-- Add more important dates: death of relatives, separation from husbands, birth of her son, foundation of Christian Science, publication of Science and Health, fall on the ice, death -->
      </listEvent>
      <listBibl>
         <head>
            <s>Bibliography of Sources</s>
         </head>
         <bibl type="article" xml:id="chronology_of_events_source">
            “A Chronology of Events Surrounding the Life of Mary Baker Eddy.” The Mary Baker Eddy Library, www.marybakereddylibrary.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Mary_Baker_Eddy_Detailed_Annotated_Chronology_2018-12-10.pdf.  
         </bibl>
         <bibl type="website" xml:id="literary_devices_source">
            Glatch, Sean. “12 Literary Devices in Poetry: Identifying Poetic Devices.” Writers.Com, 16 June 2023, writers.com/literary-devices-in-poetry. 
         </bibl>
         <bibl type="article" xml:id="britannica_eddy_source">
            Gottschalk, Stephen. "Mary Baker Eddy". Encyclopedia Britannica, 29 Nov. 2023, https://www.britannica.com/biography/Mary-Baker-Eddy. Accessed 20 February 2024.
         </bibl>
         <bibl type="article" xml:id="wikipedia_eddy_source">
            “Mary Baker Eddy.” Wikipedia, Wikimedia Foundation,  en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary_Baker_Eddy#CITEREFSilberger1980. 
         </bibl>
         <bibl type="article" xml:id="mary_baker_eddy_library_source">
            “Mary Baker Eddy - Deep Read.” Mary Baker Eddy Library, 17 Feb. 2022, www.marybakereddylibrary.org/mary-baker-eddy/mary-baker-eddy-deep-read/. 
         </bibl>
         <bibl type="website" xml:id="christian_science_source">
            “The Christian Science Pastor.” Christian Science, www.christianscience.com/the-christian-science-pastor. Accessed 20 Feb. 2024. 
         </bibl>
         <!-- Is this the correct place to host bibliographic information, or in body of the text? -->
         <!-- GT: it validates! Normally you'd put notes and bibliography in the <back> of your <text>, in which case they're considered part of the text.
            Like endnotes and bibliographies in a printed book you'd buy. <standOff> is a (newer) more database oriented approach, where the notes/bibliographies exist separately: outside and alongside the text. For <listPerson>, <listPlace> and <listEvent>, this is more common. But TEI and digital encoding is a chance to rethink the print models, so if you prefer this organization, that's fine with me. I think it's a terrific experiment with these editorial models. -->
      </listBibl>
   </standOff>
</TEI>
