<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="teibp.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <!--Use this as the master doc for our final portfolio-->
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Jasper N. Bertram Papers</title>
            <author>Various Authors</author>
            <editor>Jules Lockett, Sofia Posada, Nic Staley</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>While these documents represent a small fraction of the materials present within
               archive of Jasper N. Bertram, we hope to attach this TEI encoding to the archival
               record so that it may aid in distribution and availability of these materials
               digitally.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p> The Jasper N. Bertram papers are a collection of letters that include personal
               correspondence, business correspondence, and newspaper clippings. The material
               transcribed in this edition is a sample from those three categories, including
               handwritten letters, typewritten correspondences, and newspaper clippings. <bibl>
                  <title>Jasper N. Bertram Papers</title>
                  <author>Various</author>
                  <publisher>Personal archives, unpublished</publisher>
                  <date>Early 1900's: 1902-1909</date>
                  <idno type="Accession_No">4215-001</idno>
                  <idno type="box_#">3 of 7</idno>
                  <idno type="folder_#">3-2 "General Correspondance"</idno>
               </bibl>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>In an effort to preserve authorial intent of manuscript documents, we have chosen
                  to leave all spelling and grammatical errors unedited. This choice was made in
                  order for our edition to reflect authorial voices of the various persons
                  represented in this collection, and the time period in which the documents were
                  written.</p>
            </normalization>
            <punctuation>
               <p>Some letters contain no punctuation. No corrections were made to preserve
                  authorial voice.</p>
            </punctuation>
            <correction>
               <p>Errors were left unedited; any misspellings or odd capitalizations that appear in
                  the text were directly from the source. Places where text is unidentifiable will
                  be marked &lt;gap/&gt;</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <titlePage>
            <titlePart>...</titlePart>
         </titlePage>
         <div type="editorial_intro">
            <p>The present documents reflect a small sample of the corpus known as the Jasper N.
               Bertram papers. These papers contain an eclectic mix of letters, newspaper clippings,
               business documents, greeting cards, pamphlets, personal correspondences, and notes.
               The documents are printed, typewritten, and handwritten; some contain a mix of text
               types. The archive within the University of Washington Special Collections provides a
               brief <ref type="note" target="#n1">biographical overview</ref> of Jasper N.
               Bertram's life.</p>
            <p>While these documents represent a small fraction of the materials present within the
               archive of Jasper N. Bertram, we hope to attach this TEI encoding to the archival
               record so that it may aid in distribution and availability of these materials
               digitally. The duration of Jasper N. Bertram's life encompasses a critical time in
               our nation's history, from the Civil War, through the Industrial Revolution and the
               First World War, to his death during the Roaring Twenties. The chosen documents
               provide readers with a unique historical perspective of an individual with interests
               rooted in Seattle and beyond.</p>
            <p>In an effort to preserve authorial intent of manuscript documents, we have chosen to
               leave all spelling and grammatical errors unedited. This choice was made in order for
               our edition to reflect authorial voices of the various persons represented in this
               collection, and the time period in which the documents were written. The excerpts
               chosen represent the interests of the editors while also serving to present a sample
               of multiple document types found throughout the collection.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text>
            <body>
               <opener>
                  <orgName ref="#Cralle"><hi rend="caps">J B. Cralle &amp; Co.</hi></orgName>
                  <dateline><date when="1907-04-30"><hi rend="caps">Apr</hi> 30
                     1907</date></dateline>
                  <stamp rend="caps">Atty's.</stamp>
                  <salute>Dear Sir:</salute></opener>

               <p>We have recieved and filled your claim with the proper offi<pc type="EOLhyphen>">-</pc><lb/>cial of the
                  Government, and will prosecute it to a final settlement.<lb/></p>

               <p>Prior to <date when="1900-06-06">June 6, 1900</date>, attorneys' fee were deducted
                  and<lb/> paid them by the Government upon the allowance of claims, but this
                  <lb/>practice in reagrd to fees as follows:<lb/></p>

               <p>"<hi rend="caps">Provided</hi>, That in the settlement of claims of officers,<lb/>
                  soldiers, sailors, and marines, of their repreentatives,<lb/> and all other claims
                  for pay and allowances within the jurisdiction<lb/> of the Auditor for the
                  <lb/>War Department or the Auditor for the Navy Department, presented and filed
                  hereafter in which it is<lb/> the present practice to make deductions of
                  attorneys' fees from<lb/> the amound found due, no deductions of fees for
                  attorneys or <lb/>agents shall hereafter be made, but the draft, check or
                  warrant<lb/> for the full amount found due shall be delivered the payee<lb/> in
                  person or sent to his bona fide post office adress (residence <lb/>of place of
                  business.)"<lb/></p>

               <p>Under this act fees are held to be a matter of adjust<pc type="EOLhyphen>">-</pc><lb/>ment between claimants
                  and attorneys, and the Government <hi rend="caps">does not <lb/>now deduct and pay
                     fees to attorneys as formerly</hi> in any of the above <lb/>described claims
                  filed since the Act of Congress approved <date when="1900-06-06">June 6,<lb/>
                     1900</date>.<lb/></p>

               <p>The former practice of the Government in deducting and <lb/>paying the attorney
                  fees upon settlement with the claimants was <lb/>greatly preferred by us, but the
                  law javing changed this method as <lb/>stated, we are obliged to meet the new
                  order of things.<lb/></p>

               <p>You will, therefore, please remit us the sum of two dollars <lb/>($2) immediately
                  upon receipt of this letter, to be applied to the <lb/>fee in your case, for
                  bounty pay and other dues.<lb/></p>

               <p>We must ask that you comply with this request at once!<lb/></p>

               <closer>
                  <salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
                  <signed><orgName ref="#Cralle">J. B Cralle &amp; Co</orgName></signed>
               </closer>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="endnotes">
                  <note>
                     <note xml:id="Cralle">JB Cralle &amp; Co were claim and pension attorneys.
                        Their firm was located in Washington DC.<ref type="biblio" target="#source6"
                        />See source 6</note>
                  </note>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text>
            <body>
               <opener rend="cursive">
                  <placeName>B Green KY</placeName>
                  <dateline><date when="1903-10-18">Oct 18th 03</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <persName ref="#JN_Bertram">J. N</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Mary_Bertram"
                     >Marry Bertram</persName>
                  <salute>Dear brother &amp; Sister</salute>
               </opener>
               <div rend="cursive">
                  <p>After waiting a long time we received your nice letter and was so proud of it,
                     yes I tried to have the family reunion at any of our houses but failed hence
                     the disapointment to all</p>
                  <p>No <persName>John Green</persName> has never been for the medisan that you left
                     for him his only child is it The faint of death if not dead So I guess he won't
                     want it</p>
                  <p>I have never seen your discharge you must to have lost them before you came
                     here</p>
                  <p>We shall be so proud if you</p>
                  <p>will stop with us on your way to <placeName type="state">Washington</placeName>
                     we shall expect it and write us at once or as Soon as your can aseertain the
                     facts </p>
                  <p><persName ref="#Mary_Bertram">Mary</persName> we have got to be <add
                        place="above">^one</add> of the uppertens since you was here Street cars are
                     running out by our house you can get on, at the depo and get off at our gate
                     the cars run to the cemetry boatlanding &amp; fairground</p>
                  <p>We are getting along the best kind we have a change of diet every day bread and
                     meat one day &amp; meat and bread the next so when you come you Shall Share
                     with us</p>
                  <p>We are having Scarlett feaver &amp; diptheria have had several deths</p>
                  <p>have had Several deths we have a very Serious case close to us it <persName>J.
                        H. Hollands</persName> his 12 year <add place="below">^old </add>boy but is
                     on the rode to helth again</p>
                  <p>no new calls that I know of brother Sister be shure to spend a while with us us
                     you <add place="below">^go</add> North or Northwest feeal that that will be our
                     last meeting and parting without Sum unexcpected change ___
                        <persName>Omar</persName> is at <placeName>Birm-ingham</placeName>
                     <persName>Ala Bruce</persName> at <placeName>Indiana-polis</placeName>
                     <persName>Hial</persName> excpects to go to <persName>Omar</persName> &amp;
                        <persName>Carol</persName> is getting a long as usual has two pet Squieruls
                     and a fish his little gray man got her high braK(unintelligible scribble and
                     struckout) the <date when="1903-07-01">first of July</date> and hasent used her
                     any Since but think he can use her in a few days now write us as soon as you
                     can</p>
               </div>
               <closer>
                  <salute>as ever your Brother</salute>
                  <signed><persName ref="#DH_Bertram">DH Bertram</persName></signed>
               </closer>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="endnotes">
                  <note xml:id="JN_Bertram">"Jasper N. Bertram (1840-1928) was born in Wayne,
                     Kentucky. He enlisted in the Civil War with the Kentucky Volunteers, 9th
                     Regiment, 3rd Division, 1862-1864. He married Mary Ann Garrett on January 1,
                     1866, in Overton, Tennessee and they had five children. He was listed as a
                     school teacher in Kentucky in 1873 and a Republican Party worker in 1882 in the
                     3rd Congressional District. After his first wife died in 1888, he moved to
                     Seattle where he was district manager and salesman. He married Mary Huselby in
                     1896. He died on July 1, 1928 in Seattle, Washington." <ref type="biblio"
                        target="#source1">See source 1</ref>.</note>
                  <note xml:id="Mary_Bertram"/>
                  <note xml:id="Diptheria">Diphtheria is a bacterial respiratory illness that
                     primarily affects children under 5. The disease was considered highly
                     contagious and deadly during its height, at the end of the 19th and beginning
                     of the 20th century. Before the first vaccine was created in the 1890s, 1 out
                     of 10 children infected by the disease died. Although, the vaccine was not
                     widely distributed until the 1920s. <ref type="biblio" target="#source5">See
                        source 5</ref></note>
                  <note xml:id="DH_Bertram">DH Bertam was the brother of Jasper N. Bertram</note>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text>
            <body>
                  <head rend="small_caps"> Notary public, real estates, inusrance. Propery interests of non-residents looked after. </head>
                  <head rend="caps"><orgName> Chelan Real Estate office</orgName></head>
                  <head rend="small_caps"><placeName>Chelan. Washington</placeName><date when="1907-08-07"> Aug 7th, 1907</date></head>
                  <opener rend="typewritten">
                     <salute>Mr. J.H.Bertram,</salute>
                     <placeName>Seattle Wash.</placeName>
                  </opener>
                  <p rend="typewriten">Dear sir: Through <persName>Dr. A.I. Mitchell</persName>, I learn that you are
                     interested in the <placeName ref="#Chelan_country">Chelan Country</placeName> (n3),and contemplate settling here. If you will write
                     me telling me just what you would like in the way of land and how much you would care to
                     invest I could answer your letter and tell you whether such land could be had att all
                     and what the cost would be. You understand we have a fine fruit country and that tha
                     country is rough or rolling .We have also a fine country and few extremes of eithe rheat
                     or col.Reinquishments and homesteads are practically gone.I can s sell you a 40 close to
                     town <hi rend="struck_through">and</hi> atv $20. an acre. Out of this 40 there is 25 acres of the best
                     of fruit land and the balance is pasture.No improvements.This land joins <placeName ref="Lakeside">Lakeside</placeName> (n4)
                     on the south and is on teh first bench above. It is within reach of the town and hangs
                     ovre the hill A person could live in Lakeside if they wish and farm it. I would be glad
                     to hear from you on the subject and will furnish you any information you may wish.</p>
                  <closer rend="cursive">
                     <salute>Very truly,</salute> 
                     <signed>Barnett Stillery.</signed> 
                  </closer>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="endnotes">
                  <note xml:id="Chelan_country">Chelan County is located in central Washington<ref type="biblio" target="source3">see source 3</ref></note>
                  <note xml:id="Lakeside">Lakeside is an unincorporated community located in Chelan County <ref type="biblio" target="source4"> see source 4</ref></note>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text>
            <body>
               <opener rend="cursive">
                  <persName>Douglas</persName>
                  <dateline>March 1908</dateline>
                  <salute>Dear grandpa,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p rend="cursive">I thought you might like to hear from your only grandson.
                  <persName>Mama</persName> is going to write too.
                  I am going to school and trying to learn fast.
                  I have a nice sled and a nice little kitten. 
                  Many nice books and playmates. If you will write I will answer your letter.
                  All the uncles are well, and so is <persName ref="#aunt_nettie">aunt nettie.</persName>
                  Our coldest day this winter was yesterday,<date> March the 14th.</date>
                  What do you think of that for spring?</p>
               <closer rend="cursive">
                  <salute>With much love,</salute>
                  <signed><persName>Ralph</persName>.</signed>
               </closer> 
            </body>
         </text>
         <!-- Start of Nic Staley's documents -->
         <text xml:id="tn_letter" rend="cursive script">
            <body>
               <opener><dateline><placeName type="city" ref="#roseland">Roseland</placeName>
                  <placeName type="state" ref="#louisiana">La</placeName>. <date when="1901-06-27">June
                     27/1901</date></dateline><lb/>
                  <persName ref="#t_noel">Theo Noel</persName>
                  <roleName>President</roleName> of <orgName ref="#tn_co">T.N.Co</orgName><lb/>
                  <placeName type="city" ref="#chicago">Chicago</placeName><lb/> My Dear Sir<lb/></opener>
               <p>A few days ago I rec'd<lb/>
                  <unclear>yours</unclear> of late date giveing<lb/> ^<hi rend="superscript">your</hi>
                  agents the second of <unclear><lb/> -naity</unclear> to become stock holders<lb/> in the
                  "<orgName ref="#tn_co">Theo Noel Company</orgName>.<lb/> The reason I did not at<lb/>
                  first take the five share of<lb/> stock <unclear>and</unclear> had not
                  <unclear>up</unclear> to<lb/> The present was The uncertai<lb/> -nty of my haveing
                  time to<lb/> denote, to the handling the<lb/> remedies, so after geting The<lb/>
                  business well in hand I<lb/> came here to look after I<lb/> decided to take The stock.
                  of<pb/> five shares<lb/> and<del rend="strikethrough">before doing so ask</del> ask<lb/>
                  you <del rend="strikethrough">a few questions</del><lb/> if <del rend="strikethrough"
                     >would</del> it suits you just<lb/> as well to <del rend="strikethrough">let me make
                        out</del><lb/>
                  <del rend="strikethrough">a bill for The $50. worth</del><lb/> instead of taking it
                  all<lb/> in v.o.?</p>
               <lb/>
               <p>Have you a state agent<lb/> for this state?.if so where<lb/> is he located? and
                  have<lb/> you at state agent in<lb/>
                  <placeName type="state" ref="#kentucky">Kentucky</placeName>? in a few<lb/> months I
                  want to visit<lb/> a while in <placeName type="state" ref="#kentucky">Ky</placeName> and
                  would<lb/> like to combine business<lb/> with pleasure while there</p>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="endnotes">
                  <listPerson>
                     <person xml:id="t_noel">
                        <persName>
                           <surname>Noel</surname>
                           <forename>Theophilus</forename>
                        </persName>
                        <note>Soldier in the Confederate army during the United Stated Civil War. Born
                           <date when="1840">1840</date>.</note>
                     </person>
                  </listPerson>
                  <listOrg>
                     <org xml:id="tn_co">
                        <orgName> Theo Noel Company </orgName>
                        <note>Publishing company based in <placeName ref="#chicago"
                           >Chicago</placeName>.</note>
                     </org>
                  </listOrg>
                  <listPlace>
                     <place xml:id="kentucky">
                        <placeName>
                           <region>Kentucky</region>
                        </placeName>
                     </place>
                     <place xml:id="chicago">
                        <placeName>
                           <settlement>Chicago</settlement>
                           <region>Illinois</region>
                        </placeName>
                     </place>
                     <place xml:id="roseland">
                        <placeName>
                           <settlement>Roseland</settlement>
                           <region>Louisiana</region>
                        </placeName>
                     </place>
                     <place xml:id="louisiana">
                        <placeName>
                           <region>Louisiana</region>
                        </placeName>
                     </place>
                  </listPlace>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:id="treasury_dept" rend="print">
            <body>
               <head rend="typewrite">H-3c.</head>
               <lb/>
               <head place="left"><hi rend="bold">Form 1816</hi>.<lb/> Ed. Jan. 6-09-2,000.</head>
               <lb/>
               <opener><hi rend="caps">notice to claimant-no differences</hi>.<lb/>
                  <unclear rend="cursive script">mcx</unclear> Appeal No. <hi rend="typewrite">16518.</hi>
                  <hi rend="gothic"><orgName ref="#treasury">Treauty Department</orgName>,</hi><lb/>
                  <hi rend="caps">office of the<lb/> comptroller of the treasury</hi>.<lb/>
                  <dateline><placeName type="city">Washington, D.C.</placeName>, <date when="1909-01-09"
                     ><hi rend="typewrite">January 30</hi>, 190<hi rend="typewrite"
                        >9</hi></date>.</dateline>
                  <hi rend="typewrite">Mr. <persName ref="#JN_Bertram">Jasper N. <choice>
                     <orig>Butram</orig>
                     <corr>Bertram</corr>
                  </choice></persName>,<lb/>
                     <address>
                        <addrLine>426-34th Avenue, South,<lb/> Seattle, Wash.</addrLine>
                     </address></hi></opener>
               <lb/>
               <p><hi rend="typewrite">Sir</hi>:<lb/> I have examined your appeal, filed <date
                  when="1909-01-09"><hi rend="typewrite">January 9, 1909</hi></date>, from the
                  action<lb/> of the Auditor for the <hi rend="caps typewrite">war</hi> Department, on
                  your claim<lb/>
                  <hi rend="typewrite">for additional bounty under act of <date when="1866-07-28">July 28,
                     1866</date>, as of 9th<lb/> Regt. of Kentucky Infantry,</hi><lb/> per certificate
                  No. <hi rend="typewrite">20392</hi>, dated <hi rend="typewrite"><date when="1908-06-15"
                     >June 15, 1908</date></hi>,<lb/> and find and certify no differences, the action
                  of the Auditor being affirmed.</p>
               <lb/>
               <p rend="typewrite">It is shown by the records that you were enrolled<lb/>
                  <date when="1861-09-24">September 24, 1861</date>, and discharged <date
                     when="1864-09-20">September 20, 1864</date>, by<lb/> reason of promotion to lst
                  Lieutenant. You have been paid<lb/> $100.00 bounty under act of <date when="1861-07-22"
                     >July 22, 1861</date>, and $50.00<lb/> additional bounty under act of <date
                        when="1866-07-28">July 28, 1866</date>. Having been<lb/> discharged for promotion
                  before serving <hi rend="underline">three</hi> years as an<lb/> enlisted man you are not
                  entitled to any more bounty.</p>
               <lb/>
               <p rend="typewrite">Parol evidence will not be accepted to contradict the<lb/> records
                  which show that you were enrolled <date when="1861-09-24">September 24,<lb/>
                     1861</date>, and served less than three years as an enlisted<lb/> man. The time you
                  served as a commissioned officer cannot<lb/> lawfully be counted in computing
                  bounty.</p>
               <lb/>
               <closer>Respectfully, <signed><hi rend="cursive">L.P. Mitchell</hi></signed>
                  <hi rend="cursive script">J.W.R.</hi>
                  <hi rend="typewrite">Assistant</hi> Comptroller <hi rend="cursive script">C.H.</hi></closer>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="endnotes">
                  <listOrg xml:id="treasury">
                     <org>
                        <orgName>United States Department of the Treasury</orgName>
                     </org>
                  </listOrg>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:id="winston" rend="print">
            <body>
               <div1 type="pamphlet_front">
                  <head><hi rend="caps">we are now located in<lb/> our new home</hi><lb/>
                     <address>
                        <addrLine>Winston Building, 1006 to 1016 Arch Street</addrLine>
                        <lb/>
                     </address>
                     <placeName type="city">Philadelphia</placeName><lb/>
                     <hi rend="caps"><orgName ref="#winston_co">the john c. winston
                        co.</orgName></hi><lb/></head>
                  <head rend="bold">From <orgName ref="#phil_rec">Philadelphia "Record,"</orgName>
                     <figure type="illustration" place="inline">
                        <graphic url="Winston%20Building.png"/>
                        <figDesc>An illustration of the Winston Building, described below.</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <date when="1903-08-06">August 6, 1903</date><lb/></head>
                  <div2 style="columns">
                     <p>Workmen yesterday began the demolition of<lb/> the picturesque old Arch Street
                        Presbyterian<lb/> Church, on Arch Street, above Tenth, whose site<lb/> is to be
                        occupied by a large building for <orgName ref="#winston_co">The John<lb/> C.
                           Winston Company</orgName>. The church has not been<lb/> used for several years,
                        and its removal marks an<lb/> important step in the improvement of Arch<lb/>
                        Street for commercial purposes. The inroads of<lb/> trade have driven out nearly
                        all the residents<lb/> east of Broad Street, and west of that throrough-<lb/>fare
                        they are also gradually being forced out.<lb/> The old church has long been
                        admired for the<lb/> purity of its architecture, and its disappearance<lb/> will
                        be regretted by many.<lb/></p>
                     <p>The new building which is to take its place<lb/> will be the largest on Arch
                        street, and will<lb/> be eight stories high, with a frontage of 100 feet<lb/> and
                        a depth of 150 feet. There will be an arcade<cb/> driveway around the entire
                        building, with room<lb/> for wagons to load in the read, under cover. The<lb/>
                        building will be equipped with two freight eleva-<lb/>tors and a passenger
                        elevator, fire-proof vaults<lb/> and other modern conveniences. It will have
                        an<lb/> electrical power plant of 400-horse power, with<lb/> steam heating,
                        electric lighting, etc. The buil-<lb/>ding will be of steel construction and
                        semi-fire-<lb/>proof. The front will have a granite base, with<lb/> brick and
                        terra-cotta above.<lb/></p>
                     <p>The contract price for the building, including<lb/> the power plant is $275,000.
                        The value of the lot<lb/> is $150.000. The entire floor space of the build-<lb/>
                        ing amounts to about 135,000 square feet, or about<lb/> three acres. The building
                        will be completed in<lb/> July 1904, when <orgName ref="#winston_co">The John C.
                           Winston Company</orgName><lb/> will move into it their offices and printing
                        and<lb/> binding plant.-<hi rend="ital">Phila.Record.</hi><pb/></p>
                  </div2>
               </div1>
               <div1 type="pamphlet_back">
                  <head rend="caps">history of our house<lb/></head>
                  <div2>
                     <head rend="caps">how a great publishing house has grown<lb/> out of a small
                        beginning.<lb/></head>
                     <p>The erection of a new and magnificent building, of such unusal size,<lb/> to
                        accommodate our growing business, has awakened a great deal of<lb/> interest, and
                        led to many inquiries regarding the history of our house.<lb/> For the information
                        of those interested, and especially for the informa-<lb/>tion of agents and others
                        in distant parts of the country who do business<lb/> with us, we present the
                        following facts regarding the growth of our<lb/> business during the past twenty
                        years.<lb/></p>
                     <p>In the fall of 1884 <persName ref="#j_winston">Mr. Winston</persName> began this
                        business alone, on one<lb/> floor of a small building immediately opposite the
                        site of our new building<lb/> on Arch Street. He began with the publication of one
                        book, which<lb/> fortunately proved very successful. This book was sold by agents whom<lb/>
                        <persName ref="#j_winston">Mr. Winston</persName> himself employed and trained.
                        Encouraged by this first<lb/> success, <persName ref="#j_winston">Mr.
                           Winston</persName> added one book after another and extended his<lb/>
                        organization into many States, until his business became very extensive.<lb/></p>
                  </div2>
                  <div2>
                     <head rend="caps">formation of the company.<lb/></head>
                     <p>Realizing that a business of this size should not depend upon any one<lb/> man,
                        <persName ref="#j_winston">Mr. Winston</persName> invited into partnership with
                        him a number of able<lb/> and experienced men, and thus formed the present
                        corporate company, with<lb/> an authorized capital of $500,000.<lb/></p>
                     <p> At first <persName ref="#j_winston">Mr. Winston</persName> had his books printed
                        and bound by contract<lb/> with outside printers and binders, but many years ago
                        this was found<lb/> inconvenient. Our present establishment consists of a large
                        printing and<lb/> binding plant equipped with the best modern machinery.<lb/></p>
                  </div2>
                  <div2>
                     <head rend="caps">the publication of bibles.<lb/></head>
                     <p>Aside from the publication of several hundred popular books, many<lb/> of which
                        have reached a sale of hundreds of thousands, <orgName ref="#winston_co">The John
                           C.<lb/> Winston Company</orgName> publish what is known as the "International"
                        line of<lb/> Bibles. This line of Bibles was originally published under the
                        joint<lb/> management of two of the largest religious publication houses in the<lb/>
                        <country>United States</country>. Our Company bought out this business, and has
                        greatly<lb/> increased the line, until it now comprises over 500 styles of Bibles
                        and<lb/> Testaments. It is said that we are the largest Bible publication house
                        in<lb/> the <country>United States</country>, and certainly, taking into account
                        our books and Bibles<lb/> together, we are the largest concern making this line of
                        goods in the world.<lb/></p>
                  </div2>
                  <div2>
                     <head rend="caps">our business acquaintance.<lb/></head>
                     <p>While we do a very extensive business with agents on subscription<lb/> books, and
                        have always made a specialty of this line of books, we are<lb/> to-day doing
                        business all over the world, and are publishing books and<lb/> Bibles in
                        <lang>English</lang>, <lang>French</lang>, <lang>German</lang>,
                        <lang>Swedish</lang>, <lang>Norwegian</lang> and other<lb/> languages.<lb/></p>
                     <p>Any local banker or large merchant, having access to the usual<lb/> mercantile
                        records, can satisfy any inquirer as to our general standing and<lb/> reliability.
                        It is always easier to do business with those with whom you<lb/> are acquainted,
                        and we desire to establish a feeling of confidence with all<lb/> those in
                        correspondence with us, so that they may feel entire confidence<lb/> in any
                        arrangement we may seek to make. If we have had marked and<lb/> unusual success in
                        building up so large a business in a few years, from a<lb/> small beginning, we
                        must attribute it chiefly to our facilities for helping<lb/> agents to succeed,
                        because it has been the success of canvassers that has<lb/> brought about our own
                        success and rapid growth.<lb/></p>
                  </div2>
                  <div2>
                     <head rend="caps"><orgName ref="#winston_co">the john c. winston
                        co.</orgName><lb/></head>
                     <p><orgName ref="#winston_co">The John C. Winston Co.</orgName> are also proprietors
                        of the Union Book and Bible House and the<lb/> Universal Book and Bible House, and
                        are responsible for all contracts made by either of<lb/> these special
                        departments.<lb/></p>
                  </div2>
               </div1>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="endnotes">
                  <listPerson>
                     <person xml:id="j_winston">
                        <persName>
                           <surname>Winston</surname>
                           <forename>John</forename>
                        </persName>
                        <note>Born <date when="1856">1856</date>. Died<date when="1920"/>.</note>
                     </person>
                  </listPerson>
                  <listOrg>
                     <org xml:id="winston_co">
                        <orgName>The John C. Winston Company</orgName>
                        <note>Founded in <date when="1884">1884</date>.</note>
                     </org>
                     <org xml:id="phil_rec">
                        <orgName>The Philadelphia Record</orgName>
                        <note>A daily newspaper published in Philadelphia from <date when="1877"
                           >1877</date>to <date when="1947">1947</date>.</note>
                     </org>
                  </listOrg>
               </div>
            </back>
            <!-- End of Nic Staley's documents -->
         </text>
      </group>
      <back xml:id="appendix">
         <div type="endnotes">
            <note xml:id="n1">"Jasper N. Bertram (1840-1928) was born in Wayne, Kentucky. He
               enlisted in the Civil War with the Kentucky Volunteers, 9th Regiment, 3rd Division,
               1862-1864. He married Mary Ann Garrett on January 1, 1866, in Overton, Tennessee and
               they had five children. He was listed as a school teacher in Kentucky in 1873 and a
               Republican Party worker in 1882 in the 3rd Congressional District. After his first
               wife died in 1888, he moved to Seattle where he was district manager and salesman. He
               married Mary Huselby in 1896. He died on July 1, 1928 in Seattle, Washington." <ref
                  type="biblio" target="#source1">See source 1</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2">"Philedelphia book publisher, 1884 to 1960, original specialty
               Bibles." <ref type="biblio" target="#source2">See source 2</ref>.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3"> Chelan county is located in central Washington <ref type="biblio"
                  target="#source3">See source 3</ref></note>
            <note xml:id="n4">Lakeside an unincorporated community located in Chelan County <ref
                  type="biblio" target="#source4">See source 3</ref></note>

         </div>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Bertram_Papers">
                  <title level="a">Jasper N. Bertram papers</title>.<publisher>Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries</publisher>,
                  <ref target="https://archiveswest.orbiscascade.org/ark:/80444/xv10931">https://archiveswest.orbiscascade.org/ark:/80444/xv10931</ref>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Winston_Company">
                  <title level="a">John C. Winston Company</title>.<publisher>Wikidata</publisher>,
                  <ref target="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q21808712">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q21808712</ref>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Chelan_County" type="webpage">
                  <title level="a">City of Chelan County</title>,<ref target="https://cityofchelan.us/">cityofchelan.us</ref>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="lakeside" type="webpage">
                  <author>Wikipedia Contributors</author>,<title level="a">Lakeside, Washington</title>.<publisher>Wikipedia, the Free Encyclopedia</publisher>,
                  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Lakeside,_Washington&amp;oldid=1186419158">https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Lakeside,_Washington&amp;oldid=1186419158</ref>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Diphtheria" type="webpage">
                 <author>Case Western Reserve University</author>,<title level="a">Diphtheria</title>.<publisher>Case Western Reserve University</publisher>,
                  <ref target="https://artsci.case.edu/dittrick/2014/04/29/deadly-diphtheria-the-childrens-plague/">https://artsci.case.edu/dittrick/2014/04/29/deadly-diphtheria-the-childrens-plague/</ref>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Cralle_Co">
                  <author>JB Cralle &amp; Co</author>,<title level="a">JB Cralle &amp; Co</title>.
                  <ref target="https://www.nps.gov/common/uploads/teachers/lessonplans/General%20Affadavit%201905.pdf">https://www.nps.gov/common/uploads/teachers/lessonplans/General%20Affadavit%201905.pdf</ref>
	       </bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
