<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="teibp.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Observations On the Internal Use of the Solanum or Nightshade</title>
            <author>Thomas Gataker</author>
            <editor>Ramya Arivazhagan and Layla Youssef</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This edition was digitized and edited for the purposes of making older documents more accessible to a wider audience and learning the principles of TEI.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The pamphlet details Gataker’s study of nightshade as a treatment for cancer. He details how to develop a medicinal treatment out of nightshade plants and six different cases of these treatments being given to cancer patients. It is physically available in University of Washington's Special Collections, and was initially first read during class while exploring which documents we'd like to work on for this project. The pamphlet is fragile, with slightly frayed pages and fading ink. However, it is still in a readable condition with proper care and handling while reading.
               <bibl>
                  <title>Observations On the Internal Use of the Solanum or Nightshade</title>
                  <author>Thomas Gataker</author>
                  <publisher>London; Printed for R. and J. Dodsley, in Pall-Mall. Sold by M. Cooper, in Pater-noster-Row.</publisher>
                  <date>1757</date>
                  <idno type="ESTC">T41812</idno>
               </bibl>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="editorial_intro">
            <p>The deadly nightshade has always held a notorious reputation. From it’s use as a hallucinogen in witchcraft and the ancient Greek cult of Dionysus to the rumored preferred poison of Roman empress Livia (Lauterjung), the plant remains a historical symbol of danger and wickedness. Yet, its study and use as medicine starting in the 18th century began altering known understandings and perceptions of the plant. Thomas Gataker, an English surgeon at Westminster Hospital in London, was part of this shift, mainly in his writings advocating for the use of deadly nightshade as a treatment for cancer. His writings in this edition of <emph rend="italics">Observations on the Internal Use of Solanum or Nightshade</emph> highlight the shifting attitudes amongst doctors and scientists towards little understood and mythologized flora.</p>
            <p>With this edition, our goals are to modernize the surface-level visual elements of 18th century texts that could be a hinderance to modern readers. For example, each long “s” used in the original pamphlet is replaced with the modern lowercase “s” in the digital edition. Words with archaic spellings are also modernized, unless otherwise noted as having an original spelling that is crucial to understanding the text. Each of these editorial decisions are made to provide wider access to significant historical materials. The constant shifts in understandings of science and medicine are highly crucial to its implementation as a practice, and having the opportunity to read and understand these historical shifts contributes to that cruciality. With that, this edition aims to provide both historical knowledge and opportunities to implement this knowledge for future study.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <p><emph rend="italics">The following is the account, with some additions, which was read at the <ref target="#royal_history" corresp="#royal_mission">Royal Society</ref>, <date when="1757-05-26">May 26, 1757</date>.<note type="context" place="foot">The Royal Society is the national natural science academy of the UK, whose mission is “to recognise, promote, and support excellence in science and to encourage the development and use of science for the benefit of humanity” (Mission and priorities, The Royal Society). Founded in 1660, the Society in 18th century London functioned as a center of scientific and medical discussion, offering fellowships to and publishing the work of renowned scientists, such as Isaac Newton and Benjamin Franklin, who have made significant progress and discoveries in their fields (History of the Royal Society, Royal Society).</note></emph></p>
         <p>About a half year ago I read a memoir, published in the <emph rend="italics">Bibliotheque des beaux Arts et Sciences</emph>, in which an account is given of a disorder declared to have been cancerous, and to have been cured by an infusion of deadly nightshade. I determined to make some experiments with this plant; but as the season of the year would not then permit me to procure any that was fresh, I was obliged to make use of some nightshade that had been gathered and was dried. Soon after I had begun to give it, with great care and caution, to three or four patients, it was discovered to be the species of nightshade called <ref target="garden_plant" corresp="#garden_medicine">garden nightshade,</ref><note type="context" place="foot">Garden nightshade is a member of Solanaceae or Nightshade family. It differs from deadly nightshade in that it’s toxicity varies depending on environmental conditions and plant maturity, but it is still dangerous to ingest (UC Integrated Pest Management). However it is still commonly used within medicine to treat cancer, as well as dysentery, ulcers, and skin diseases (Kuete et.al, 2017).</note> and not that which is distinguished by the name of deadly, and which is the sort recommended in the memoir abovementioned. Finding however very remarkable effects from the former, and not being then able to procure any of the other kind, I pursued my experiments with the garden nightshade. The cases in which I first tried the operation of this plant, besides the two cancerous cases hereafter to be related, were foul or painful ulcers, obstinate pains in particular parts of the body, <ref target="#scurvy">scorbutic</ref><note type="definition" place="foot">Scorbutic describes the condition of being affected by scurvy (Oxford Reference).</note>eruptions, and other common disorders: but as there were seldom attended with any very particular malignity, when I say, that upon taking the infusion the ulcers healed, the pains ceased, and other complaints were removed; I ought likewise to acknowledge, that the same purposes might possibly have been answered by other medicines, those in several instances this succeeded where the <ref target="#cancer">common means</ref> failed.<note type="context" place="foot">Understandings of cancer in 18th century England revolved around the four humours, a theoretical medicinal model where the body contained four combinations of temperature and moisture that permeated throughout, and was at an ideal state of health when all humours were in correct quantities. Cancer was viewed as a pest that caused severe imbalance in the humours, resulting physicians often taking extreme measures, such as surgery without anesthesia, to restore balance to the body (Skuse, 2015).</note></p>
         <p>By these frequent experiments I became better acquainted with the common operations of the medicine, and with the proper manner of giving it. I found from repeated trials, made with great caution and safety to the patient, that so small a quantity as one <ref target="#grain" corresp="#apothecary">grain-weight</ref><note type="context" place="foot">A unit of mass equal to 1/7000 of a pound, or 0.0648 gram (Oxford Reference). The grain is a metric within the apothecaries’ weight, a traditional weight system in the UK used for measuring pharmaceutical items (Britannica).</note>of the leaf, infused in about an ounce of boiling water, and the liquor afterwards strained from the leaf and taken at bedtime, would sometimes have a <ref target="#deadly">considerable effect</ref>; but that two or three grains seldom failed to either vomit, sweat, or <ref target="#purge">purge</ref> the patient moderately, or to increase the quantity of urine. It sometimes occasioned a giddiness, especially when it made the patient sick; but neither the sickness or the giddiness were constant symptoms; and when they happened, they generally abated or entirely ceased after the first or second dose. The most common effects that I have observed to ensue upon taking this medicine were a heat or warmth diffused in a few hours over the body, a plentiful sweat succeeding this heat, a purging the next day: if a sweat did not break out, an extraordinary discharge of urine was the consequence, and frequently followed likewise by a purging. One or more of the natural evacuations were almost always increased.<note type="context" place="foot">Very small amounts of the deadly nightshade plant, from its leaves to its berries, can have incredibly strong effects on humans and animals. All parts of the plant are toxic, and if consumed or handled without proper coverage, can result in a wide range of symptoms including rapid heartbeat, delirium, vomiting, hallucinations, severe dermatitis, paralysis, and death. However, despite its dangers, deadly nightshade has been used throughout history as medicine (as displayed in this pamphlet), a cosmetic and a weapon. It was common for Venetian women to use belladonna eye-drops, which contained atropine, to dilate their pupils. The Roman army also used the plant as a biological weapon to contaminate their enemies’ food reserves (National Park Service).</note> <note type="definition" place="foot">Purging refers to the forceful expelling of internal items within the body, whether that be through vomiting, bloodletting, or enemas. Purging as a medical practice derived from humoural theory, with physicians aiming to achieve balance throughout the body by forcefully removing any malignant items (Harvard Library).</note></p>
         <p>These are the general effects proceeding from the internal use of the nightshade, and are such as I am persuaded will correspond with the experiments made by the others; as much at least can be expected from any medicine of efficacy given to persons of different constitutions and under different circumstances and states of health.</p>
         <p>As to all the uses of which this medicine may be applied to, time and much experience only can ascertain them. I have already tried it in some disorders with advantage, as I took notice before; but as a circumstantial account of particular cases may be desired, I will relate the effects of the infusion in a few instances.</p>
         <p>I shall begin with two cases of a cancerous nature; not with a view to establish an opinion that this medicine is a specific for that complaint, nor indeed would these cases sufficiently authorise such an opinion; but as they were first in which I tried the medicine, they were likewise the only ones that, till lately, I took a regular account of; and as the particular case which induced me to use the medicine at all is laid to have been a cancer, and radically cured by an infusion of deadly nightshade.</p>
         <p>One of these was a woman about 50 years of age, a patient in the Westminster Hosptial. She had a sore under her right-eye, which began by a slight accident upon the part about a year and half before she came under my care. The sore, which was as broad as a <ref target="#crown">half-crown,</ref><note type="definition" place="foot">A half-crown was a coin and monetary unit used as legal tender in Britain until 1970 (Merriman Webster).</note> consisted of several indigested, foul ulcerations, intermixed with callous eminences, or hard knots rising in particular parts of it, and the whole was encircled by an unequal jagged edge. Below the sore the cheek was discoloured by a deep red appearance, and was swelled. She had suffered considerable and frequent pains in the part many months. The common methods were tried for her relief ineffectually. Amongst other things the solution of mercury, and other mercurials were used so as to produce a slight salivation. The sore however, appeared in full as bad a state as has been just represented, when I began to give her the infusion of garden nightshade. In a month after taking it the pain entirely ceased, and in little more than another month, the ulcerations were healed, and the callosities subsided, leaving only a slight soreness or tenderness of the skin, with two or three scurfy inequalities in the upper part of it. No application was used to the sore except common softening dressings to the keep it from the air.</p>
         <p>As the woman was quite free from pain and saw very little appearance on the part more than was natural; and as she was very desirous to go into the country to her family, I could not prevail on her to stay unnecessarily as she thought, any longer, in order to confirm the cure, and prevent a return of the symptoms. The Medicine, in this instance, occasioned at first a sickness and giddiness, producing a plentiful sweat in the night, and a moderate purging in the morning, with some increase of urine. It continued to sweat her considerably as long as she took it, preserving also in general a lax state of her bowels, and acting sometimes as a diuretic. She never took more than an infusion of two grains at a time. I have not yet had any account of her since she left the hospital.</p>
         <p>The other patient who suffered under this disease, was a woman above 70 years of age, and in the same hospital. She came there about five months ago with a very large and bad-looking sore on her left-breast, with callous edges surrounding the ulcer, and hardnesses in other parts. This complaint began above a year before before with a small hard knot, which increasing, broke into a sore, and for some months had gradually spread broader and corroded deeper. She began to take the infusion of garden nightshade, after a dose or two of purging physic, and in less than three months, using only common applications to the part, the sore was reduced to a very inconsiderable size, without any remaining hardnesses at the edges of it, and had the appearance of healing in a week or ten days. The hardnesses about the breast were likewise diminished. In this situation, she was attacked with feverish complaints, a slight difficulty of breathing, and an inflamatory swelling on her left-hand. Upon these accounts it was judged necessary to suspend the use of the infusion; and during this interval, the surface of the sore enlarged and grew foul again. Soon after, she lost her appetite, and was affected with a general weakness of body, asrising probably in some degree from a long confinement in the hospital. All these circumstances joined her to age, afforded no encouragement to try the medicine again, nor hopes of success from any other method.<ref target="#patient">*</ref><note type="context" place="foot">*She is since dead.</note></p>
         <p>When this woman began to take the infusion it made her giddy, and sweat her very considerably. It continued to sweat her moderately, but never affected her either by urine or stool, and some time before she left off taking the infusion, it produced no visible alteration in any of the natural evacuations, though the dose was increased to five grains. I was afterwards concerned that I had not increased the dose still more, as her strength was not at that time impaired; but the progress of the cure was so remarkably favourable in the method she was then in, and the dose being larger than I had ever given before, I omitted to do what might possibly have been of service to her.</p>
         <p>As I neglected till lately to give a strict attention to the particulars of each case wherein this medicine has been used (except in the two preceding instances) I cannot properly enter into a detail of them: For this reason, as well as to avoid the imputation of giving partial accounts, I shall at present only mention such others as are now in the hospital, and were this day <date when='--06-21'>(June 21)</date> examined there.</p>
   
      </body>
      <back>
         <list>
         <head>Bibliography</head>
            <item><bibl xml:id="apothecary" type="webpage"><title level="a">Apothecaries weight | Units, Definition, &amp; Facts</title>. <title level="m">Britannica</title>, <ref target="https://www.britannica.com/science/apothecaries-weight">www.britannica.com/science/apothecaries-weight</ref>.</bibl></item>
            <item><bibl xml:id="grain" type="webpage">"<title level="a">Grain | Metric, Imperial &amp; Avoirdupois</title>."<title level="m">Britannica</title>, <ref target="https://www.britannica.com/science/grain-unit-of-weight">www.britannica.com/science/grain-unit-of-weight</ref>.</bibl></item>
            <item><bibl xml:id="crown" type="webpage">"<title level="a">Half crown Defintion &amp; Meaning</title>."<title level="m">Merriman Webster</title>, <ref target="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/half%20crown">www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/half%20crown</ref>.</bibl></item>
            <item><bibl xml:id="royal_history" type="webpage">"<title level="a">History of the Royal Society</title>."<title level="m">Royal Society</title>, <ref target="https://royalsociety.org/about-us/history/">royalsociety.org/about-us/history/</ref>.</bibl></item>
            <item><bibl xml:id="purge" type="webpage">"<title level="a">Humoral Theory | Contagion - CURIOSity Digital Collections</title>."<title level="m">CURIOSity Digital Collections</title>, <ref target="https://curiosity.lib.harvard.edu/contagion/feature/humoral-theory">curiosity.lib.harvard.edu/contagion/feature/humoral-theory</ref>.</bibl></item>
            <item><bibl xml:id="garden_medicine" type="book"><author><surname>Kuete</surname>,<forename>V., et al</forename></author>."<title level="a">Anticancer Activities of African Medicinal Spices and Vegetables</title>."<title level="m">Medicinal Spices and Vegetables from Africa</title>, <publisher>Academic Press</publisher>, <date>2017</date>, <biblScope>pp.271-297</biblScope>.<title level="s">ScienceDirect</title>, <ref target="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/B9780128092866000108">www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/B9780128092866000108</ref>.</bibl></item>
            <item><bibl xml:id="royal_mission" type="webpage">"<title level="a">Mission and priorities - what the Royal Society does | Supporting excellence in science</title>."<title level="m">Royal Society</title>, <ref target="https://royalsociety.org/about-us/mission-priorities/">royalsociety.org/about-us/mission-priorities/</ref>.</bibl></item>
            <item><bibl xml:id="deadly" type="webpage">"<title level="a">The Powerful Solanaceae: Belladonna</title>."<title level="m">USDA Forest Service</title>, <ref target="https://www.fs.usda.gov/wildflowers/ethnobotany/Mind_and_Spirit/belladonna.shtml">www.fs.usda.gov/wildflowers/ethnobotany/Mind_and_Spirit/belladonna.shtml</ref>.</bibl></item>
            <item><bibl xml:id="scurvy" type="webpage">"<title level="a">scorbutic</title>."<title level="m">Oxford Reference</title>, <ref target="https://www.oxfordreference.com/display/10.1093/oi/authority.20110803100448189">www.oxfordreference.com/display/10.1093/oi/authority.20110803100448189</ref>.</bibl></item>
            <item><bibl xml:id="cancer" type="book"><author><surname>Skuse</surname>,<forename>Alanna</forename></author>."<title level="a">Introduction</title>."<title level="m">Constructions of Cancer in Early Modern England: Ravenous Natures</title>, <publisher>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher>, <date>2015</date>.<title level="s">National Library of Medicine</title>, <ref target="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK547259/">www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK547259/</ref>.</bibl> </item>
            <item><bibl xml:id="garden_plant" type="webpage">"<title level="a">Weed Gallery: Black Nightshade - UC</title>."<title level="m">UC IPM</title>, <ref target="https://ipm.ucanr.edu/PMG/WEEDS/black_nightshade.html">ipm.ucanr.edu/PMG/WEEDS/black_nightshade.html</ref>.</bibl></item>
         </list>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
