<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Ladies' Handbook of Fancy and Ornamental Work</title>
            <author>Miss Florence Hartley</author>
            <editor>Riley Hull</editor>
            <editor>Tara Boyd</editor>
            <editor>Trisha Binwade</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This text in particular is interesting because of the connectivity it fosters between
               the past and the present, specifically in regards to the subject of “fancy and
               ornamental” work. In that sense, our edition hopes to offer a text that highlights
               various methods of ornamental work that were utilized in the past, thus allowing us
               to preserve these traditional practices, introduce a new audience of people to them,
               and invite comparison between the methods of the past and those of the present day.
               Within our class at the University of Washington, we first chose a specific section
               of the text to focus on, ultimately ending up choosing the knitting section because
               its relatively concise nature meant we would be able to complete an entire section.
               We then transcribed the text into plain text digital files and created a project
               schema to guide our TEI markup. We plan to encode and markup our text and create some
               sort of digital edition interface to help facilitate our goals and bring our text to
               a modern audience.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This text is found in the Costume and Textile Collections within the University of
               Washington Special Collections Library. It is a medium-sized, hard-bound text in a
               dark brown binding. <bibl>
                  <title>The Ladies' Handbook of Fancy and Ornamental Work</title>
                  <author>Miss Florence Hartley</author>
                  <publisher>John E. Potter &amp; Company</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>617 Samson Street, Philadelphia PA</pubPlace>
                  <date>1859</date>
                  <idno type="callNumber">TT 750 H37</idno>
               </bibl>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>There were very minimal spelling modernizations, as most of the text consisted of
                  words that fit in with modern vernacular and would be understandable to a modern
                  audience.</p>
            </normalization>
            <correction>
               <p>There were very minimal grammar and spelling errors, which were ultimately
                  adjusted by the editors based on the text’s established patterns and grammatical
                  structure.</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" rend="roman">
      <front>
         <div type="editorial_intro">
            <p>Published in 1859 by John E. Potter &amp; Company, The Ladies’ Handbook of Fancy and
               Ornamental Work is an instructional text written by Miss Florence Hartley, who
               ensures her readers that the material within her pages was “compiled from the best
               authorities.” This historical handbook is centered around traditionally-feminine
               crafts and skills, such as sewing, baking, crocheting, embroidery, and – as this
               editorial edition specifically focuses on – knitting. Given that these types of texts
               are not as commonplace in today’s society or literary sphere, Hartley’s text provides
               an interesting look at the culture and practices of the past.</p>
            <p>Specifically focusing our efforts on Hartley’s instructions for knitting, this
               specific edition offers an overview of numerous knitting-based crafts exactly as they
               were done in the late nineteenth century. We hope to bring visibility to these
               traditional practices by presenting them to a new audience of people, ultimately
               helping to preserve the knowledge and culture of past generations. For those that
               have no prior experience with knitting, this text may serve as a captivating
               introduction to the practice itself, especially in the context of its history. On the
               other hand, for readers that do have experience with knitting, this edition may
               provide a basis for intriguing comparisons between the methods of the past and those
               of the present day.</p>
            <p>For this edition, there were very minor changes made from the source text,
               specifically in terms of transcription. While a majority of Hartley’s text is indeed
               presentable to a modern audience, there were a small number of spelling and grammar
               alterations made to best ensure that the instructions of this edition were as clear
               as possible.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="glossary" xml:id="ExplanationOfTerms">
            <head type="main" rend="caps">Explanation of Terms Used in Knitting, and Hints on
               Knitting.</head>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="CastOn">
               <ref type="note" target="#n1"><term><hi rend="italics">To cast on-</hi></term>
                  <gloss>The first interlacement of the cotton on the needle.</gloss></ref></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="CastOff">
               <term><hi rend="italics">To cast off-</hi></term>
               <gloss>to knit two stitches, and to pass over the second, and so on to the last
                  stich, which is to be secured by drawing the thread through.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="CastOver">
               <term><hi rend="italics">To cast over-</hi></term>
               <gloss>to bring the cotton forward round the needle.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="Narrow">
               <term><hi rend="italics">To narrow-</hi></term>
               <gloss>to lessen by bringing two stitches together.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="Seam">
               <term><hi rend="italics">To seam-</hi></term>
               <gloss>to knit a stitch with the cotton before the needle.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="Widen">
               <term><hi rend="italics">To widen-</hi></term>
               <gloss>to increase by making a stitch, bringing the cotton round the needle, and
                  knitting the same when it occurs.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="ATurn">
               <term><hi rend="italics">A turn-</hi></term>
               <gloss>two rows in the same stitch, backwards and forwards.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="ToTurn">
               <term><hi rend="italics">To turn-</hi></term>
               <gloss>to change the stitch.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="Row">
               <term><hi rend="italics">A row-</hi></term>
               <gloss>the stitches from one end of the needle to the other.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="Round">
               <term><hi rend="italics">A round-</hi></term>
               <gloss>a row when the stitches are on two, three, or more needles.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="PlainRow">
               <term><hi rend="italics">A plain row-</hi></term>
               <gloss>that composed of simple knitting.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="PearlARow">
               <term><hi rend="italics">To pearl a row-</hi></term>
               <gloss>to knit with the cotton before the needle.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="Rib">
               <term><hi rend="italics">To rib-</hi></term>
               <gloss>to work alternate rows of plain and pearl knitting.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="BringTheThreadForward">
               <term><hi rend="italics">To bring the thread forward-</hi></term>
               <gloss>to bring the cotton forward so as to make an open stitch.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="LoopStitch">
               <term><hi rend="italics">A loop stitch-</hi></term>
               <gloss>made by bringing the cotton before the needle, which in knitting the
                  succeeding stitch, will again take its own place.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="SlipOrPassAStitch">
               <term><hi rend="italics">To slip or pass a stitch-</hi></term>
               <gloss>to change it from one needle to the other without knitting it.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="FastenOn">
               <term><hi rend="italics">To fasten on-</hi></term>
               <gloss>the best way is to place the ends contrariwise, and knit a few stitches with
                  both together.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="TakeUnder">
               <term><hi rend="italics">To take under-</hi></term>
               <gloss>to pass the cotton from one needle to the other without changing its
                  position.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse"><hi rend="italics"><ref target="#PearlARow">Pearl</ref>,
                     <ref target="#Seam">seam</ref>,</hi> and <hi rend="italics"><ref target="#Rib"
                     >rib-stitch</ref></hi> are the same.</ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">Be careful in knitting to have the cotton or wool of a
               moderate tension-not too lose, nor too tight.</ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">When it is requisite to <ref type="StitchType"
                  target="#CastOff">cast off</ref>, and continue a row on a separate needle, run a
               coarse thread through the <ref target="#CastOff">cast off</ref> stitches, as they are
               easily taken up when required.</ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">It is a good plan to have children taught to knit, boys as
               well as girls, and to have them learn to knit without looking at their work. Old
               ladies who have lost their sight often knit very beautifully, and as a general rule
               we find that they began very young, and learned to knit without giving their work
               steady attention. The blind in all Asylums are beautiful knitters, and in case of any
               accident to the eyesight it would be a great resource, as well as when deprived of
               sight by old age.</ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse"><ref type="note" target="#n2">Knitting needles vary in size
                  and length. For small articles the short ones are most convenient. They are made
                  of steel, bone, ivory, or wood, and you purchase such sizes as agrees with the
                  work you have to do. In all large trimming stores where this kind of material is
                  kept, they will tell you the best sizes, if you are ignorant yourself.</ref></ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">Here is a cut of a gauge for measuring needles for knitting
               and netting meshes, and for crochet needles.</ab>
            <ab type="figure">
               <ref target="ExplanationOfTerms">
                  <figure type="ToolImage">
                     <graphic url="WireGauge.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>A side-view of a metal gauge tool, resembling a spoked wheel with a
                        hollow center and several spokes labeled with numbers 1-19.</figDesc>
                     <p rend="bottom"><hi rend="caps">Wire Gauge</hi></p>
                  </figure>
               </ref>
            </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" xml:id="OperaCap">
            <head type="main" rend="caps">Opera Cap</head>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">These caps look the prettiest when of two colors. The
               material is single Berlin wool. Scarlet and white contrast extremely well. To
               commence, <ref target="#CastOn">cast on</ref> seventy-two loops on the smallest sized
               ivory needles, with the scarlet wool; knit and purl until you have five <ref
                  target="#Row">rows</ref> knitted on the right side; this forms one stripe. Take
               the white wool and repeat this, only reversing the stripe, continue this process
               until you have nine stripes, purled and knitted alternately; five of the scarlet,
               four of the white. Before <ref target="#CastOff">casting off</ref> prepare as
               follows: take the first loop upon your needle, drop the second, take the third, and
               so on to the end of the row, taking care to avoid any mistake, which would be the
               ruin of the whole. The first and last loops must of course be preserved. You will now
               have just half the original number of loops upon your needle. <ref target="#CastOff"
                  >Cast off</ref>, leaving the wool very loose. Afterwards assit the dropped loops
               to run down. This makes a very simple but very pretty stitch in knitting.</ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">The fringe is now to be added, which is done by <ref
                  target="#LoopStitch">looping</ref> lengths of wool through the stitches just <ref
                  target="#CastOff">cast off</ref>, and slipping the ends through the loop, so as to
               form a knot.</ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">The ends of the knitted pieces are now to be gathered up
               with a needle, the ribbon string attached, a pretty rosette of the same sewed on over
               the gathering up, and this useful little article is completed.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" xml:id="FourBeautifulPatterns">
            <head type="main" rend="caps">Four Beautiful Patterns</head>
            <head type="sub" rend="italics">Of Lace Edgings, for Collars, Dresses, &amp;c.</head>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">By means of the following directions, every lady can provide
               herself with lace edgings of the most durable kinds, and without either much expense
               or trouble. These laces, when knit with fine thread and small needles, are
               exceedingly pretty. When they are intended for common wear, or to trim the bottom of
               petticoats, they should be knit with needles of the ordinary size, and coarse cotton.
               They wash well, and wear a long time. After a little practice, a great facility in
               knitting them is acquired, and the work progresses with a rapidity which young
               beginners are apt to despair of obtaining.</ab>
            <ab type="InstructionList">
               <ab><ref target="#CastOn">Cast on</ref> 8 stitches.-1st <ref target="#Row"
                  >row</ref>,-take off the first stitch without knitting it, knit <ref
                     target="#Plain">plain</ref> the 2 next, lap in the thread once, take off 1
                  stitch, knit 1, <ref target="#SlipOrPassAStitch">slip and bind</ref>, knit 1, lap
                  in the thread twice, knit 1, lap in the thread twice, knit 1.</ab>
               <ab>2nd <ref target="#Row">row</ref>,-knit <ref target="#Plain">plain</ref> 2
                  stitches, <ref target="#Seam">seam</ref> 1, and put back your thread, knit 2, seam
                  1, and put back your thread, knit 2, seam 1, and put back your thread, knit
                  3.</ab>
               <ab>3rd <ref target="#Row">row</ref>,-take off the first stitch, knit 2, lap in the
                  thread, take off 1, knit 1, <ref target="#SlipOrPassAStitch">slip and bind</ref>,
                  knit the rest.</ab>
               <ab>4th <ref target="#Row">row</ref>,-knit the two first, <ref
                     target="#SlipOrPassAStitch">slip and bind</ref>, knit, and <ref
                     target="#SlipOrPassAStitch">slip and bind</ref>, until only 7 stitches are on
                  the left hand needle, and one on the other, knit 3, <ref target="#Seam">seam</ref>
                  1, and put back your thread, knit the rest.</ab>
            </ab>
            <ab type="InstructionList">
               <ab><ref target="#CastOn">Cast on</ref> 11 stitches.-1st <ref target="#Row"
                  >row</ref>,-take off the first stitch, knit 2, lap in the thread, take off 1, knit
                  1, <ref target="#SlipOrPassAStitch">slip and bind</ref>, knit 1, lap in the thread
                  twice, knit 1.</ab>
               <ab>2nd <ref target="#Row">row</ref>,-knit 2, <ref target="#Seam">seam</ref> 1, and
                  put back your thread, knit 2, <ref target="#Seam">seam</ref> 1, and put back your
                  thread, knit 2, <ref target="#Seam">seam</ref> 1, and put back your thread, knit
                  2, <ref target="#Seam">seam</ref> 1, and put back your thread, knit 3.</ab>
               <ab>3rd <ref target="#Row">row</ref>,-take off 1, knit 2, lap in the thread, take off
                  1, knit 1, <ref target="#SlipOrPassAStitch">slip and bind</ref>, knit 1, lap in
                  the thread, take off 1, knit 1, <ref target="#SlipOrPassAStitch">slip and
                     bind</ref>, knit the rest.</ab>
               <ab>4th <ref target="#Row">row</ref>,-knit 2, <ref target="#SlipOrPassAStitch">slip
                     and bind</ref>, knit, and <ref target="#SlipOrPassAStitch">slip and bind</ref>,
                  until only 10 stitches are on the left hand needle, and one on the other, knit 3,
                     <ref target="#Seam">seam</ref> 1, and put back your thread, knit 2, <ref
                     target="#Seam">seam</ref> 1, and put back your thread, knit the rest.</ab>
            </ab>
            <ab type="InstructionList">
               <ab><ref target="#CastOn">Cast on</ref> 11 stitches.-1st <ref target="#Row"
                  >row</ref>,-knit 3, make 1, <ref target="#Narrow">narrow</ref> 1, knit 1, make 1,
                     <ref target="#Narrow">narrow</ref> 1, make 2, <ref target="#Narrow"
                     >narrow</ref> 1, knit 1.</ab>
               <ab>2nd <ref target="#Row">row</ref>,-knit 3, <ref target="#Seam">seam</ref> 1, and
                  put back your thread, knit 2, make 1, <ref target="#Narrow">narrow</ref> 1, knit
                  1, make 1, <ref target="#Narrow">narrow</ref> 1, knit 1.</ab>
               <ab>3rd <ref target="#Row">row</ref>,-knit 3, make 1, <ref target="#Narrow"
                     >narrow</ref> 1, knit 1, make 1, <ref target="#Narrow">narrow</ref> 1, knit
                  4.</ab>
               <ab>4th <ref target="#Row">row</ref>,-knit 2, <ref target="#SlipOrPassAStitch">slip
                     and bind</ref>, knit 4, make 1, <ref target="#Narrow">narrow</ref> 1, knit 1,
                  make 1, <ref target="#Narrow">narrow</ref> 1, knit 1.</ab>
            </ab>
            <ab type="InstructionList">
               <ab><ref target="#CastOn">Cast on</ref> 7 stitches.-1st <ref target="#Row"
                  >row</ref>,-take off 1 stitch, knit 2, lap in the thread once, <ref
                     target="#Narrow">narrow</ref> 1, lap in the thread twice, <ref target="#Narrow"
                     >narrow</ref> 1.</ab>
               <ab>2nd <ref target="#Row">row</ref>,-make 1 stitch, knit 2, <ref target="#Seam"
                     >seam</ref> 1, put back your thread, knit 1, lap in the thread once, <ref
                     target="#Narrow">narrow</ref> 1, knit 2.</ab>
               <ab>3rd <ref target="#Row">row</ref>,-take off 1, knit 2, lap in the thread once,
                     <ref target="#Narrow">narrow</ref> 1, lap in the thread twice, <ref
                     target="#Narrow">narrow</ref> 1, lap in the thread twice, <ref target="#Narrow"
                     >narrow</ref> 1.</ab>
               <ab>4th <ref target="#Row">row</ref>,-make 1, knit 2, <ref target="#Seam">seam</ref>
                  1, and put back your thread, knit 2, <ref target="#Seam">seam</ref> 1, and put
                  back your thread, knit 1, lap in the thread once, <ref target="#Narrow"
                     >narrow</ref> 1, knit 2.</ab>
               <ab>5th <ref target="#Row">row</ref>,-take off 1, knit 2, lap in the thread once,
                     <ref target="#Narrow">narrow</ref> 1, knit 7.</ab>
               <ab>6th <ref target="#Row">row</ref>,-knit 8, lap in the thread once, <ref
                     target="#Narrow">narrow</ref> 1, knit 2.</ab>
               <ab>7th <ref target="#Row">row</ref>,-take off 1, knit 2, lap in the thread once,
                     <ref target="#Narrow">narrow</ref> 1, lap in the thread twice, <ref
                     target="#Narrow">narrow</ref> 1, lap in the thread twice, <ref target="#Narrow"
                     >narrow</ref>, lap in the thread twice, <ref target="#Narrow">narrow</ref> 1,
                  knit 1.</ab>
               <ab>8th <ref target="#Row">row</ref>,-knit 3, <ref target="#Seam">seam</ref> 1, and
                  put back your thread, knit 2, <ref target="#Seam">seam</ref> 1, and put back your
                  thread, knit 2, <ref target="#Seam">seam</ref> 1, and put back your thread, knit
                  1, lap in the thread once, <ref target="#Narrow">narrow</ref> 1, knit 2.</ab>
               <ab>9th <ref target="#Row">row</ref>,-take off 1, knit 2, lap in the thread once,
                     <ref target="#Narrow">narrow</ref> 1, knit 10.</ab>
               <ab>10th <ref target="#Row">row</ref>,-knit, and <ref target="#SlipOrPassAStitch"
                     >slip and bind</ref> 8, leaving 6 on the other needle, then knit 2, lap in the
                  thread once, <ref target="#Narrow">narrow</ref> 1, knit 2.</ab>
            </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" xml:id="ABabysSock">
            <head type="main" rend="caps">A Baby's Sock</head>
            <ab type="materials" rend="italics">With 2 colors done in stripes, and double German
               lamb's-wool.</ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse"><ref type="#CastOn">Cast on</ref> 26 stitches, knit a <ref
                  target="#PlainRow">plain <ref target="#Row">row</ref></ref> with the first color,
                  <ref target="#FastenOn">fasten on</ref> the second, knit a <ref target="#Row"
                  >row</ref>, adding a stitch at the end for the heel, and back again; then take the
               first color, knit a <ref target="#Row">row</ref>, adding another stitch, and back
               again; continue the same, alternately, but without adding any more stitches for the
               heel, until there are 6 ridges of each color; then with the first, knit a <ref
                  target="#Row">row</ref>, and in coming back, <ref target="#CastOff">cast off</ref>
               15 stitches, beginning from the end at which you added two sticthes, knit the 13 that
               are left; with the second color, knit a <ref target="#Row">row</ref> and back again,
               then knit a <ref target="#Row">row</ref> and back again with the first, and continue
               the same until you have four ridges of the second, and three of the first color: then
               with the first color knit the 13 stitches, add 15, and knit back again. Finish this
               side like the other, only decreasing for the heel. It is then sewed up in the shape
               of a shoe. Take four needles, pick up the 36 stitches round the instep, putting 12 on
               each of three needles, and knit two <ref target="#Round">rounds</ref>
               <ref target="#PlainRow">plain</ref>, then pass the lamb's-wool forward, so as to form
               a stitch, <ref target="#SlipOrPassAStitch">slip</ref> a stitch, and knit two <ref
                  target="#PlainRow">plain</ref>, then pull the <ref target="#SlipOrPassAStitch"
                  >slipped</ref> stitch over the 2 knitted ones, <ref target="#SlipOrPassAStitch"
                  >pass</ref> the lamb's-wool forward, and repeat this for one <ref target="#Round"
                  >round</ref>, continue <ref target="#PlainRow">plain</ref> knitting for an inch;
               after that, <ref target="#Rib">rib</ref> 4 <ref target="#Row">rows</ref>, knit 4,
                  <ref target="#Rib">rib</ref> 4, knit 2, and <ref target="#CastOff">cast
               off</ref>.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" xml:id="BabysSocks1stSize">
            <head type="main" rend="caps">Baby's Socks. 1st Size.</head>
            <ab type="materials" rend="italics">Two ivory needles, No. 12, and 3-ply fleecy are
               required.</ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse"><ref target="#CastOn">Cast on</ref> 24 stitches; knit two
                  <ref target="#PlainRow">plain</ref>
               <ref target="#Row">rows</ref>, add one stitch; knit 2 more <ref target="#Row"
                  >rows</ref> and add another stitch which forms the heel; then continue knitting
               until you can count 10 ridges; <ref target="#CastOff">cast off</ref> 14 stitches,
               beginning from where you added on for the heel: knit 6 more ridges, add on 14
               stitches, and make this side to match with the other, decreasing for the heel. Pick
               up the 14 <ref target="#LoopStitch">loops</ref> on each side, with the 6 in the
               middle, and put them all on one needle: knit a <ref target="#PlainRow">plain</ref>
               <ref target="#Row">row</ref>, then a <ref target="#Row">row</ref> of holes for the
               ribbon to pass through, which is done in this manner:-begin with the lamb's-wool <ref
                  target="#BringTheThreadForward">forward</ref>, <ref target="#SlipOrPassAStitch"
                  >slip</ref> a stitch, knit the next, and <ref target="#SlipOrPassAStitch">pass the
                  slipped</ref> stitch over the knitted one; after this <ref target="#Row">row</ref>
               is finished, knit 8 ridges.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" xml:id="Fringe1">
            <head type="main" rend="caps">Fringe. No. 1.</head>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">A skein of knitting cotton must be cut into 8 lengths for
               the fringe; or, if you wish your fringe to be very deep, cut your skein into 4 or 6.
               The most convenient way, is to divide these lengths into sets containing 3 threads in
               each, and lay them before you, then with a ball of the same cotton, and two steel
               needles, which should be rather coarse, <ref target="#CastOn">cast on</ref> 8
               stitches, and knit 1 <ref target="#Row">row</ref>
               <ref target="#PlainRow">plain</ref>; begin the next <ref target="#Row">row</ref> by
               knitting the first 2 stitches <ref target="#PlainRow">plain</ref>, bring the cotton
                  <ref target="#BringTheThreadForward">forward</ref>, knit 2 stitches taken
               together, by this means you make a <ref target="#LoopStitch">loop</ref> stitch; take
               1 of the sets of cotton, put the ends even, double it in half, and <ref
                  target="#LoopStitch">loop</ref> it over the needle you are knitting with, <ref
                  target="#BringTheThreadForward">forward</ref>; knit 1 stitch, <ref
                  target="#SlipOrPassAStitch">pass</ref> the set back between the needles, knit 2
               stitches, bring the set <ref target="#BringTheThreadForward">forward</ref> again, and
               knit the last stitch. The back <ref target="#Row">rows</ref> are <ref
                  target="#PlainRow">plain</ref> knitting; you must be careful to take the whole
               head of the set with the 4th stitch, which leaves 4 to be knitted <ref
                  target="#PlainRow">plain</ref>, and you have 8 as at the beginning; after
               finishing this <ref target="#Row">row</ref>, give the set or tuft a pull down, which
               puts it in its right place, before beginning another.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" xml:id="Fringe2">
            <head type="main" rend="caps">Fringe. No.2. </head>
            <ab><ref target="#CastOn">Cast on</ref> 9 stitches. <ref target="#SlipOrPassAStitch"
                  >Slip</ref> the 1st stitch, knit the 2nd and 3rd, <ref
                  target="#BringTheThreadForward">bring the thread forward</ref>, knit 2 together,
               knit 1, <ref target="#BringTheThreadForward">turn the thread forward</ref>, knit 2
               together, knit the last. When you have the length you want, <ref target="#CastOff"
                  >cast off</ref> 5 stitches, and unravel the 4 others, which form the fringe.</ab>
            <ab>This fringe may be made wider, by <ref target="#CastOn">casting on</ref> 12 or 15
               stitches.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" xml:id="HerringBonePurse">
            <head type="main"><hi rend="caps">Herring-Bone Purse.</hi></head>
            <ab type="materials"><hi rend="italics">Two needles only are required for this
                  knitting.</hi></ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse"><ref target="#CastOn">Cast on</ref> 88 stitches, begin with
               the silk forward, <ref target="#SlipOrPassAStitch">slip a stitch</ref>, knit a
               stitch, pass the 1st over the 2nd, knit a stitch, <ref target="BringTheThreadForward"
                  >bring the silk forward</ref>, and <ref target="#Rib">rib</ref> the next. When
               this is done, the silk will be forward; begin again.</ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">If the purse is required to be longer, <ref target="#castOn"
                  >cast on</ref> as many stitches as are necessary, observing that it must be a
               number which can be divided by four.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" xml:id="StrongPurse">
            <head type="main"><hi rend="caps">A Strong Purse.</hi></head>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">With 2 steel needles and coarse netting silk, <ref
                  target="#CastOn">cast on</ref> 60 stitches, knit the first, <ref
                  target="BringTheThreadForward">bring the silk forward</ref>, <ref
                  target="#SlipOrPassAStitch">slip a stitch</ref>, knit the next, and pull the
               slipped stitch over the knitted one, bring the silk forward and begin again. The
               second row is <ref target="PlainRow">simple knitting</ref>.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" xml:id="PorcupineKnittingForAPurse">
            <head type="main"><hi rend="caps">Porcupine Knitting For A Purse.</hi></head>
            <ab type="materials"><hi rend="italics">Four fine needles, nearly 3 <ref type="note"
                     target="#n3">skeins</ref> of netting silk, and one string of gold beads are
                  required. Thread some of the beads on the silk, before you begin.</hi></ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse"><ref target="CastOn">Cast</ref> 36 stitches on each of 3
               needles, knit a <ref target="PlainRow">plain</ref>
               <ref target="Round">round</ref>; knit 4 stitches, <ref target="BringTheThreadForward"
                  >bring the silk forward</ref>, knit a stitch—this is the centre stitch of the
                  pattern—<ref target="BringTheThreadForward">bring the silk forward</ref>, knit 4
               stitches, <ref target="SlipOrPassAStitch">slip a stitch</ref>, <ref
                  target="TakeUnder">taking it under</ref>, knit 2 taken together, pull the slipped
               stitch over it, then begin knitting the 4 stitches, etc.; it is better at the end of
               each needle to knit a stitch of the next one, as it prepares for the next <ref
                  target="Round">round</ref>. Continue thus for 6 <ref target="Round">rounds</ref>,
               increasing before and after every centre stitch, and knitting till within 1 of where
               you decreased, which <ref target="SlipOrPassAStitch">stitch slip</ref>, knit the next
               2 together, and pull the <ref target="SlipOrPassAStitch">slipped stitch</ref> over
               it. Knit a <ref target="PlainRow">plain</ref>
               <ref target="Round">round</ref>. Knit another <ref target="Round">round</ref>
               <ref target="Plain Row">plain</ref>, excepting over the centre stitches, where you
               are to knit a bead, bringing it through the stitch. Knit a <ref target="PlainRow"
                  >plain</ref>
               <ref target="Round">round</ref>, keeping the beads on the outside of the purse. (This
               purse is knitted wrong side outwards.) Knit to within one stitch of the bead stitch,
               which <ref target="SlipOrPassAStitch">slip</ref>; knit 2 together: these 6 <ref
                  target="Round">rounds</ref> increase each side of the stitch you decreased with
               the last pattern, which makes that the centre stitch for the bead.</ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">It is easy to count the number of <ref target="Round"
                  >rounds</ref> you have done, at the place where you decreased.</ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">This pattern is very pretty for a boa, knitted with German
               lamb's wool, and needles No.15.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" xml:id="SpottedPurse">
            <head type="main"><hi rend="caps">Spotted Purse.</hi></head>
            <ab type="InstructionProse"><ref target="CastOn">Cast on</ref> 69 stitches; take off the
               first stitch, <ref target="BringTheThreadForward">bring the silk forward</ref>, <ref
                  target="SlipOrPassAStitch">slip a stitch</ref>, knit 2, pass the slipped stitch
               over the 2 last, repeat this to the end of the <ref target="Row">row</ref>. The back
                  <ref target="Row">rows</ref> are <ref target="Rib">ribbed</ref>.</ab>
            <ab type="InstructionalProse">This pattern is very pretty in two colors, changing them
               every 2 <ref target="Row">rows</ref>.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" xml:id="AnotherPurse">
            <head type="main"><hi rend="caps">Another Purse.</hi></head>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">First <ref target="Row">row</ref>: <ref
                  target="SlipOrPassAStitch">slip a stitch</ref>, knit a stitch, <ref
                  target="SlipOrPassAStitch">pass the first stitch</ref> over the second; repeat
               this to the end of the <ref target="Row">row</ref>. Second <ref target="Row"
                  >row</ref>: <ref target="BringTheThreadForward">bring the silk forward</ref> every
               time.</ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">This is a very pretty stitch for doyleys, with a plain
               border. Any even number of stitches may be set up.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" xml:id="ANetPurseInPoints">
            <head type="main"><hi rend="caps">A Net Purse In Points.</hi></head>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">Fifty stitches long, and 80 <ref target="Row">rows</ref>
               wide, of a middle-sized silk and mesh. Net 31 stitches, with one color, and back
               again; then 28, 25, 22, 19, and back again to each; then with the other color, begin
               at the distance of 19 stitches, and net until you meet the side already done: pass
               the needle through the stitch to connect them. Half a point is now done, you reverse
               the number of stitches to complete it.</ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">It is also very pretty if the points are made longer, say 45
               stitches, decreasing by four stitches every other <ref target="Row">row</ref>, until
               you leave only 5 for the other point.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" xml:id="CorkscrewNettingForAPurse">
            <head type="main"><hi rend="caps">Corkscrew Netting For A Purse.</hi></head>
            <ab type="materials"><hi rend="italics">Two different colored silks are required, for
                  instance, brown and blue; 1 mesh, and 2 needles; thread each of the needles with
                  one color. A round foundation, consisting of 60 stitches, should be
               used.</hi></ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">Join both needles on together, net with the brown 30
               stitches, then begin with the blue and net the other 30 stitches; net the blue silk
               back, and continue it over 6 stitches of the brown; now take the needle with brown,
               pass it through the blue stitch, and net till you meet the needle with blue, <ref
                  target="ToTurn">turn</ref> back (still with the brown silk) and net round till you
               have gone over 6 blue stitches; net with blue again, passing the needle through the
               brown stitch; continue thus advancing each color 6 stitches at one side, and receding
               at the other, till the purse is one-third long enough, then begin the opening, which
               is made by omitting to pass the silk through the stitch at one place; the pattern you
               must carry on as before, for which you will be obliged to fasten on your silk to fill
               up where you recede.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" xml:id="Doyleys">
            <head type="main"><hi rend="caps">Doyleys.</hi></head>
            <ab type="materials"><hi rend="italics">Two needles are required.</hi></ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse"><ref target="CastOn">Cast on</ref> 86 stitches, knit <ref
                  target="PlainRow">a row of two stitches plain</ref>, and two <ref target="Rib"
                  >ribbed</ref>. In the 2nd <ref target="Row">row</ref>, <ref target="Rib">rib</ref>
               the stitches that were <ref target="PlainRow">plain</ref> in the first <ref
                  target="Row">row</ref>, and knit <ref target="PlainRow">plain</ref> those that
               were <ref target="Rib">ribbed</ref>. In the 3rd <ref target="Row">row</ref>, <ref
                  target="Rib">rib</ref> the stitches that were <ref target="Rib">ribbed</ref> in
               the last <ref target="Row">row</ref>, and knit <ref target="PlainRow">plain</ref>
               those that were knitted <ref target="PlainRow">plain</ref>. 4th <ref target="Row"
                  >row</ref>, <ref target="Rib">rib</ref> the <ref target="PlainRow">plain</ref>
               stitches and knit the <ref target="Rib">ribbed</ref> ones. Repeat these four <ref
                  target="Row">rows</ref> five times.</ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">2nd pattern in the doyley, continue the first pattern for 10
               stitches, then knit, putting the cotton twice round the needle, every stitch, until
               you have only 10 left on the needle, knit them like the 10 first; these 10 stitches
               on each side form the border, and are always the same pattern; knit the next three
                  <ref target="PlainRow">rows plain</ref>, except the border; then repeat the first
                  <ref target="Row">row</ref> of this pattern; knit 3 <ref target="Row">rows</ref>;
               the border as before. 3rd <ref target="Row">row</ref>, begin with the cotton forward,
               knit two in one, <ref target="BringTheThreadForward">bring the cotton forward</ref>,
               etc., until you come to the border again; knit 3 <ref target="PlainRow">plain
                  rows</ref>, repeat those 4 <ref target="Row">rows</ref> 3 times, and begin the 2nd
               pattern again; continue these two patterns alternatively, until the doyley is nearly
               square, then finish with the same width of border as at the top.</ab>
            <ab type="materials">For this knitting, your cotton and needles should be rather
               fine.</ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">N.B. Many of the patterns given as purse stitches are very
               pretty for doyleys, with a border either of <ref target="PlainRow">plain</ref> or
               fancy knitting.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" xml:id="SaveAllBag">
            <head type="main"><hi rend="caps">Save All Bag.</hi></head>
            <ab type="materials"><hi rend="italics">Four coarse needles are required. This bag is so
                  called, because it may be made with odds and ends of netting silk, or all of one
                  color, at pleasure.</hi></ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse"><ref target="CastOn">Cast</ref> 40 stitches on each of 3
               needles; knit one <ref target="PlainRow">plain</ref>
               <ref target="Round">round</ref>; then knit one stitch, <ref
                  target="BringTheThreadForward">bring the silk forward</ref>, knit a stitch, thus
               forming a <ref target="LoopStitch">loop-stitch</ref> in addition to the original
               number, knit a stitch, <ref target="BringTheThreadForward">bring the silk
                  forward</ref>, and continue as before for the whole <ref target="Round"
                  >round</ref>. Next <ref target="Round">round</ref>, knit a stitch, <ref
                  target="BringTheThreadForward">bring the silk forward</ref>, knit two stitches
               (the loop and that next it) together; knit a stitch, <ref
                  target="BringTheThreadForward">bring the silk forward</ref>, and knit two
               together, until the bag is long enough.</ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">This bag looks well with a clasp, and a tassel at the
               bottom.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" xml:id="MossStitch">
            <head type="main"><hi rend="caps">Moss Stitch, To Make A Thick Bag.</hi></head>
            <ab type="materials"><hi rend="italics">Two needles are required.</hi></ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">Moss-stitch can be done with any even number of stitches.
               Take off the first stitch, pass the cotton forward, <ref target="Rib">rib</ref> a
               stitch, pass the cotton back, and knit one <ref target="PlainRow">plain</ref>, pass
               it forward, <ref target="Rib">rib</ref> a stitch, pass it back, and so on to the end
               of the <ref target="Row">row</ref>. In the second <ref target="Row">row</ref>, <ref
                  target="Rib">rib</ref> and knit alternate stitches. It may be knitted either with
               four or two needles.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" xml:id="DoubleKnitting">
            <head type="main"><hi rend="caps">Double Knitting.</hi></head>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">For doubling knitting, you may <ref target="CastOn">cast
                  on</ref> any even number of stitches; <ref target="BringTheThreadForward">bring
                  the thread forward</ref>, <ref target="SlipOrPassAStitch">slip a stitch</ref>,
               pass the thread back, knit a stitch, putting the thread twice round the needle. This
               repeated, forms the pattern.</ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">You will find, in the next row, you take off the knitted
               stitch. Should you prefer beginning with a knitted stitch, pass the thread but once
               round the needle in every first stitch, as this will form a firmer edge.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" xml:id="DoubleBlanket">
            <head type="main"><hi rend="caps">Double Blanket.</hi></head>
            <ab type="materials"><hi rend="italics">This blanket is very light and warm. Two large
                  wooden pins are required. It takes 2 pounds and a half of lamb's-wool to make one
                  4 feet wide and 5 long.</hi></ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">Put on 250 stitches, knit 10 <ref target="PlainRow">simple
                  rows</ref>; then begin and end each <ref target="Row">row</ref> with 6 stitches in
                  <ref target="PlainRow">plain knitting</ref>; the rest of the <ref target="Row"
                  >row</ref> is double knitting, putting the wool twice round the pin. The border is
               frequently made of a different color from the middle; in this case, the two balls of
               wool are passed once round each other, so as to loop the wool every time.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" xml:id="AGentlemansComforter">
            <head type="main"><hi rend="caps">A Gentleman's Comforter.</hi></head>
            <head type="sub"><hi rend="caps">Double Knitting</hi></head>
            <ab type="materials"><hi rend="italics">Two coarse steel needles are necessary, and 5
                  skeins of fine knitting yarn.</hi></ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse"><ref target="CastOn">Cast on</ref> 72 stitches; knit the
               first stitch, putting the yarn only once round your needle, <ref
                  target="BringTheThreadForward">bring the yarn forward</ref>, <ref
                  target="SlipOrPassAStitch">slip a stitch</ref>, pass the yarn back again, knit a
               stitch, passing the yarn twice round the needle; continue knitting in double knitting
               with the yarn twice round the needle, until the comforter is long enough. In the last
                  <ref target="Row">row</ref>, before you <ref target="CastOff">cast off</ref>, the
               yarn should be passed round the needle only once. Small comforters, to cover the
               chest in riding, are made in the same way.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" xml:id="AComfortableComforter">
            <head type="main"><hi rend="caps">A Comfortable Comforter.</hi></head>
            <ab type="InstructionProse"><ref target="CastOn">Cast on</ref> 50 stitches; knit 44
               turns <ref target="PlainRow">plain knitting</ref>, decrease one stitch in five, until
               you have only 40 in the <ref target="Row">row</ref>; knit 6 <ref target="ATurn"
                  >turns</ref>, then decrease again 10 stitches in the <ref target="Row">row</ref>;
               knit 18 <ref target="ATurn">turns</ref>, increase 10 stitches in the <ref
                  target="Row">row</ref>; knit 6 <ref target="ATurn">turns</ref>, increase 10
               stitches in the <ref target="Row">row</ref>; knit 44 <ref target="ATurn">turns</ref>,
               and <ref target="CastOff">cast off</ref>.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" xml:id="DoubleKnittedShawl">
            <head type="main"><hi rend="caps">Double Knitted Shawl.</hi></head>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">Begin with one stitch; increase a stitch every other <ref
                  target="Row">row</ref>, which will make one side slant; knit <ref
                  target="PlainRow">plain knitting</ref> until you have 9 stitches, 7 of which are
               for the border; these are knitted in <ref target="PlainRow">plain knitting</ref>
               throughout; with the other stitches begin double knitting, as before. When your shawl
               is nearly large enough, knit a few <ref target="Row">rows</ref> of <ref
                  target="PlainRow">plain knitting</ref>, to correspond with the border on the other
               side.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" xml:id="DoubleKnittedShawlWithColoredBorder">
            <head type="main"><hi rend="caps">Double Knitted Shawl, With Colored Border.</hi></head>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">This shawl is knitted in precisely the same way as the one
               above, except that you begin with the color you mean to have for the border: when you
               have 7 stitches, you must <ref target="SlipOrPassAStitch">pass</ref> the white round
               it and knit in the end. Every time you come to the border, you <ref
                  target="SlipOrPassAStitch">pass</ref> the colored and white lamb's-wool round each
               other, thus looping them together.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" xml:id="PincushionCoverLeafPattern">
            <head type="main"><hi rend="caps">Pincushion Cover.</hi></head>
            <head type="sub"><hi rend="caps">Leaf Pattern</hi></head>
            <ab type="materials"><hi rend="italics">This pattern is knitted with 4 needles, No. 18.</hi></ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse"><ref target="CastOn">Cast</ref> 45 stitches on each of 3
               needles (15 being required for each stripe). First <ref target="Round">round</ref>,
               begin with the cotton forward, purl 2 stitches, pass the cotton back, knit one,
               taking it at the back, purl 2, pass the cotton back, <ref target="SlipOrPassAStitch"
                  >slip one stitch</ref>, knit one, pull the slipped stitch over the knitted one;
               knit 6, <ref target="BringTheThreadForward">bring the cotton forward</ref>, knit one,
               this increases two <ref target="LoopStitch">loop-stitches</ref>; repeat this all
               around. You will find you have increased 1 stitch in every 15.</ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">2nd round; begin with the cotton forward, purl 2 stitches,
               knit one, taking it at the back, purl 2, <ref target="SlipOrPassAStitch">slip</ref>
               one, knit one, pull the slipped stitch over the knitted one, <ref target="PlainRow"
                  >knit plain</ref> until you come to the next purl stitches, and continue as
               before. In this, and every alternate round, no <ref target="LoopStitch"
                  >loop-stitches</ref> are to be made, but the purled stripes and the decrease to be
               done as before, which will reduce the stitches to the original number.</ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">Knit these <ref target="Round">rounds</ref> alternately,
               making the 2 holes (which occur in every alternate <ref target="Round">round</ref>)
               one stitch sooner each time, i.e., knitting 5, then 4, then 3, then 2, then 1,
               instead of six stitches, as mentioned in the first <ref target="Round">round</ref>.
               You will then have six <ref target="Row">rows</ref> of holes, which completes the
               leaf, and you will find the holes brought to the side of the stripe opposite to that
               on which they began; you must then begin again as at first.</ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">Nine <ref target="Round">rounds</ref> of leaves complete a
               pincushion.</ab>
         </div>

         <div type="notesinprogress">
            <p><ref type="note" target="#n4">This work will wash and look equal to new, by mixing a
                  little ox-gall with a little curd soap lather, and washing it in the ordinary way,
                  spreading it out to dry, and turning it frequently.</ref></p>
            <p><ref type="note" target="#n5">Then, with shaded wool, work a row of double L stitches
                  all round.</ref></p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="endnotes">
            <note xml:id="n1" source="#HowToCastOn">A current, common way for beginners to cast on
               uses the thumb method. Knitters start by creating a loop out of a single thread and
               pulling the loose end of the yarn through the loop to create a slip knot. Then, the
               slip knot is placed onto the needle and the loose yarn is brought around the thumb to
               create a loop that the needle slides through. Holding the needle with the left hand,
               the right hand holds the yarn attached to the yarn ball, wraps it around the needle
               and pulls down, slides the loop on the left thumb over and onto the needle, and the
               yarn tail is pulled down to create the first stitch.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2" source="#NeedleSizes">Yarn weight must also be taken into account when
               choosing a needle. The finer/thinner the yarn being used, the smaller the needle
               should be. In the common range today, a very thin 2-ply yarn should be paired with a
               US size 0-2 needle, a medium-thick 8-ply yarn should be paired with a US size 3-6,
               and the thickest 14-ply yarn should be paired with a US size 11-17 needle.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3" source="#SkeinDefinition">A common term utilized by those who practice
               knitting, a skein is a loosely coiled length of length of yarn, thread, or other
               material wound onto a reel.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4" source="#WashingTechnique">Often, hand knitted works require a special
               washing practice. Contemporary washing practices require you to look at the yarn
               label for any specific instructions pertaining to washing. Usually, you use a mild
               detergent mixed with warm water in a basin or sink, submerge the yarn in the soapy
               water and agitate it to loosen any dirt or residue, rinsing thoroughly to remove any
               soapy residue, gently squeezing the item to remove excess water, and laying it on a
               clean towel or drying rack to air dry. You can block the yarn to shape it and even
               out any inconsistencies in texture or gauge during the drying step.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5" source="#ShadedWoolDefinition">Shaded wool refers to yarn that has
               been dyed in multiple colors creating a gradient or variegated effect giving your
               work a visually appealing color variation.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="ShadedWoolDefinition" type="webpage"><title>"Berlin Wool: Fine Fiber
                     from an Innovative Age."</title><publisher><hi rend="italics">
                     PieceWork</hi></publisher>, <ref
                     target="https://pieceworkmagazine.com/berlin-wool-fine-fiber-from-an-innovative-age/"
                     >https://pieceworkmagazine.com/berlin-wool-fine-fiber-from-an-innovative-age/</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="HowToCastOn" type="webpage"><title>"How To Cast On for Total
                     Beginners."</title><publisher><hi rend="italics"> Sheep and
                     Stitch</hi></publisher>, <date>17 Dec 2018</date>, <ref
                     target="sheepandstitch.com/library/long-tail-cast-on-for-beginners/"
                     >sheepandstitch.com/library/long-tail-cast-on-for-beginners/</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="WashingTechnique" type="webpage"><title>"How To Wash Hand-Knitted
                     Items."</title><publisher><hi rend="italics"> In The Wash</hi></publisher>,
                     <date>08 June 2023</date>, <ref
                     target="https://inthewash.co.uk/laundry-and-ironing/how-to-wash-hand-knitted-items/#:~:text=Hand-Washing%20Knitwear%20Step-By-Step%201%20Step%201%3A%20Fill%20a,...%206%20Step%206%3A%20Remove%20excess%20water%20"
                     >https://inthewash.co.uk/laundry-and-ironing/how-to-wash-hand-knitted-items/#:~:text=Hand-Washing%20Knitwear%20Step-By-Step%201%20Step%201%3A%20Fill%20a,...%206%20Step%206%3A%20Remove%20excess%20water%20</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="NeedleSizes" type="webpage"><title>"Knitting Needle Sizes for
                     Yarn."</title><publisher><hi rend="italics"> Yarn Worx</hi></publisher>,
                     <date>11 June 2021</date>, <ref
                     target="www.yarnworx.com/blogs/yarn-guides/knitting-needle-sizes-for-yarn"
                     >www.yarnworx.com/blogs/yarn-guides/knitting-needle-sizes-for-yarn</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="SkeinDefinition" type="webpage"><title>"Skein."</title><publisher><hi
                        rend="italics"> Merriam-Webster</hi></publisher>, <ref
                     target="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/skein"
                     >https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/skein</ref>.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
