<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Ladies' Handbook of Fancy and Ornamental Work</title>
            <author>Miss Florence Hartley</author>
            <editor>Riley Hull</editor>
            <editor>Tara Boyd</editor>
            <editor>Trisha Binwade</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This text in particular is interesting because of the connectivity it fosters between
               the past and the present, specifically in regards to the subject of “fancy and
               ornamental” work. In that sense, our edition hopes to offer a text that highlights
               various methods of ornamental work that were utilized in the past, thus allowing us
               to preserve these traditional practices, introduce a new audience of people to them,
               and invite comparison between the methods of the past and those of the present day.
               Within our class at the University of Washington, we first chose a specific section
               of the text to focus on, ultimately ending up choosing the knitting section because
               its relatively concise nature meant we would be able to complete an entire section.
               We then transcribed the text into plain text digital files and created a project
               schema to guide our TEI markup. We plan to encode and markup our text and create some
               sort of digital edition interface to help facilitate our goals and bring our text to
               a modern audience.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This text is found in the Costume and Textile Collections within the University of
               Washington Special Collections Library. It is a medium-sized, hard-bound text in a
               dark brown binding. <bibl>
                  <title>The Ladies' Handbook of Fancy and Ornamental Work</title>
                  <author>Miss Florence Hartley</author>
                  <publisher>John E. Potter &amp; Company</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>617 Samson Street, Philadelphia PA</pubPlace>
                  <date>1859</date>
                  <idno type="callNumber">TT 750 H37</idno>
               </bibl>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>There were very minimal spelling modernizations, as most of the text consisted of
                  words that fit in with modern vernacular and would be understandable to a modern
                  audience.</p>
            </normalization>
            <correction>
               <p>There were very minimal grammar and spelling errors, which were ultimately
                  adjusted by the editors based on the text’s established patterns and grammatical
                  structure.</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" rend="roman">
      <front>
         <div type="editorial_intro">
            <p>Published in 1859 by John E. Potter &amp; Company, The Ladies’ Handbook of Fancy and
               Ornamental Work is an instructional text written by Miss Florence Hartley, who
               ensures her readers that the material within her pages was “compiled from the best
               authorities.” This historical handbook is centered around traditionally-feminine
               crafts and skills, such as sewing, baking, crocheting, embroidery, and – as this
               editorial edition specifically focuses on – knitting. Given that these types of texts
               are not as commonplace in today’s society or literary sphere, Hartley’s text provides
               an interesting look at the culture and practices of the past.</p>
            <p>Specifically focusing our efforts on Hartley’s instructions for knitting, this
               specific edition offers an overview of numerous knitting-based crafts exactly as they
               were done in the late nineteenth century. We hope to bring visibility to these
               traditional practices by presenting them to a new audience of people, ultimately
               helping to preserve the knowledge and culture of past generations. For those that
               have no prior experience with knitting, this text may serve as a captivating
               introduction to the practice itself, especially in the context of its history. On the
               other hand, for readers that do have experience with knitting, this edition may
               provide a basis for intriguing comparisons between the methods of the past and those
               of the present day.</p>
            <p>For this edition, there were very minor changes made from the source text,
               specifically in terms of transcription. While a majority of Hartley’s text is indeed
               presentable to a modern audience, there were a small number of spelling and grammar
               alterations made to best ensure that the instructions of this edition were as clear
               as possible.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="glossary" xml:id="ExplanationOfTerms">
            <head type="main" rend="caps">Explanation of Terms Used in Knitting, and Hints on
               Knitting.</head>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="CastOn">
               <ref type="note" target="#n1"><term><hi rend="italics">To cast on-</hi></term>
               <gloss>The first interlacement of the cotton on the needle.</gloss></ref></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="CastOff">
               <term><hi rend="italics">To cast off-</hi></term>
               <gloss>to knit two stitches, and to pass over the second, and so on to the last
                  stich, which is to be secured by drawing the thread through.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="CastOver">
               <term><hi rend="italics">To cast over-</hi></term>
               <gloss>to bring the cotton forward round the needle.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="Narrow">
               <term><hi rend="italics">To Narrow-</hi></term>
               <gloss>to lessen by bringing two stitches together.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="Seam">
               <term><hi rend="italics">To seam-</hi></term>
               <gloss>to knit a stitch with the cotton before the needle.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="Widen">
               <term><hi rend="italics">To widen-</hi></term>
               <gloss>to increase by making a stitch, bringing the cotton round the needle, and
                  knitting the same when it occurs.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="ATurn">
               <term><hi rend="italics">A turn-</hi></term>
               <gloss>two rows in the same stitch, backwards and forwards.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="ToTurn">
               <term><hi rend="italics">To turn-</hi></term>
               <gloss>to change the stitch.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="Row">
               <term><hi rend="italics">A row-</hi></term>
               <gloss>the stitches from one end of the needle to the other.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="Round">
               <term><hi rend="italics">A round-</hi></term>
               <gloss>a row when the stitches are on two, three, or more needles.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="PlainRow">
               <term><hi rend="italics">A plain row-</hi></term>
               <gloss>that composed of simple knitting.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="PearlARow">
               <term><hi rend="italics">To pearl a row-</hi></term>
               <gloss>to knit with the cotton before the needle.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="Rib">
               <term><hi rend="italics">To rib-</hi></term>
               <gloss>to work alternate rows of plain and pearl knitting.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="BringTheThreadForward">
               <term><hi rend="italics">To bring the thread forward-</hi></term>
               <gloss>to bring the cotton forward so as to make an open stitch.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="LoopStitch">
               <term><hi rend="italics">A loop stitch-</hi></term>
               <gloss>made by bringing the cotton before the needle, which in knitting the
                  succeeding stitch, will again take its own place.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="SlipOrPassAStitch">
               <term><hi rend="italics">To slip or pass a stitch-</hi></term>
               <gloss>to change it from one needle to the other without knitting it.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="FastenOn">
               <term><hi rend="italics">To fasten on-</hi></term>
               <gloss>the best way is to place the ends contrariwise, and knit a few stitches with both together.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="StitchType" xml:id="TakeUnder">
               <term><hi rend="italics">To take under-</hi></term>
               <gloss>to pass the cotton from one needle to the other without changing its position.</gloss></ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse"><hi rend="italics"><ref target="#PearlARow">Pearl</ref>, <ref target="#Seam"
                  >seam</ref>,</hi> and <hi rend="italics"><ref target="#Rib"
                     >rib-stitch</ref></hi> are the same.</ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">Be careful in knitting to have the cotton or wool of a
               moderate tension-not too lose, nor too tight.</ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">When it is requisite to <ref type="StitchType"
               target="#CastOff">cast off</ref>, and continue a row on a separate needle, run a
               coarse thread through the <ref target="#CastOff">cast off</ref>
               stitches, as they are easily taken up when required.</ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">It is a good plan to have children taught to knit, boys as
               well as girls, and to have them learn to knit without looking at their work. Old
               ladies who have lost their sight often knit very beautifully, and as a general rule
               we find that they began very young, and learned to knit without giving their work
               steady attention. The blind in all Asylums are beautiful knitters, and in case of any
               accident to the eyesight it would be a great resource, as well as when deprived of
               sight by old age.</ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse"><ref type="note" target="#n2">Knitting needles vary in size
               and length. For small articles the short ones are most convenient. They are made
               of steel, bone, ivory, or wood, and you purchase such sizes as agrees with the
               work you have to do. In all large trimming stores where this kind of material is
               kept, they will tell you the best sizes, if you are ignorant yourself.</ref></ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">Here is a cut of a gauge for measuring needles for knitting
               and netting meshes, and for crochet needles.</ab>
            <ab type="figure">
               <ref target="ExplanationOfTerms">
                  <figure type="ToolImage">
                     <graphic url="WireGauge.jpg"/>
                     <figDesc>A side-view of a metal gauge tool, resembling a spoked wheel with a
                        hollow center and several spokes labeled with numbers 1-19.</figDesc>
                     <p rend="bottom"><hi rend="caps">Wire Gauge</hi></p>
                  </figure>
               </ref>
            </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="section" xml:id="OperaCap">
            <head type="main" rend="caps">Opera Cap</head>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">These caps look the prettiest when of two colors. The
               material is single Berlin wool. Scarlet and white contrast extremely well. To
               commence, <ref target="#CastOn">cast on</ref> seventy-two loops on the smallest sized
               ivory needles, with the scarlet wool; knit and purl until you have five rows knitted
               on the right side; this forms one stripe. Take the white wool and repeat this, only
               reversing the stripe, continue this process until you have nine stripes, purled and
               knitted alternately; five of the scarlet, four of the white. Before <ref
                  target="#CastOff">casting off</ref> prepare as follows: take the first loop upon
               your needle, drop the second, take the third, and so on to the end of the row, taking
               care to avoid any mistake, which would be the ruin of the whole. The first and last
               loops must of course be preserved. You will now have just half the original number of
               loops upon your needle. <ref target="#CastOff">Cast off</ref>, leaving the wool very
               loose. Afterwards assit the dropped loops to run down. This makes a very simple but
               very pretty stitch in knitting.</ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">The fringe is now to be added, which is done by <ref
               target="#LoopStitch">looping</ref> lengths of wool through the stitches just <ref
                  target="#CastOff">cast off</ref>, and slipping the ends through the loop, so as to
               form a knot.</ab>
            <ab type="InstructionProse">The ends of the knitted pieces are now to be gathered up
               with a needle, the ribbon string attached, a pretty rosette of the same sewed on over
               the gathering up, and this useful little article is completed.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="notesinprogress">
         <p><ref type="note" target="#n3">Four fine needles, nearly 3 skeins of netting silk, and
            one sting of gold beads are required.</ref></p>
         <p><ref type="note" target="#n4">This work will wash and look equal to new, by mixing a
            little ox-gall with a little curd soap lather, and washing it in the ordinary way,
            spreading it out to dry, and turning it frequently.</ref></p>
         <p><ref type="note" target="#n5">Then, with shaded wool, work a row of double L stitches
            all round.</ref></p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="endnotes">
            <note xml:id="n1" source="#HowToCastOn">A current, common way for
               beginners to cast on uses the thumb method. Knitters start by creating a loop out
               of a single thread and pulling the loose end of the yarn through the loop to
               create a slip knot. Then, the slip knot is placed onto the needle and the loose
               yarn is brought around the thumb to create a loop that the needle slides through.
               Holding the needle with the left hand, the right hand holds the yarn attached to
               the yarn ball, wraps it around the needle and pulls down, slides the loop on the
               left thumb over and onto the needle, and the yarn tail is pulled down to create
               the first stitch.</note>
            <note xml:id="n2" source="#NeedleSizes">Yarn weight must also be
               taken into account when choosing a needle. The finer/thinner the yarn being used,
               the smaller the needle should be. In the common range today, a very thin 2-ply
               yarn should be paired with a US size 0-2 needle, a medium-thick 8-ply yarn should
               be paired with a US size 3-6, and the thickest 14-ply yarn should be paired with a
               US size 11-17 needle.</note>
            <note xml:id="n3" source="#SkeinDefinition">A common term utilized by
               those who practice knitting, a skein is a loosely coiled length of length of yarn,
               thread, or other material wound onto a reel.</note>
            <note xml:id="n4" source="#WashingTechnique">Often, hand knitted
               works require a special washing practice. Contemporary washing practices require
               you to look at the yarn label for any specific instructions pertaining to washing.
               Usually, you use a mild detergent mixed with warm water in a basin or sink,
               submerge the yarn in the soapy water and agitate it to loosen any dirt or residue,
               rinsing thoroughly to remove any soapy residue, gently squeezing the item to
               remove excess water, and laying it on a clean towel or drying rack to air dry. You
               can block the yarn to shape it and even out any inconsistencies in texture or
               gauge during the drying step.</note>
            <note xml:id="n5" source="#ShadedWoolDefinition">Shaded wool refers to
               yarn that has been dyed in multiple colors creating a gradient or variegated
               effect giving your work a visually appealing color variation.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="ShadedWoolDefinition" type="webpage"><title>"Berlin Wool: Fine Fiber
                  from an Innovative Age."</title><publisher><hi rend="italics"
                     > PieceWork</hi></publisher>, <ref
                        target="https://pieceworkmagazine.com/berlin-wool-fine-fiber-from-an-innovative-age/"
                        >https://pieceworkmagazine.com/berlin-wool-fine-fiber-from-an-innovative-age/</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="HowToCastOn" type="webpage"><title>"How To Cast On for Total
                  Beginners."</title><publisher><hi rend="italics"> Sheep and
                     Stitch</hi></publisher>, <date>17 Dec 2018</date>, <ref
                        target="sheepandstitch.com/library/long-tail-cast-on-for-beginners/"
                        >sheepandstitch.com/library/long-tail-cast-on-for-beginners/</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="WashingTechnique" type="webpage"><title>"How To Wash Hand-Knitted
                  Items."</title><publisher><hi rend="italics"> In The
                     Wash</hi></publisher>, <date>08 June 2023</date>, <ref target="https://inthewash.co.uk/laundry-and-ironing/how-to-wash-hand-knitted-items/#:~:text=Hand-Washing%20Knitwear%20Step-By-Step%201%20Step%201%3A%20Fill%20a,...%206%20Step%206%3A%20Remove%20excess%20water%20">https://inthewash.co.uk/laundry-and-ironing/how-to-wash-hand-knitted-items/#:~:text=Hand-Washing%20Knitwear%20Step-By-Step%201%20Step%201%3A%20Fill%20a,...%206%20Step%206%3A%20Remove%20excess%20water%20</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="NeedleSizes" type="webpage"><title>"Knitting Needle Sizes for
                  Yarn."</title><publisher><hi rend="italics"> Yarn Worx</hi></publisher>, <date>11
                     June 2021</date>, <ref
                        target="www.yarnworx.com/blogs/yarn-guides/knitting-needle-sizes-for-yarn"
                        >www.yarnworx.com/blogs/yarn-guides/knitting-needle-sizes-for-yarn</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="SkeinDefinition" type="webpage"><title>"Skein."</title><publisher><hi
                  rend="italics"> Merriam-Webster</hi></publisher>, <ref
                     target="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/skein"
                     >https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/skein</ref>.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>

