<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="teibp.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Poems</title>
            <author>Mary Baker Eddy</author>
            <editor>Emma Hong</editor>
            <editor>Annie Melnick</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This transcription of "Poems" was created as our final project submission for Professor Turnovsky's TXTDS 404 course, "Texts, Publics and Publication" at the University of Washington. Poems was chosen amongst various texts provided by the UW Libraries' Special Collections department. Our intention with this transcription was to preserve the content of Eddy's poetry, and provide through our poem selections and annotations a curated understanding of Eddy's beliefs and life. The literary content of the poems and historical period of time they were written in were a central focus in our transcription efforts. </p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Poems is a collection of poems written by Mary Baker Eddy throughout her lifetime. Poems was published in 1910 by the First Church of Christ, Scientist, in Boston, Massachusetts.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="editorial_intro">
            <p>Mary Baker Eddy’s "Poems" is a collection of poetry written by Eddy during the course of her life, dated from childhood through her last years. As editors, we found this text notable because we wanted to contextualize Eddy’s poems by researching additional historical and biographical information, therefore deriving and providing more meaning from her work. An aspect of note is that there are varying levels of context provided for each poem. Only a portion of Eddy’s poems have footnotes listing the year and location the work was written. With the help of additional biographical information, we are able to piece together additional context. But many of the poems do not have that level of specificity. Some only list the year or time period in which it was written; many do not provide footnotes at all. This gives us a significant challenge when it comes to contextualizing Eddy’s poems.</p>
            <p>The goal of our project is twofold. The first is to attempt to contextualize some of Eddy’s poems based on clues, seeing if we could utilize stylistic and thematic elements to provide our best guess as to when and where the poem was written. In addition, for the poems with identifying information, we are going to provide annotations with facts about Eddy’s life during the time it was written. Our second goal is to share which poems stood out to us. Our edition only contains ten poems, and we picked our favorites to feature. This could give insight as to which of Eddy’s poems continue to be impactive in the twenty-first century.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="preface">
            <head><hi rend="uppercase">Preface</hi></head>
               <p>The poems garnered up in this little volume were written at different periods in the life of the author, dating from her early girlhood up to recent years. They were not written with a view of making a book, each poem being the spontaneous outpouring of a deeply poetic nature and called forth by some experience that claimed her attention.</p>
               <p>The "Old Man of the Mountain," for instance, was written while the author was contemplating this lofty New Hampshire crag, whose rugged outlines resemble the profile of a human face. Inspired by the grandeur of this masterpiece of nature's handiwork, and looking "up through nature, unto nature's God," the poem began to take form in her thought, and alighting from her carriage, she seated herself by the roadside and began to write. Some tourists who were passing, and who made her acquaintance, asked her what she was writing, and she replied by reading the poem to them. They were so pleased with it that each requested a copy, which was subsequently mailed to them. Similar requests continued to reach the author for years afterward, until the poem finally found its way into print, appearing, together with "The Valley Cemetery," in a book "Gems for You," published in Manchester, N. H., in 1850, and again in Boston, in 1856.</p>
               <p>The poem on the "Dedication of a Temperance Hall," in Lynn, Mass., in 1866, was written for that occasion, and was sung by the audience as a dedicatory hymn. "The Liberty Bells" appeared in a Lynn, Mass., newspaper, under the date of February 3, 1865. A note from the author, which was published with the poem, read as follows:</p>       
               <p>"Mr. Editor:—In 1835 a mob in Boston (although Boston has since been the pioneer of anti-slavery) dispersed a meeting of the Female Anti-Slavery Society, and assailed the person of William Lloyd Garrison with such fury that the city authorities could protect him nowhere but in the walls of a jail. To-day, by order of Governor Andrew, the bells are ringing to celebrate the passing of a resolution in Congress prohibiting slavery in the United States."</p>           
               <p>All of the author's best-known hymns are included in this collection, as well as many poems written in girlhood and during the years she resided in Lynn, Mass., and which appeared in various publications of that day. Among her earliest poems are "Upward," "Resolutions for the Day," "Autumn" (written in a maple grove), "Alphabet and Bayonet," and "The Country-Seat" (written while visiting a family friend in the beautiful suburbs of Boston); yet, even these are characterized by the same lofty trend of thought that reached its fulness in her later productions.</p>        
               <p>In May, 1910, Mrs. Eddy requested her publisher to prepare a few bound volumes of her poems, for private distribution. When this became known to her friends, they urged her to allow a popular edition to be issued, to which she assented. With grateful acknowledgment, therefore, of this permission, this little volume is presented to the public, in the hope that these gems of purest thought from this spiritually-minded author will prove a joy to the heavy laden and a balm to the weary heart.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" n="1">
            <head><hi rend="uppercase">Autumn</hi></head>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>Quickly earth's jewels disappear;</l>
               <l><ref target="#Sanbornton">The turf</ref>, whereon <ref target="#mary_baker_eddy">I</ref> tread,</l>
               <l>Ere autumn blanch another year,</l>
               <l>May rest above my head.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>Touched by the finger of decay</l>
               <l>Is every earthly love;</l>
               <l>For joy, to shun my weary way,</l>
               <l>Is registered above.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>The languid brooklets yield their sighs,</l>
               <l>A requiem o'er the tomb</l>
               <l>Of sunny days and cloudless skies,</l>
               <l>Enhancing autumn's gloom. </l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>The wild winds mutter, howl, and moan,</l>
               <l>To scare my woodland walk</l>
               <l>And frightened fancy flees, to roam</l>
               <l>Where ghosts and goblins stalk.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>The cricket's sharp, discordant scream</l>
               <l>Fills mortal sense with dread;</l>
               <l>More sorrowful it scarce could seem;</l>
               <l>It voices beauty fled.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>Yet here, upon this faded sod,—</l>
               <l>O happy hours and fleet,—</l>
               <l>When songsters' matin hymns to God</l>
               <l>Are poured in strains so sweet,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>My heart unbidden joins rehearse,</l>
               <l>I hope it's better made,</l>
               <l>When mingling with the universe,</l>
               <l>Beneath the maple's shade.</l>
            </lg>
            <note place="footnote">
               Written in girlhood, <ref target="#Sanbornton">in a maple grove.</ref>
            </note>      
         </div>
         <div type="poem" n="2">
            <head><hi rend="uppercase">Spring</hi></head>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>Come to <ref target="#Sanbornton">thy bowers</ref>, sweet spring,</l>
               <l>And paint the gray, stark trees,</l>
               <l>The bud, the leaf and wing—</l>
               <l>Bring with thee brush and breeze.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>And soft thy shading lay</l>
               <l>On vale and woodland deep;</l>
               <l>With sunshine's lovely ray</l>
               <l>Light o'er the rugged steep.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>More softly warm and weave</l>
               <l>The patient, timid grass,</l>
               <l>Till heard at silvery eve</l>
               <l>Poor robin's lonely mass.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>Bid faithful swallows come</l>
               <l>And build their cozy nests,</l>
               <l>Where wind nor storm can numb</l>
               <l>Their downy little breasts.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>Come at the sad heart's call,</l>
               <l>To empty summer bowers,</l>
               <l>Where still and dead are all</l>
               <l>The vernal songs and flowers.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>It may be months or years</l>
               <l>Since joyous spring was there.</l>
               <l>O come to clouds and tears</l>
               <l>With light and song and prayer!</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" n="3">
            <head><hi rend="uppercase">O For Thy Wings, Sweet Bird!</hi></head>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>O for thy wings, sweet bird!</l>
               <l>And soul of melody by being blest—</l>
               <l>Like thee, <ref target="#mary_baker_eddy">my</ref> voice had stirred</l>
               <l>Some dear remembrance in a weary breast.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>But whither wouldst thou rove,</l>
               <l>Bird of the airy wing, and fold thy plumes?</l>
               <l>In what dark leafy grove</l>
               <l>Wouldst chant thy vespers 'mid rich glooms?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>Or sing thy love-lorn note—</l>
               <l>In deeper solitude, where nymph or saint</l>
               <l>Has wooed some mystic spot,</l>
               <l>Divinely desolate the shrine to paint?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>Yet wherefore ask thy doom?</l>
               <l>Blessed compared with me thou art—</l>
               <l>Unto thy greenwood home</l>
               <l>Bearing no bitter memory at heart;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>Wearing no earthly chain,</l>
               <l>Thou canst in azure bright soar far above;</l>
               <l>Nor pinest thou in vain</l>
               <l>O'er joys departed, unforgotten love.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>O take me to thy bower!</l>
               <l>Beguile the lagging hours of weariness</l>
               <l>With strain which hath strange power</l>
               <l>To make me love thee as I love life less!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>From mortal consciousness</l>
               <l>Which binds to earth—infirmity of woe!</l>
               <l>Or pining tenderness—</l>
               <l>Whose streams will never dry or cease to flow;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>An aching, voiceless void,</l>
               <l>Hushed in the heart whereunto none reply,</l>
               <l>And in the cringing crowd</l>
               <l>Companionless! Bird, bear me through the sky!</l>
            </lg>
            <note place="footnote">
               Written more than sixty years ago for the <hi rend="italic">New Hampshire Patriot.</hi>
            </note>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" n="4">
            <head><hi rend="uppercase">Meeting Of My Departed Mother And Husband</hi></head>
            <lg type="stanza" rhyme="aabccb">
               <l>Joy for thee, happy friend! thy bark is past</l>
               <l>The dangerous sea, and safely moored at last—</l>
               <l>Beyond rough foam.</l>
               <l>Soft gales celestial, in sweet music bore—</l>
               <l>Spirit emancipate for this far shore—</l>
               <l>Thee to thy home.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza" rhyme="aabccb">
               <l>"You've traveled long, and far from mortal joys,</l>
               <l>To Soul's diviner sense, that spurns such toys,</l>
               <l>Brave wrestler, lone.</l>
               <l>Now see thy ever-self; Life never fled;</l>
               <l>Man is not mortal, never of the dead:</l>
               <l>The dark unknown.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza" rhyme="aabccb">
               <l>"When hope soared high, and joy was eagle-plumed,</l>
               <l>Thy pinions drooped; the flesh was weak, and doomed</l>
               <l>To pass away.</l>
               <l>But faith triumphant round thy death-couch shed</l>
               <l>Majestic forms; and radiant glory sped</l>
               <l>The dawning day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza" rhyme="aabccb">
               <l>"Intensely grand and glorious life's sphere,—</l>
               <l>Beyond the shadow, infinite appear</l>
               <l>Life, Love divine,—</l>
               <l>Where mortal yearnings come not, sighs are stilled,</l>
               <l>And home and peace and hearts are found and filled,</l>
               <l>Thine, ever thine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza" rhyme="aabccb">
               <l>"Bearest thou no tidings from <ref target="#mary_baker_eddy">our loved on earth</ref>,</l>
               <l>The toiler tireless for Truth's new birth</l>
               <l>All-unbeguiled?</l>
               <l>Our joy is gathered from her parting sigh:</l>
               <l>This hour looks on her heart with pitying eye,—</l>
               <l>What of <ref target="#george_washington_glover_ii">my child?</ref>"</l> 
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza" rhyme="aabccb">
               <l>"When, severed by death's dream, <ref target="#abigail_baker">I</ref> woke to Life,</l>
               <l>She deemed I died, and could not know the strife</l>
               <l>At first to fill</l>
               <l>That waking with a love that steady turns</l>
               <l>To God; a hope that ever upward yearns,</l>
               <l>Bowed to His will.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza" rhyme="aabccb">
               <l>"Years had passed o'er <ref target="#george_washington_glover">thy</ref> broken household band,</l> 
               <l>When angels beckoned <ref target="#abigail_baker">me</ref> to this bright land,</l>
               <l>With thee to meet.</l>
               <l><ref target="#mary_baker_eddy">She</ref> that has wept o'er thee, kissed my cold brow,</l>
               <l>Rears the sad marble to our memory now,</l>
               <l>In lone retreat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza" rhyme="aabccb">
               <l>"By the remembrance of her loyal life,</l>
               <l>And parting prayer, I only know <ref target="#mary_baker_eddy">my wife</ref>,</l>
               <l>Thy <ref target="#george_washington_glover_ii">child</ref>, shall come—</l>
               <l>Where farewells cloud not o'er our ransomed rest—</l>
               <l>Hither to reap, with all the crowned and blest,</l>
               <l>Of bliss the sum.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza" rhyme="aabccb">
               <l>"When Love's rapt sense the heartstrings gently sweep</l>
               <l>With joy divinely fair, the high and deep,</l>
               <l>To call her home,</l>
               <l>She shall mount upward unto purer skies;</l>
               <l>We shall be waiting, in what glad surprise,</l>
               <l>Our spirits' own!"</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" n="5">
            <head><hi rend="uppercase">Dedication of a Temperance Hall</hi></head>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>Author of all divine</l>
               <l>Gifts, lofty, pure, and free,</l>
               <l>Temperance and truth in song sublime</l>
               <l>An offering bring to Thee!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>A temple, whose high dome</l>
               <l>Rose from a water-cup;</l>
               <l>And from its altar to Thy throne</l>
               <l>May we press on and up!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>And she—last at the cross,</l>
               <l>First at the tomb, who waits—</l>
               <l>Woman—will watch to cleanse from dross</l>
               <l>The cause she elevates.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>Sons of the old Bay State,</l>
               <l>Work for our glorious cause!</l>
               <l>And be your waiting hearts elate,</l>
               <l>Since temperance makes your laws.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>"Temples of Honor," all,</l>
               <l>"Social," or grand, or great,</l>
               <l>This blazoned, brilliant temperance hall</l>
               <l>To Thee we dedicate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>"Good Templars" one and all,</l>
               <l>Good "Sons," and daughters, too,</l>
               <l>We dedicate this temperance hall</l>
               <l>To God, to Truth, and you!</l>
            </lg>
            <note place="footnote">
               Lynn, Mass., <hi rend="italic">August 4, 1866.</hi>
            </note>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" n="6">
            <head><hi rend="uppercase">I'm Sitting Alone</hi></head>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="aabb">
               <l><ref target="#mary_baker_eddy">I'm </ref>sitting alone where the shadows fall</l> 
               <l>In somber groups at the vesper-call,</l>
               <l>Where tear-dews of night seek the loving rose,</l>
               <l>Her bosom to fill with mortal woes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="aabb">
               <l>I'm waiting alone for the bridal hour</l>
               <l>Of nymph and naiad from woodland bower;</l>
               <l>Till vestal pearls that on leaflets lay,</l>
               <l>Ravished with beauty the eye of day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="aabb"> 
               <l>I'm watching alone o'er the starlit glow,</l>
               <l>O'er the silv'ry moon and ocean flow;</l>
               <l>And sketching in light the heaven of my youth—</l>
               <l>Its starry hopes and its waves of truth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="aabb">
               <l>I'm dreaming alone of its changeful sky—</l>
               <l>What rainbows of rapture floated by!</l>
               <l>Of a <ref target="#abigail_baker">mother's</ref> love, that no words could speak</l> 
               <l>When parting the ringlets to kiss my cheek.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="aabb">
               <l>I'm thinking alone of a fair young bride,</l>
               <l>The light of a home of love and pride;</l>
               <l>How the glance of <ref target="#daniel_patterson">her husband</ref>'s watchful eye</l>
               <l>Turned to his star of idolatry.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="aabb">
               <l>I'm picturing alone a <ref target="#george_washington_glover_ii">glad young face</ref>,</l>
               <l>Upturned to his mother's in playful grace;</l>
               <l>And the unsealed fountains of grief and joy</l>
               <l>That gushed at the birth of that beautiful boy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="aabb">
               <l>I'm weeping alone that the vision is fled,</l> 
               <l>The leaves all faded, the fruitage shed,</l>
               <l>And wishing this earth more gifts from above,</l>
               <l>Our reason made right and hearts all love.</l>
            </lg>
            <note place="footnote">
               <ref target="#Lynn">Lynn, Mass.</ref>, <hi rend="italic">September 3, 1866.</hi>
            </note>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" n="7">
            <head><hi rend="uppercase">To Etta</hi></head>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>Fair girl, thy rosebud heart rests warm</l>
               <l>Within life's summer bowers!</l>
               <l>Nor blasts of winter's angry storm,</l>
               <l>Nor April's changeful showers,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>Its leaves have shed or bowed the stem;</l>
               <l>But gracefully it stands—</l>
               <l>A gem in beauty's diadem,</l>
               <l>Unplucked by ruthless hands.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>Thus may it ripen into bloom,</l>
               <l>Fresh as the fragrant sod,</l>
               <l>And yield its beauty and perfume</l>
               <l>An offering pure to God.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="abab">
               <l>Sweet as the poetry of heaven,</l>
               <l>Bright as her evening star,</l>
               <l>Be all thy life in music given,</l>
               <l>While beauty fills each bar.</l>
            </lg>
            <note place="footnote">
               Lynn, Mass., <hi rend="italic">December 8, 1866.</hi>
            </note>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" n="8">
            <head><hi rend="uppercase">Constancy</hi></head>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="aabb">     
               <l>When starlight blends with morning's hue,</l>
               <l><ref target="#mary_baker_eddy">I</ref> miss thee as the flower the dew!</l>
               <l>When noonday's length'ning shadows flee,</l>
               <l>I think of <ref target="#george_washington_glover">thee</ref>, I think of thee!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="aabb">
               <l>With evening, memories reappear—</l>
               <l>I watch thy chair, and wish thee here;</l>
               <l>Till sleep sets drooping fancy free</l>
               <l>To dream of thee, to dream of thee!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="aabb">
               <l>Since first we met, in weal or woe</l> 
               <l>It hath been thus; and must be so</l>
               <l>Till bursting bonds our spirits part</l>
               <l>And Love divine doth fill my heart.</l>
            </lg>
            <note place="footnote">
               Written many years ago.
            </note>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" n="9">
            <head><hi rend="uppercase">Old Man of the Mountain</hi></head>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="aabb">
               <l>Gigantic sire, unfallen still thy crest!</l>
               <l>Primeval dweller where the wild winds rest,</l>
               <l>Beyond the ken of mortal e'er to tell</l>
               <l>What power sustains thee in thy rock-bound cell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="aabb">
               <l>Or if, when first creation vast began,</l>
               <l>And far the universal fiat ran,</l>
               <l>"Let there be light"—from chaos dark set free,</l>
               <l>Ye rose, a monument of Deity,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="aabb">
               <l>Proud from yon cloud-crowned height to look henceforth</l>
               <l>On insignificance that peoples earth,</l>
               <l>Recalling oft the bitter draft which turns</l>
               <l>The mind to meditate on what it learns.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="aabb">
               <l>Stern, passionless, no soul those looks betray;</l>
               <l>Though kindred rocks, to sport at mortal clay—</l>
               <l>Much as the chisel of the sculptor's art</l>
               <l>"Plays round the head, but comes not to the heart."</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="aabb">
               <l>Ah, who can fathom thee! Ambitious man,</l>
               <l>Like a trained falcon in the Gallic van,</l>
               <l>Guided and led, can never reach to thee</l>
               <l>With all the strength of weakness—vanity!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="aabb">
               <l>Great as thou art, and paralleled by none,</l>
               <l>Admired by all, still art thou drear and lone!</l>
               <l>The moon looks down upon thine exiled height;</l>
               <l>The stars, so cold, so glitteringly bright,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="quatrain" rhyme="aabb">
               <l>On wings of morning gladly flit away,</l>
               <l>Yield to the sun's more genial, mighty ray;</l>
               <l>The white waves kiss the murmuring rill—</l>
               <l>But thy deep silence is unbroken still.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" n="10">
            <head><hi rend="uppercase">The New Century</hi></head>
            <lg type="stanza" rhyme="aabbccddee">
               <l>Thou God-crowned, patient century,</l>
               <l>Thine hour hath come! Eternity</l>
               <l>Draws nigh—and, beckoning from above,</l>
               <l>One hundred years, aflame with Love,</l>
               <l>Again shall bid old earth good-by—</l>
               <l>And, lo, the light! far heaven is nigh!</l>
               <l>New themes seraphic, Life divine,</l>
               <l>And bliss that wipes the tears of time</l>
               <l>Away, will enter, when they may,</l>
               <l>And bask in one eternal day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza" rhyme="aabbccddee">
               <l>'Tis writ on earth, on leaf and flower:</l>
               <l>Love hath one race, one realm, one power.</l>
               <l>Dear God! how great, how good Thou art</l>
               <l><ref target="#christian_science_foundation">To heal humanity's sore heart</ref>;</l>
               <l><ref target="#ice_fall">To probe the wound, then pour the balm</ref>—</l>
               <l>A life perfected, strong and calm.</l>
               <l>The dark domain of pain and sin</l>
               <l>Surrenders—Love doth enter in,</l>
               <l>And peace is won, and lost is vice:</l>
               <l>Right reigns, and blood was not its price.</l> 
            </lg>
            <note place="footnote">
               Pleasant View, Concord, N. H., <hi rend="italic">January, 1901.</hi>
            </note>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
   <standOff>
      <listPerson>
         <head>
            <s>Important People</s>
         </head>
         <person xml:id="mary_baker_eddy">
            <persName>
               <forename>Mary</forename>
               <surname>Baker</surname>
               <surname>Eddy</surname>
            </persName>
            <birth when="1821-07-16"> 16 July 1821 
               <placeName>
                  <settlement type="town">Bow</settlement>
                  <region type="state">New Hampshire</region>
               </placeName>
            </birth>
            <death when="1910-12-03"> 3 December 1910
               <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Newton</settlement>
                  <region type="state">Massachusetts</region>
               </placeName>
            </death>
            <note>Mary was married three times in her life, and went by many different names. These include Mary Baker, Mary Glover, Mary Patterson, Mary Eddy, and Mary Baker Eddy, the name most frequently associated with her.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="albert_baker">
            <persName>
               <forename>Albert</forename>
               <surname>Baker</surname>
            </persName>
            <birth when="1810-02-05"> 5 February 1810 
               <placeName>
                  <settlement type="town">Bow</settlement>
                  <region type="state">New Hampshire</region>
               </placeName>
            </birth>
            <death when="1841-10-17"> 17 October 1841
               <placeName>
                  <settlement type="town">Hillsborough</settlement>
                  <region type="state">New Hampshire</region>
               </placeName>
            </death>
            <note>Credited with teaching and mentoring Mary in youth.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="george_washington_glover">
            <persName>
               <forename>George</forename>
               <surname>Washington</surname>
               <surname>Glover</surname>
            </persName>
            <birth when="1811-08-02"> 2 August 1811</birth>
            <death when="1844-06-27"> 27 June 1844
               <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Wilmington</settlement>
                  <region type="state">North Carolina</region>
               </placeName>
            </death>
            <note>Mary's first husband, who died 6 months into their marriage of a fever.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="abigail_baker">
            <persName>
               <forename>Abigail</forename>
               <surname>Baker</surname>
            </persName>
            <birth when="1784-04-18"> 18 April 1784</birth>
            <death when="1849-11-21"> 21 November 1849</death>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="daniel_patterson">
            <persName>
               <forename>Daniel</forename>
               <surname>Patterson</surname>
            </persName>
            <death when="1896-08-14"> 14 August 1896
               <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Saco</settlement>
                  <region type="state">Maine</region>
               </placeName>
            </death>
            <note>Mary separated from Patterson in 1866, due to his desertion and adultery. Their divorce was finalized in 1873, 20 years after they married.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="asa_gilbert_eddy">
            <persName>
               <forename>Asa</forename>
               <surname>Gilbert</surname>
               <surname>Eddy</surname>
            </persName>
            <birth when="1832"> 1832</birth>
            <death when="1882-06-02"> 2 June 1882</death>
            <note>Mary met Asa when he was a student in her class on the teachings of Christian Science. He was her last husband, and they were married until his death.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="george_washington_glover_ii">
            <persName>
               <forename>George</forename>
               <surname>Washington</surname>
               <surname>Glover II</surname>
            </persName>
            <birth when="1844-09-12"> 12 September 1844
               <placeName>
                  <settlement type="town">Sanbornton</settlement>
                  <region type="state">New Hampshire</region>
               </placeName>
            </birth>
            <death when="1915-12-26"> 26 December 1915
               <placeName>
                  <settlement type="county">Lawrence</settlement>
                  <region type="state">South Dakota</region>
               </placeName>
            </death>
            <note>Mary and her son were separated from 1856 to 1879, as he was told she had died. He visited her occasionally after reuniting.</note>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="phineas_parkhurst_quimby">
            <persName>
               <forename>Phineas</forename>
               <surname>Parkhurst</surname>
               <surname>Quimby</surname>
            </persName>
            <birth when="1802-02-16"> 16 February 1802</birth>
            <death when="1866-01-16"> 16 January 1866
               <placeName>
                  <settlement type="city">Belfast</settlement>
                  <region type="state">Maine</region>
               </placeName>
            </death>
            <note>Quimby treated Mary of her physical ailments in the 60s, and the two discussed healing practices together.</note>
         </person>
      </listPerson>
      <listPlace>
         <head>
            <s>Important Places</s>
         </head>
         <place xml:id="Bow">
            <placeName>
               <settlement type="town">Bow</settlement>
               <region type="state">New Hampshire</region>
            </placeName>
            <note>Where the Baker Home is located, birthplace of Mary and her siblings.</note>
         </place>
         <place xml:id="Sanbornton">
            <placeName>
               <settlement type="town">Sanbornton Bridge</settlement>
               <region type="state">New Hampshire</region>
            </placeName>
            <note>Where the Baker family moved to during Mary's youth and continued to live throughout her adulthood.</note>
         </place>
         <place xml:id="Lynn">
            <placeName>
               <settlement type="town">Lynn</settlement>
               <region type="state">Massachusetts</region>
            </placeName>
            <note>Where Mary lived with Daniel Patterson, and established the Christian Science ptactice later in her life.</note>
         </place>
         <place xml:id="Newton">
            <placeName>
               <settlement type="town">Newton</settlement>
               <region type="state">Massachusetts</region>
            </placeName>
            <note>Where Mary died in 1910.</note>
         </place>
      </listPlace>
      <listEvent>
         <head>
            <s>Important Events</s>
         </head>
         <event xml:id="paitent_of_phineas" when="1862">
            <label>Patient of Phineas Quimby</label>
            <desc>After a prolonged period of physical ailments and sickness, Mary became a patient of Phineas Quimby in 1862, a doctor recommended by her then-husband Daniel Patterson. From 1862 to 1865, Mary and Quimby attempted to cure Mary without medicine, a process which Mary found religiously motivating. Mary produced notes as a result of her relationship with Quimby that associated physical healing with strong religious beliefs.</desc>
         </event>
         <event xml:id="ice_fall" when="1866-02-01">
            <label>Ice Fall</label>           
            <desc>In 1866 in Lynn, Massachusetts, Mary was critically injured after slipping on a path of ice. Mary's treatment was medical and spiritual - her doctor, Alvin Cushing, gave her small doses of morphine, which she would continue taking through the end of her life. However, Mary attributed her renewed health to faith, and her renewed belief in the New Testament and God's healing power gave her spiritual momentum which resulted in the foundation of the Christian Science religion.</desc>
         </event>
         <event xml:id="science_and_health_publication" when="1875-10-03">
            <label>Publication of Science and Health</label>
            <desc>In 1872, Mary began writing Science and Health, the foundational religious text for Christian Science, intended as a companion to the Christian Bible. The first edition of Science and Health was published in 1875, and the text continued to be revised and reprinted throughout Mary's lifetime. The work is comprised of fourteen primary chapters, a "Key to the Scriptures," and a Fruitage composed of testimonies.</desc>
         </event>
         <event xml:id="christian_science_foundation" when="1879-08-23">
            <label>Foundation of the Church of Christ, Scientist</label>
            <desc>In 1879, Mary and her fellow Christian Scientists voted to organize a Church around the teachings from Science and Health. The Church of Christ, Scientist, became an official religion in August of 1879, and in the years following, Mary and other founding members established official buildings, created missionary services, and offered classes through the Church. Christian Scientists believe in that physical healing can occur through spirituality and is still a religion today.</desc>
         </event>
         <event xml:id="poems_publication" when="1910">
            <label>Publication of Poems</label>
            <desc>Mary wrote poems throughout her lifetime, and a few months prior to her death in December of 1910, she requested that her writings be collected for publication. The collection was published through the Church of Christ, Scientist, a decision authorized by the trustees of Mary's will. The poems featured in this collection are taken from a various points in her life, and touch on subjects of religion, family, and nature.</desc>
         </event>
      </listEvent>
      <listBibl>
         <head>
            <s>Bibliography of Sources</s>
         </head>
         <bibl type="article" xml:id="chronology_of_events_source">
            “A Chronology of Events Surrounding the Life of Mary Baker Eddy.” The Mary Baker Eddy Library, www.marybakereddylibrary.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Mary_Baker_Eddy_Detailed_Annotated_Chronology_2018-12-10.pdf.  
         </bibl>
         <bibl type="website" xml:id="literary_devices_source">
            Glatch, Sean. “12 Literary Devices in Poetry: Identifying Poetic Devices.” Writers.Com, 16 June 2023, writers.com/literary-devices-in-poetry. 
         </bibl>
         <bibl type="article" xml:id="britannica_eddy_source">
            Gottschalk, Stephen. "Mary Baker Eddy". Encyclopedia Britannica, 29 Nov. 2023, https://www.britannica.com/biography/Mary-Baker-Eddy. Accessed 20 February 2024.
         </bibl>
         <bibl type="article" xml:id="wikipedia_eddy_source">
            “Mary Baker Eddy.” Wikipedia, Wikimedia Foundation,  en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary_Baker_Eddy#CITEREFSilberger1980. 
         </bibl>
         <bibl type="article" xml:id="mary_baker_eddy_library_source">
            “Mary Baker Eddy - Deep Read.” Mary Baker Eddy Library, 17 Feb. 2022, www.marybakereddylibrary.org/mary-baker-eddy/mary-baker-eddy-deep-read/. 
         </bibl>
         <bibl type="website" xml:id="christian_science_source">
            “The Christian Science Pastor.” Christian Science, www.christianscience.com/the-christian-science-pastor. Accessed 20 Feb. 2024. 
         </bibl>
      </listBibl>
   </standOff>
</TEI>
